All right, so let's get started. Today
we're going to be talking about some
very recent results in foundation
models. This lecture is not going to be
super focused on like an architecture
design that we've kind of been doing,
but more so a paradigm and we're going
to see some tricks and examples about
how to think about this. Um, most of the
results here are a year or less old
actually. So um, for those who I think
one of you asked about pins and said
that pins are getting old. Well, I
promise you this is not nothing here is
that old. So, okay. So, what have we
been doing so far on this design of
scientific machine learning? Well, we've
been looking at different architectures,
right? So, we looked at this this neural
OD where we basically learn a flow field
and we embed in our OD solver and we saw
with this architecture, one of the key
ideas was learning the gradients via the
adjoint method, right? So, we design an
OD for the back propagation and we
propagate. We also saw two forms of
neural operators kind of in detail. We
saw this dep depot deep on net where we
assumed some sort of separable kernel
and we tried to learn a truncated basis
mapping for our operator and then we saw
this fn where we essentially apply a
forier transform learn in frequency
space and then inverse forier transform
right and then okay we saw these
paradigms and highlighted a little bit
of of why we would use them and then we
saw okay what happens if we don't have
any data right so we have no data
what can we try to do? And we kind of
introduce this idea of a pin where we
basically encode the loss function with
a soft regularization term. And that
soft regularization term essentially
enforces our equation, right? And does
anyone remember what the problem was
with pins?
Just any problem.
Exactly. Okay. So you have to retrain
them for example every time you want to
do a new equation. Great. We also saw
that they require quite a bit of
fine-tuning, right? And so today we kind
of are going to ask a different
question. We're going to go into what
actually should we train on and how
should we sort of think about this this
training paradigm maybe at a broader
scale. Okay. All right. And so
for example, so far we've kind of been
tight in scope in what we're trying to
learn. So for example, we said, okay, a
neurode is going to learn one dynamical
system, but you can't take it, you know,
one dynamical system for a robot and
then go try to use it on a fluid
mechanics problem, right? And we saw
okay neural operators they might be
trained on a family of PTEES. So for
example on the advection diffusion
equation but they're not going to be
useful for Schroinger's equation or wave
PTEs right and we also saw that we might
have a bunch of different parameters on
those neural operators and those
parameters are going to really change
how our PTE behaves. Okay. And so the
idea is and okay yes we saw for example
pin needs retraining as our friend said
here. So the idea is what if we wanted
one model that kind of works across all
of these different problems. So we can
train on batch diffusion PTEs Navier
Stokes Burger's equation and this
paradigm is not new. I think that's kind
of the chat GPT paradigm and we'll we'll
make some connections. So how are we
going to do this? Well, around let's say
2018, maybe even a little bit earlier,
the way that NLP was working at the time
was that people were designing a
specific model for a specific task.
Okay? So, you might design one neural
network that gives me the sentiment of a
sentence. So, how happy, sad, mad, angry
the sentence is, right? Another one
might extract important features. So,
this is NE stands for named entity
recognition. Essentially what this is is
okay I have a sentence you know Bob
jumped out of the tree it might
recognize okay the name Bob is the
subject of the noun and for example a
tree is where he jumped out of and
lastly people also had models okay let's
say for translation so you know I have
Deutski's crime and punishment in
Russian can I translate that to English
okay
what happened basically well as you guys
know around let's say 2018 2019 a series
of models came out called BERT have any
of you guys heard of BERT models
okay actually a few of you right so BERT
at the time was invented at Google and
it was basically this idea that we could
do things from sort of a pre-training
standpoint and ultimately this got spun
out into what you guys know today as GPT
so for example I think GPT code GPT2
code is fully publicly available
actually um so you can implement it
yourself but the idea was okay GPT we're
going to stand for generative
pre-trained transformer right so the
idea is okay we pre-train it on a corpus
of data and then later we're going to
let's say fine-tune or adjust depending
on our task all right and so the goal is
okay instead of you know having to train
an individual model each time we train
one model once at scale and then let's
say fine-tuning is usually easy in some
way all
And so nowadays in machine learning
basically everyone is trying to do some
form of this this foundation model.
Okay. Whether you work on robots,
computer vision or in this case
scientific machine learning. Okay. And
so what we're going to look at is some
examples about how this recipe can kind
of be implemented and also why you know
natural language processing is actually
a really easy case study for foundation
models compared to let's say physics or
PDS.
And so at the end of the day hopefully
you'll have some idea of what the world
looks like right now on can we have a
GPT for some PTE architecture.
Okay. Uh I assume that most of you have
heard of foundation models before given
the popularity, but it actually was
pretty recently, you know, 21 where
people have defined a foundation model,
right? And this idea is very simple.
We're going to pre-train on a huge
amount of data. The data quality needs
to be good, but let's say, you know, it
can be a very diverse kind. Okay? And
then we're going to you know downstream
for for our target tasks for example you
know solving the Navier Stokes PTE or
let's say the advction diffusion PD
we're going to do some sort of
adaptation okay some sort of fine-tuning
right and the key is that okay our data
needs to be very diverse so the
underlying principle here is that
there's some sort of there's some value
in let's say learning
a Navi learning from Navier Stokes
equations that can help the Helm Holtz
PTE later which is not obvious right
like it's not obvious that if I trained
on a bunch of data from let's say news
reporters that's actually useful for
let's say making haikus right it's the
same kind of idea here so essentially
there's some structure in physical
systems that's universal
okay
then we're going to consider adaptation
so how do we adapt
I think the easiest way is actually you
don't. So that's called zero shot
tuning. Basically you don't update the
weights at all and you see how well you
do on a new task. And this is sort of
the holy grail. For example, in time
series analysis, everybody tries to
claim that LLMs are what we call zerosot
time series forecasters, which just
basically means they can predict the
future time series. Well, and it turns
out that's actually not so easy. As you
can imagine, zeros is a pretty tricky
paradigm. But what does considerably
help is something called fshot or
incontext learning. So for example,
imagine I have this huge corpus of PTEs
and I want to do something let's say
with the Helmholds PTE. So I might pick
three parameters for my Helmholds PTE
and three initial conditions, you know,
nine solves with my classical solver.
And okay, it'll take let's say a day.
But if I show those solves to my
pre-trained model, I might save, you
know, 100x on training time later. Okay.
And lastly, of course, we can do
fine-tuning. So fine-tuning, you guys
heard of Laura before.
Yeah, same people. Okay. Yeah,
fine-tuning most commonly done with with
something like Laura where you have a
huge number of weights and you need to
update them sort of in a in a smart way.
But let's say you have a small corpus of
of training data. Let's say 200
examples. Okay. So these are kind of our
three different paradigms for adapting.
We need a broad set of training data.
And this whole sort of idea is is
wrapped in this word called foundation
model.
Okay. And so as you can imagine it's not
so easy to adapt foundation models to
every problem in physics. It's actually
much harder than what you would imagine
in NLP. And the reason is that there's
not as much structure for example as
there is in language that is universal.
So we talked about for example Navia
Stokes on 3D takes 10 billion points
give or take.
If I want to sort of modify that and
work on let's say a regular sized grid
you know a square grid I would have to
let's say resolve right we have some
sort of different geometry and so
whereas in you know NLP we just have
this unifying token of a word right or
even a sentence let's say for example
it's pretty consistent throughout let's
say if we stay in the English language
we always have a consistent token but
the way you encode the heat equation
on let's say a square grid compared to
the Navia Stokes is very different and
it's also different from let's say we
get some sensor data from weather which
is typically represented in a point
cloud. So the point is that these data
representations are not uniform and
there's no kind of concept of what a
token is in physics. We'll sort of talk
about this more later. Okay. And so
as you can also imagine kind of one
thing I I haven't really told you about
too much is we we talked a little bit
about chaotic systems. And so if you
change one token in a sentence, okay,
95% of you will actually still read the
sentence ignoring that token change. But
if we change let's say the viscosity
parameter in a in a PTE, we know that
like for example chaotic systems will
yield very different trajectories. Okay.
And so this this is also a little bit
tricky. It's a more diverse
representation.
All right. And so let's take a step back
and kind of go into what the training
pipeline might look like for a PTE.
Nowadays there is more and more data
sets coming out. For example, this well
data set. There's also a data set called
PTE bench that just sort of take a bunch
of solves let's say from our national
lab solvers and put them together. Okay.
And so what you might do is you might,
you know, concatenate all these data
sets and build, let's say, some large
pre-trained corpus.
Then we're going to pre-train this
model. This part is a little bit tricky
because it's not so simple how we're
going to build this data set and how
we're going to kind of design this
model. We'll talk about this, right?
Because for example, if PTE bench solved
all their PTEs looking for a target time
of let's say 10 seconds and let's say
the well here solved their PTEs for 15
seconds. How do you use both of those
data? You have to be a little bit smart,
right? Because one of them you have more
time that you solve for, right?
The next thing we talked about is
adaptation and then deployment, right?
And so the kind of cost here that we're
selling is is very simple actually to
the FNO. You have some offline cost
that's very expensive upfront. So this
pre-training cost, you can imagine it
might take a week to pre-train, you
know, one to 8 billion parameter model
and then it might take two hours to
fine-tune later. Okay. And we'll see
kind of what this scaling law looks like
an idea.
So any questions about what the paradigm
for foundation models is right. So we
pre-train on a big courses we're going
to fine-tune later.
Great. All right. And so I want to start
with a a very simple example of one of
the first papers. This came out in 23
about foundation models. Okay. And so
what they consider here we have an
action diffusion equation. Okay. with
parameters K and new and a source
parameter F. And so what they did is
they said, okay, let's take snapshots of
FK and new almost as images. We're going
to pass them to a neural operator and
we're going to get some set of outputs U
the target solution of the PTE at some
later time.
And then they down they basically said
okay this works great for you know our
train set but let's consider for example
values of FK and new that we haven't
seen before. Okay so this was kind of
what you were asking about if we have
some parameter right in the pin and they
showed okay this this pre-trained neural
operator basically if you fine-tune it
and we'll see how much fine-tuning you
need you can do pretty much the same as
if you trained from scratch. actually
you can do a little bit better without
the same cost of training again.
All right. And so the problem here is
three-fold.
Like I mentioned, we had different
geometries, different scales. We had
chaotic dynamics. We also don't know
what a token is. Okay? And we have no
huge corpus of data. Okay? So for
example, you guys know GPT is basically
trained on the whole internet. And here
we don't have a whole internet
equivalent for solutions of PTEs. Let's
say for example, okay, it's kind of an
ongoing study, but you can imagine how
easy is it for you to create a sentence.
It's pretty easy, right? You know, you
can make your Facebook post or Instagram
post in five minutes. To solve a PTE, it
takes a quite a bit of time. And so this
this corpus here is a huge limitation
actually that we have to the scale of
our problem. and we'll see kind of some
tricks that we can do to sort of build a
bigger data set with the data we have.
We also talked about okay we have no
idea of what some token means. What is a
token? Not really obvious here. For
example, what we're going to use
essentially is these parameters that we
saw on the previous slide as tokens
and then chaotic dynamics. So I talked
about this fact that physics can be
chaotic, right? So we have these
trajectories. you change some small
parameter and they diverge
significantly. All right. And so
up until the last year and a half and
there's quite a few startups actually
betting on this. Foundation models
really haven't been shown to work for
physical problems. Okay? And we'll see
where they do work and where they don't
work. But it's really still an open
question today.
Um, and maybe you know by the end of the
the lecture, one second. By the end of
the lecture, you'll believe that they
have some promise. Go ahead.
Sorry. For what?
For NLP.
Okay. So, like I was saying, so back in
the day, everybody trained individual
models for each NLP task, right? So for
example, I may train a model that is
let's say very I'm a stock broker. Okay,
I want to predict the output of stocks.
So I might train a model that's very
good at reading the news. Okay, but then
you know I want that model to maybe work
in some other environment. Let's say,
you know, I'm a biologist. I want it to
be interested in helping me design drugs
for pharma. So what it will do is it'll
read my design docs, let's say, for
example, and give me an idea. So these
two used to be separate but then the
whole chat GBT paradigm basically said
that this is the wrong way to do this.
That's where it kind of came out of.
Okay. And then would you agree that GPT
is pretty great today?
Why did you need multiple models? Oh, I
mean that's kind of what people are it's
it's nice to say that in hindsight,
right? But like if you are two reasons
first, okay, you're 2018, you have
significantly less compute than you have
today actually. So building a 8 billion
parameter model, you don't really get
the emergent effects yet, right? So back
then a huge model was in the millions of
parameters, right? So that might be why
you can only do certain tasks because
you can't scale that much. Basically the
whole NLP idea is about scale saying as
you scale more things look better. But
if you're in 2018 you didn't have the
scale that we have today. So that's kind
of where why why people did things like
that. But it was it was six years ago.
No, eight years ago. Right. So
both both. So, okay. So, so the first
paradigm that you're describing is
called zero shot. Okay. So, it works on
something it's never seen. The second
paradigm you're describing is sort of
this fine-tuning paradigm. Okay. where
and it's also it can be in two kind of
flavors. So the first flavor could be
you want it to work on parameters but it
still has the same PD structure, right?
The second is you could want it to work
on PTEs that it hasn't seen before. The
latter flavor is where people are going.
Okay.
Yeah, I think so. But text does have
problems where for they have their own
unique set of challenges. So you might
say, okay, we have sensor measurements
and those sensor measurements are noisy.
Text can argue, okay, we have this world
where context matters, for example.
Another thing text might have is that,
you know, you have the word u spelled
three different ways, right? So like
it's spelled yo u or it could just be
spelled with the letter u. That's
actually a little bit tricky to
distinguish, right? So yes, I would say
that you you definitely have noise in
that sense, but you could think of noise
also in a text way, in a similar way.
Yeah. But yeah.
Okay. All right. So the main one we're
going to look at today was this study
that came out in NERURPS in 2024
called Poseidon and it's from a group in
Zurich that actually works a little bit
on neural operators but but not too much
and the idea is kind of answering your
question. They wanted to ask not just if
you could do parameter transfer but if
you could do equation to equation
transfer so in this case they're going
to train on some set of fluid dynamics.
Okay, let's say 15 different ones. Okay,
different variations of the Navia Stokes
equations essentially. And they're going
to ask whether or not this model that's
trained on fluid dynamics can work for
let's say advection diffusion PTE,
right? So different PTE designs
completely. All right. Um and so the
whole kind of idea here is kind of
summarized in this this this sort of
diagram. So basically you have some set
of fluid flows uh compressible or
incompressible. If you don't know what
these are, just assume that they are a
set of PTEs that have pretty rich
dynamics and you train just on these
PDEs and then you want to see okay, how
well do we do on out of distribution
downstream task that is completely new
PDS okay and we'll go into detail here
in a minute but for here you can see
okay imagine that you compare their
architecture to just a flatout FNO you
see that as we see more fine-tuned
examples we do better which is you as
you would expect. We'll talk about this
in detail. Okay. And so the kind of
weird or not natural part is like why
does a model trained on Navia Stokes
tell us something about other PTEEs?
Okay. And I kind of want you guys to
maybe spend 60 seconds sort of talking
about this. So like why is fluids a good
idea? Why do they choose fluids let's
say? And and do you think this will
actually work in the long run? So spend
60 seconds talking with your partner and
we'll reconvene.
So I can be your partner. Okay.
There we go. All right. So, hopefully
you guys had some conversation. So, do
you guys think this should like is this
intuitive? Advantages, disadvantages,
ideas? So, we had a a little group over
here. Some of you thought it wasn't
intuitive at all. Yeah. What do you guys
think? Maybe we could go over here. Our
favorite friends. I see you guys have
moved back to hide from me. How about
you guys? What did you guys talk about,
right? But what if you don't use it on a
fluid dynamics problem? Does it make any
sense? It doesn't make sense, right? No.
No.
What if there was some argument that
fluid dynamics tells us something
fundamental about all PDS? Would you
agree with that argument?
You're hesitant.
You're not convinced.
Yeah, I don't think it's obvious either
actually. And so that's basically what
these guys tried to set out to figure
out. So 2024 we've seen probably chatbt
not widely adopted but in the CS
community it's well known and so these
guys basically said like can I do the
same thing but for for their area of
expertise machine learning right once
this loads we'll talk about it
okay and so here might be some reasons
why this this would be valuable. So we
agree that fluids are well understood.
We have some clean data. We know how to
do them. And you would agree that fluids
have rich rich dynamics, right? So we
talked about they're chaotic. They have
shocks. These types of things. Okay? And
you know we have a bunch of operators to
learn actually. Let's say in this case
they chose six operators. Okay.
Why would it not make sense? Well, it's
exactly what you said. Yeah. Then it
doesn't make sense that this would work
for some elliptic PTE, right? And the
analog that we kind of talked about is
you you pre-trained on news and you
tried to work on let's say poetry or
something like that. So it's it's not
obvious unless news and poetry have some
underlying structure they agree on, for
example, language, right? And so it's
not obvious that this will work kind of
off the top of of your head, but it
turns out it will work. And the first
thing we need to sort of think about is
how to solve that data problem. Okay?
And so basically imagine that we have a
bunch of pairs, a bunch of snapshots
from our solver and we need to collect
more data somehow from the snapshots and
and I promise that you know GPT is
trained on the whole internet. You can
imagine that's quite a bit of data. So
in physics we have a limited data set
and so what might you do? Well you might
build this sort of mapping. So you might
say okay an input output pair for my
pre-trained corpus is the mapping from
t0 to t1. It's also the mapping from T0
to T2, T0 to T3, so on and so forth
based on all my snapshots, right? And so
this for example, if I had, you know,
this would build me capital T data sets,
right? Or capital T pairs. Okay? And I
can do the same thing with T1 for all
future times. So my input now is going
to be the data at T1. So that is the PD
snapshot at T1. And my output will be
let's say an example of T2, an example
of T3, so on and so forth. I can do this
over and over and over again. And let's
say for example I had five data pairs. I
actually turned five snapshots
into essentially 15.
Okay. So this is a little bit of way
okay you might imagine I had now
building this corpus and there's one
little trick that we have. So for k
snapshots you can essentially do the
common cominatorics problem and you get
basically k square data pairs. Okay, but
the thing that we didn't talk about is
that these snapshots obviously are going
to depend on how much distance is
between the data pairs, right? And so if
we're going to build this data set, we
might need to encode this distance into
our model. For example, choosing the
model to have delta t as input. All
right, so this is the first little trick
that we can do to build out a lot more
data. It was introduced in this Poseidon
paper. It's I think pretty
straightforward.
Okay. The second thing is that what are
we going to think about our
architecture? And there's a pretty big
deep dive that we could go down in this
direction. But we're going to just stay
present here and do something very
simple. But we're going to say that we
have a bunch of transformers and those
transformers get that input snapshot
some TK and they output that output
snapshot at whatever my target time is
and they get let's say at every layer
some delta t and we'll talk about this
design about how we should feed in these
snapshots because that's kind of the
main point of this paper actually. They
take a pre-existing transformer model,
not pre-existing but like a an
architecture that's sort of wellknown
and they ask about how to kind of
augment our data. Okay. And so how are
we going to do this? It turns out it's
in a pretty unintuitive way. So
essentially what we have is in each
transformer we're going to have a layer
norm, right? I assume you're all
familiar with this layer norm.
Basically, this ensures that our
gradients don't blow up. And the idea is
the following. Okay, let's say our input
vector from our previous layer to the
layer norm is V. I'm going to normalize
V based on its mean and variance. Okay,
with two parameters, let's call them
alpha and beta. Okay, so this is a
standard layer norm architecture. I
think most of you are familiar with it.
Alpha and beta sort of control the the
scaling and shift of the norm. Okay. And
so what did Poseidon do? Well, they
actually just did this very simple thing
in the layer norm. They basically
changed alpha and beta these parameters
to be functions of delta t. Okay. And
then for example, you have a shift on
how large your layer norm is based on
this delta t.
This is kind of a weird trick. uh it
doesn't actually make sense to me at
least why how you would come up with
this idea off the top of my head but
essentially what they're saying is that
the size of your normalization okay
should depend on how many steps you're
trying to predict in the future all
right anyone have any intuition for why
this may work
yeah I also didn't have any at the same
time it turns out basically is that you
need to inject this delta t at every
layer. And we'll see why in a second.
And this is just a very simple way to do
it, but there's about a 50 different
others that they did that also work.
Okay. Okay. And so, like I was saying,
why do we need to do this? It turns out
that essentially by reminding the neural
network at each transformer layer, you
can actually get better performance than
let's say if you concatenated your input
with delta t at the start.
So this is a a unique little finding.
I'm not sure exactly
what to make of it to be honest with you
guys because there's like about a
billion different ways I could decide to
inject this delta t that I think would
work. Um, but this is the way they chose
and I think it's kind of a little trick
that you probably haven't seen before
that I thought was interesting.
Any questions here?
Yes. Let's go in the front and then
we'll go in the back. Go ahead.
So the positional encoding is typically
over x in this case and so like okay the
way they define the data set for example
the positional encoding will be u at a
bunch of points with where I've written
this dot represents a bunch of points in
x and so then that will be augmented
with a set of positional encodings that
learnable. Okay. But what isn't sort of
encoded is actually this this time. So
they don't treat the time as like you
know how you would do positional
encoding for a token for an NLP. They
don't treat it like that actually. Okay.
They treat time as sort of your input
and output and that's it. Flat. And so
the way they kind of do this is Yeah.
It's but it's weird, right? Like why
wouldn't you just treat time as a
position encoding? I agree. I'm not sure
to be honest with you. I I assume it
didn't work. Yeah, but good question in
the back.
I think that could be probably where
it's inspired from. I'm not so familiar
with the adaptive layer norm idea in
diffusion models to be honest. We can
talk after but okay actually it makes
sense. So diffusion model you're
basically iterating a bunch of times
with some small time step adding and
denoising and I guess they add this sort
of delta t in that
I see. Yeah, I think then probably
that's where it's from if I had to
guess. Yeah.
Okay. All right. And so how does this
actually work? Well, let's say, okay, we
picked 15 downstream tasks. Some of
them, everything I'll show you today in
images is not a fluid. Okay. And
basically what they do is they take this
Poseidon which was just trained on let's
say you know this huge corpus of
fluid dynamic data and then they're
going to slowly give it a small number
of data from the actual PTE that they
want to learn. Let's say that data is
generated by varying an initial
condition or parameter.
And then they're going to compare about
this against an FNL which was trained
from scratch. Okay. Basically, this
tells you how much effect that
pre-training has, right? And you know
the problems are exactly the same as you
might imagine. So we have six PTE but
the exact initial conditions are
different. So this would be that
parameter modification and then they
also consider the case where we have new
PTEES, right? Okay. And so what was the
the headline? And we'll look at some
qualitative examples in a second, but
the headline was that it takes about 20
samples for the largest Poseidon model
about a 1 billion model. We'll see to
match what FNO does when it takes 1,024
samples. Okay, so the idea here is that
okay, if I have this pre-trained model
and I try to start training it from n
equals 1, it's only going to take 20
different PTE samples to do well
compared to if I've trained it from
scratch. So basically saying that this
pre-trained MA model actually helped us
for some weird reason on the downstream
task. Okay. And so here's an example of
what this looks like. So here on the
left I have the ground truth solution of
an elliptic PTE. Okay. And here is
Poseidon the pre-trained models output
as I fine-tune it slowly and slowly over
more models. And you see at first it
actually sucks. Like it's exactly as you
would imagine. Uh why would something
that's trained on fluids work on an
elliptic and it and it doesn't, right?
But it only takes fewer samples down the
line to fine-tune.
That's the essential argument that they
made here. Okay. And the next question
you may ask and it's a common question
is that okay maybe I just needed more
compute like how much does that benefit
my system just like in NLP. And so they
explored this problem with three models
they call it tiny, big and large. Okay.
And here's exactly what their training
error is going to look like over the
whole corpus. So there's not many epochs
here, but it's a huge corpus, 77,000
trajectories. And so what you see is
okay, the smallest model does not do
nearly as well as let's say, you know,
the largest model. And the left is the
training, the right is your testing
error. Okay,
so what does this tell us? Well, it
tells us the scale still does matter.
And scale really matters when we
consider pre-training. Okay, so we need
a larger model.
The next finding that they sort of
investigated is actually a pretty
interesting one is how much does data
matter? And it turns out like the
question is does more data help? Does
the type of data help? What matters
more? Okay. And so this would imagine
you know it's very important for a
physicist, right? Because we talked
about how data was expensive to get,
right? Right? We even did that little
trick to build kar data. And here's what
they found. So on the left, these are
both on the same scale. On the left,
this is for example the median relative
L1 error over all of the downstream
tasks. Okay? So as they show more
trajectories of the downstream task,
this is the sort of error. And what they
said is, okay, here's what happens if
you pre-train on the full data set. you
do, you know, pretty well. Okay, it's
log scale. And then if you just train on
1/8 of the data set, what are you giving
up? How much are you giving up? And
you're actually not giving up too too
much. This is probably at max one
magnitude difference. Okay, then they
asked, okay, but what if I only train on
half of the data set? It turns out I
repeat the same results as the full one.
Okay, but then they said, okay, what if
I take out one class of the PTEES? Okay,
so I don't show it for example that
fifth operator and it and it turns out
this this diversity basically
also significantly limits your problems.
And so what is the the the result here?
Well, the result is the following. So
once you have enough data, okay, so
between full and a half data set, we see
no difference. the diversity of the data
set starts to really matter. Okay, so
for example, this data set's still the
same size, but you lost half the
results.
This is kind of a a nice result
actually. It's it's one that's
encouraging for physicists or or people
in scientific machine learning because
we have a problem with data, but we can
choose how we generate it typically. So,
it's kind of an opposite of NLP where
they don't actually have a problem with
data. they can train on the whole
internet. But they didn't choose how
they generated that internet data
actually, right? It was generated sort
of out of by someone else. Okay. All
right. And the third lesson is is how
good is fine-tuning. And what I'm going
to show you here is exactly what you
would expect. So in this case, let's
just consider FNL and let's just
consider the Poseidon large and big
models. Ignore you can ignore the other
architectures. Okay, just just for this
purpose. And so what we see is okay,
this is what FNO looks like trained from
scratch. Okay, before this this is 64.
Before 64, it's basically off the screen
and it ruins the whole point.
And what you see is that okay, this is
just fine-tuning and we actually
outperform the FNO when trained from
scratch. And this is kind of a a
shocking result because basically what
it says is that this pre-trained model
can actually do better from scratch on
the same number of trajectories when
it's given physics that it's not
necessarily
relevant to the problem, right? So this
kind of answers your question about like
why does this work? Well, it turns out
it kind of doesn't work in the
beginning, but it gives you this sort of
prior that's a good set of weights to
sort of learn quickly. That's kind of
the idea. Um, yeah, this idea is
actually not new. It's been developed
for a long time. Have any of you guys
heard about the lottery ticket
hypothesis paper?
It's basically this idea that certain
sets of weights are much better to start
training from than others. And finding
these sets of weights that are good is
equivalent to finding a lottery ticket.
But once you find that lottery ticket,
you should just reuse it over and over
and over again. Okay. All right. And so
yeah, the question is, okay, uh I have a
question for you all. So imagine I was
given this set of pairs, okay? And I was
given it up to this kar some final time.
All right? And at inference, I ask you
for some t that's much larger than seen
during training. All right? Because you
know, we're building this foundation
model. It's supposed to solve every
problem downstream, but you know, our
architecture didn't see very long
horizon correlations, right? So any
ideas about how we would sort of work
this out and and maybe you could talk to
the person next to you, but I would say
think about some ideas from what they
did in NLP to generate long sequences of
text. All right, so take 60 seconds and
we'll come back to it.
Great. All right. Any ideas here? Maybe
not from you guys because we we kind of
got there over here. What did you guys
Any ideas? Yeah. What's up?
Yep. So essentially we could do it in an
auto reggressive format. That's exactly
what you're saying, right? So you take
the first k steps and you pass it
through the model and you would get some
output U1 and then you treat that as an
input back to your model again. You can
do this over and over and over again.
And so this auto reggressive design is
is pretty common I would say whenever
you have large time dependencies. Okay.
And I think the advantages or
disadvantages are pretty clear. So for
example, the advantage is that you do
get some long horizon output without
retraining. The disadvantage is of
course that your errors are going to
compound every time you sort of do this,
right? So if we have some small error in
U1, that's going to lead to some little
bit bigger error in U2 and so on. So you
can't really do this too too far. And
actually, this is a problem with all
auto reggressive models, including in
natural language processing. And that's
kind of
a hot topic actually about whether or
not things should be auto reggressive
and turns out they kind of moved away
from this but this is the idea and so
the question is does this work and how
good does it work and so what they did
is they compared these two models okay
on a set of number of trajectories here
on the left and on the right okay and
these are for two different problems
okay and so what we see is that or sorry
not two different problems on the left
is the training problem and on the right
is actually the testing problem and so
you actually get this really really
weird phenomenon really weird so on the
left your FNO when done auto
reggressively actually trains better
than if you try to just learn the long
time dependency directly okay whereas
okay your Poseidon when you're
fine-tuning it turns out that it does
better again auto reggressively during
training but when you try to learn
directly there's sort of a a loss right
so during training it's clear that auto
reggressive works better you agree
but during testing it turns out that the
direct method really looks better that
is somehow in this training set we were
overfitting a little bit with the auto
reggressive model and you see there's a
huge magnitude of drop off between
training and testing for both models
Okay. And so does the auto reggressive
design actually work? This plot would
tell you don't. Okay. So just something
to keep in mind because we were talking
about okay this you know transformer can
work for very long time dependency for
any problem you want. It's sort of an
overselling. Um it turns out it's
actually not so easy to do this.
Okay. So a little recap of this this
first scientific PTE model. We took 15
tasks. Nine are downstream. Six are
fluid dynamics which were our
pre-trained corpus. Okay. And four
design choices really mattered. So the
first one is that they did a
pre-training on fluid dynamics. And it
turns out that fluid dynamics is the
right type of PTE problem to do
pre-training on. So for example, if you
tried to do pre-training on advection
diffusion and then go to fluid dynamics,
they found it didn't work. Okay? So
that's what kind of we were talking
about.
The second thing is that
we need some way to generate more data
and we have these snapshots but
basically they introduce this little
trick okay to make every single snapshot
pair training example and then they
introduce this sort of delta t in the
layer norm. Okay. And so what we need to
kind of think about is it's important to
design our architecture with some
physical principles in mind from our
data set. And lastly, we saw that if
they fine-tune on each downstream's
task, we actually did better than let's
say FNO trained on that test directly,
right? And so the three lessons are
scaling is going to help. We care a lot
about that data set diversity and we saw
that fine-tuning really works.
And so the kind of surprise of this is
this was the first result published that
I know of that actually did this sort of
learning from let's say fluid dynamics
to other PTEs and it's it's not that old
you know two years ago.
All right since then new approaches have
came out. So this approach is called
walrus very similar idea. Has anyone
heard of walrus?
Anyone heard of Polymathic?
Okay, it's a small little startup that
probably offers quite a bit of money for
you to join. And it was invented by this
girl, her name is Shirley Hoe. She was a
physicist actually who's kind of into
machine learning. And so what did they
do? So they first have about double the
size of the model. Okay, so remember the
largest model we saw for Poseidon was
600 million parameters. Here it's a 1.3
billion parameter model. The second
thing they did is that they didn't
restrict their initial corpus to just
fluid dynamics. Okay. So they took a
bunch of problems all over and they
built a set of data sets a set of data
based on these you know problems from a
bunch of different domains. Okay. And
the key is that they had varying domains
here. So in the previous example we
talked about okay the tokens being
inputed into the neural network as just
a set of X of eyes and it turns out
those were all on nice square grids.
Here they actually considered grids that
are you know an air foil flow or a
circle oval random shapes. Okay.
And the key thing they introduced is
they said that instead of trying to do
this t all at once as a snapshot, we're
just going to predict small changes at
every time step and then we're going to
use this auto reggressive roll out.
Okay, the same idea as kind of a neural
OD, right? So a neural OD kind of
predicts the vector field you're going
to go from every single place. And when
we put it into an OD solver, we take
really really small steps.
And the last thing we're going to see is
that they introduced this convol stride
convolutional stride modulation.
It sounds fancy. It's really simple. And
the reason they had to do this is
because they changed the domain of their
input. We'll see what that looks like.
So what is this idea? Basically they
said, okay, we have a bunch of different
resolution grids. So you might have, for
example, data sets with, you know, 64
cubed, a 3D data set, 64 points per
grid. Or you might have something that's
non-symmetric, right? So, you know, a 2D
data set, but over the Y-axis we have a
fourth of the number of points. Okay?
And basically what they said is that
we're going to pass all of these through
a convolution. And the convolution
essentially is going to choose a stride
to map us to 32 by 32 tokens.
Okay, nothing complicated here. It's
actually the same idea from vision. So
they they'll do something similar. And
okay, how you choose these strides
depends on what your input was, but
essentially they designed an encoder for
all of their input data. Okay, so that
they all get to this same
representation.
So what is this problem solving that the
other one didn't? Well, the other one
always considered let's say 256 x 256
grits.
All right. And so the idea is okay, this
does this work? Well, we'll see in a
minute. The second thing that they did,
okay, so now we can handle
multi-resolutions.
The second thing that they did is they
said we actually have some invariance
for physics.
So for example, if we consider a 2D
physical system, okay, I can rotate that
physical system four times, let's say
for example, over my square. And
actually the physics should be the same
as long as I rotate the output
accordingly. Okay. Okay. So now I have a
lot more data right because I have these
k snapshots. I can get k square data out
of that. And then for each k square data
I can do four rotations matching this.
And this is actually an idea that comes
from these sort of equivariant neural
networks if you guys have ever heard of
them.
All right. And of course you need to do
this in the right way. So you need to
think about your PTE to actually do this
properly. Say you need some background
knowledge. So for example, how you
rotate adction diffusion might be a
little bit different than how you're
going to rotate a couple Navier Stokes
equations.
Okay. Another little trick that they do
is everything is inputed into their
neural network in a 3D domain, but they
have plenty of 2D snapshots.
So what they do is they add this fake
Z-axis where they just repeat the
snapshots Z times.
So for example, if I have a 2D image and
then I repeat the 2D image, you know, K
times, I'll have a 2D by K vector. Make
sense?
And then they do rotations on 3D.
So you actually get eight permutations.
So this is all to just build more data
from what you have essentially.
All right. And here's what happened. So
basically what you can see is that up
here is our ground truth on an invection
diffusion example. Okay. All they did
was scale our data and added
multi-resolution. Those are the two
initial ads compared to Walrus. And we
see that Walrus actually starts to
introduce some weird error or sorry not
Walrus Poseidon starts to introduce some
weird errors. So for example here at the
end we see that it doesn't even capture
the dynamics correctly at all. Okay just
sort of rotated and here you can see
okay what the actual error looks like.
So basically what this company did is
they took Walrus and they did two
things. We we they found a new trick to
add more data and they scaled the
parameter size. All right. And it turns
out this helps a lot.
What else could you do? Well,
they also compared everything to
essentially see if they helped over long
horizons. All right. And so this is kind
of an example of that. Let's just
consider, okay, Poseidon is in blue and
this walrus is in red. Okay. And here
what they're comparing essentially is
how far away your initial step is
because remember they're they're
actually learning the residual. Okay. So
what I mean by one step is that you only
move delta t units, very small time.
Okay, for t= 1 to 10, you're going to
move a little bit farther. And then for
the last case, it's t from 10 to 30. So
you move really far. Okay, from your
initial condition.
And it turns out that this walrus method
actually does pretty well about
I would say 20% improvement over the
Poseidon method that we saw before.
Okay, the other two examples let's
ignore for now. All right,
so basically this group that's you know
raised quite a bit of money for their
startup has put in that that if we can
find a way to make more data we instead
learn residuals
and we consider multi-resolution cases
with a really simple convolution we can
get about 20% improve in performance.
This paper actually came out just in
December. Okay. And so it has not been
peer- reviewviewed. I will I will give
you a little stipulation, but that's the
idea.
Okay. And so what was the themes here?
So the themes are pretty standard. So
what I said is okay, we care about how
much we can pull out of our data and we
do these little tricks like repeating
and stuff like that.
Okay. The second theme is that
transformers are going to scale but we
do need to consider for example working
with our data in the right way. So we
needed to encode that delta t we needed
to consider the multi-resolution point
and we did find that this odd paradigm
where we train on something unrelated to
our problem is actually related. Okay,
which is the same thing we actually see
in NLP. All right,
the last thing I want to kind of finish
with guys is is some scaling laws. So in
NLP when it first started, everyone was
kind of trying to predict how fast is
this thing going to scale? That is if I
have more compute, more data, so on, how
much better is my model going to be? And
there's an old paper in 23 that kind of
answered this. Okay, so how much do we
get from each component?
And when does this pre-training maybe
stop working? You know, you can imagine
we get some diminishing marginal
returns. We actually start needing to
find on our task. Okay. And so I give
you the paper in the slides, but the
idea is that they just defined a small
FNO and they do a couple toy examples.
Okay. So it's an older paper. So what
did they find? So the first thing they
asked is how much does fine-tuning help
compared to pre-training? And in this
problem, all they do is they consider
parameters. Okay? So in pre-training
they're considering parameters between 0
2 and one. And the downstream task is
from 0 2 to 0 point 4. So it's within
the data set. Okay. And here's what they
see. Well, they see that okay, if you
train from scratch, for example, it
might take you 32k samples to retrieve
an error 10us 2. But if you have
pre-trained, you're going to get it in
one shot when the distribution matches.
Exactly what you would imagine. Okay.
The next thing they said is they asked
how much does the size of the problem
matter. Okay. And so everything dotted
here, okay, is from scratch and
everything lined is from pre-trained,
okay, and the green to purple goes from
64 really small model to a size of 256
million parameters. It's just an FNL
architecture, okay? And what you see is
scaling. You see good scaling from each
environment, but you do see a sort of a
diminishing marginal returns compared to
the beginning.
So in other words, scaling matters.
Okay? And it turns out it's really going
to matter. And this actually gives us an
estimate about how good scaling is. And
so if you did a similar example, okay,
in natural language processing, what you
would see is that the scaling is
actually much stronger.
Meaning that as you get larger models,
the gap between these guys widen. All
right.
And then the last thing is how well can
you do out of distribution from your
downstream training. Okay. And so in
this case what I have on the left is
actually pretty close from pre-training
to down out of stream. So their
parameters they trained on was from 1 to
five. Okay. And downstream is from 5 to
10. Okay. And these are the number of
fine-tuned examples that they see. And
actually, you can see that you do pretty
okay. Okay, you're going to get
something around the order of 10 to the
minus 3 if you give 32,000 snapshots.
Reasonable.
But here, if you have a larger gap
between your parameters, okay, so it was
still trained on one to five, but now
we're doing a larger gap. We see that we
don't do as well. Exactly what you would
imagine for the scaling law.
Similarly, we also see that actually if
you train from scratch, you also don't
learn as well.
The reason being is that twofold. First,
this is a wider range of parameters than
over here. So, you would imagine you
need more examples. And the second is
these parameters they claimed were a
little bit harder quote unquote.
All right. And so, what are the
takeaways from the scaling laws? Well,
data is scarce. So we need to reuse it.
We need to do tricks. We're going to see
that scaling does matter both in model
size and the number of fine-tuned
examples, but it's actually not as
strong as NLP. And lastly, we needed to
introduce some ideas into the
architecture. All right. And so I think
the key takeaway is obvious. You you
need to consider all of these things
when you're designing something for
physical systems. And you do need to
consider similar things for NLP, but
scale doesn't necessarily shown to solve
every problem yet.
They talk about data diversity
specifically in that analysis
with the the walrus or no sorry the
Poseidon. So let me pull it up for you
here.
So here this data sets are the same
size. Okay,
for the for the walrus work the walrus
work they they I didn't talk about it
here but but the data diversity
definitely matters. For example, they
consider many more PTE tasks for their
pre-training. That'll just tell you
they're getting more diverse, right?
They consider 19 different tasks instead
of six. Make sense?
We could talk more at the end.
All right.
And so I want to give you guys a real
world example to kind of end the day. So
here's a weather forecast. This is kind
of the first foundation model. It was
accepted in nature last year. Okay. And
we're interested in solving atmospheric
dynamics on the grid. Okay. And what
this IFS is essentially a classical
solver.
And so the cost of each IFS is run by
these universities or not universities,
these organizations. They run on a a
supercomput. And of course, we're going
to care about this. For example, we need
to know when a hurricane's coming. It's
important to know, for example, for
agriculture, energy costs, turbulence,
you can imagine, right? So here's our
problem. And here's what this paper
Aurora did for Microsoft. So it just
came out last year. They designed a $1.3
billion par or billion parameter model
over it took them a million hours and
then they fine-tuned on four tasks.
Okay, so the idea here, okay, is they
did pre-training and we'll look about
how they did this and then they did
fine-tuning on each of these tasks and
the tasks are things like wind
prediction, pressure prediction for
example. Okay. And so how did they do
their pre-training? They essentially
took a ton of climate simulation data
from every organization and gathered it
together under one corpus. Okay, they
designed this this architecture that's
actually a little bit close to an idea
from from computer vision. Okay, we're
not going to talk about too much. And
then they kind of looked at these
fine-tuning targets. So they were
interested in air quality, ocean,
cyclones, and weather. Okay, we're just
going to show you cyclones today. All
right. And these pre-trainings, they
were diverse. So we kind of talked about
this, but it considered a bunch of
different forecasts, okay? All over the
the world. So not just in the US, for
example, everything is in Europe and so
on and so forth. Okay. Additionally,
they have to be a little bit careful. So
most of this pre-training was from CFD.
And then for fine-tuning they have they
use basically sensor measurements for
each of these problems all over the grid
to get real data right
and what do they show? Well they show
that they could beat the agencies okay
on the sort of lead time over a data set
from 22 to 23 on cyclones. Okay. And so
what is what is lead time? Essentially
it's how far out in the future you can
predict. Can you do better? Okay, so can
I predict a cyclone 10 days away
compared to a month? So on and so forth.
All right, and here's an example of what
their sort of prediction looked like for
this Syrian cyclone. I'm not sure if I'm
pronouncing it correctly, but it was it
was actually a cyclone that hit Europe.
Okay. And up top here is their
prediction. Okay. And this is the wind
speeds. Okay. So meters per second of
the cyclone. And at the bottom here is
what the true data is when you stitch
everything together from the sensors.
And it looks pretty similar. It's not
perfect. So for example, they actually
underestimate the wind speeds quite a
bit in the end. Okay. But this is almost
a 24-hour prediction out. Actually, I
think it's more than 24 hours. No, 24
hours. Okay. And they show this
quantitatively as well. But um this
looks quite well. And so this was kind
of the first first foundation model
that's sort of been accepted in the
weather community as a real problem.
Okay. And so where does this leave us?
Well, we started with this question of
can we have a GPT for for PTE. And it
turns out that we cared a lot about this
data set diversity.
Transfer learning is going to work for
PDEs which is kind of surprising.
We do need to consider our architecture
to be aligned with our data. It needs to
be done in a smart way. And we actually
showed that there is an operational
model used today. It's actually a
foundation model for the first time.
Okay. And so this is kind of a a more
state-of-the-art lecture. Things here
are very very new. And so I would say a
lot a lot of directions are still