Hi everyone. So I'm I'm Luke going to be
teaching the the next few lectures. Most
of it's based on on my research. And
this is like kind of the exciting part
of the class. We're actually going to
look at like some physics inspired ideas
instead of just like general
architectures. So um yeah, just a like
quick poll for my interests. How many of
you are PhD students?
Okay. How many of you are master
students?
Okay, so like almost everyone. How many
of you are students not in ECE?
Okay, so a couple. Great. Looks like we
have a variety. Yeah, feel free to ask
questions throughout the lecture. Kind
of just raise your hand. I'll be happy
to call on you. Yeah, let's get started.
So, a little bit about me.
Yeah. So, I'm a fourth year student
under Yan and another professor in MAE,
Mir Christristitch. My research kind of
spans a wide variety of things. ML,
applied math, control theory, um,
dynamical systems in general.
Uh, my undergrad was at a small school
in Nashville, Tennessee called
Vanderbilt and I did CS and physics
there. So, kind of a little bit
different going to ECE.
I've worked on quite a bit of research
directions. So for those not in ECE, I
worked a little bit in material science
actually on density functional theory.
Maybe some of you guys have heard of it.
Uh spent some time working in robots and
and now I kind of work purely in in
applied math.
And last year I taught this sort of
minieries of lectures EC28. So feel free
to give any suggestions. Most of the
slides are kind of improved from last
year. And outside of work, I spend most
of my time with this dog of mine, Irwin.
Um, he's kind of quite a different set
of breeds. And then I'm also trying to
learn hockey. So, yeah.
All right. So, up until this point in
this class, we kind of looked at
supervised learning paradigms that kind
of take this this structure, right? And
so, the idea is, okay, we're going to
collect some data set, let's say n pairs
of data. We're going to take each input
output pair and our model is going to do
a series of nonlinear transformations on
any input pair via some matrix or matrix
multiplication. And then the
nonlinearity comes from the activation
functions we saw. And so to kind of
learn our models, right, we're going to
do back propagation off some L2 loss,
right? I think this paradigm should be
pretty familiar. um almost all of the
models we looked at so far, even the LLM
ones, kind of follow this this sort of
structure, right? And so today we're
kind of going to look at some new types
of models that embed physics better
instead of just this general matrix
multiplication. And I'll kind of explain
to you what this sort of means in in a
few minutes. But the idea is that this
input output matrix multiplication can
be
can ignore some of the properties or
structure of the system that we're
missing. And so for example becomes
super super expensive to train. I'm sure
you guys know the explosion of data
centers and the energy grid quite a hot
topic right now.
And of course with these large matrix
multiplications the key kind of idea is
this overparameterization right and so
the downside of this
overparameterization
is of course the fact that we lose
interpretability.
So something like, you know, fitting a
tailaylor series is pretty interpretable
compared to a machine learning model,
but it doesn't work as well, right? And
explaining this is a little bit
complicated to to be understated. And
lastly, it's not really a respectable
way of actually how our brains work. And
so I'm sure maybe you guys have seen
Jeffrey Hinton. How many of you know
that name?
Okay, so maybe a fourth of the class.
Yeah, he was kind of the one who
pioneered machine learning at University
of Toronto. He just won the Turing Award
and also the Nobel Prize. Um, you know,
he's famously said that that back
propagation is kind of gross. It's not
so elegant because it's actually very
different than how a neuron would would
sort of learn in our brains, right? And
so, we want to kind of design models
that respect the structure of our object
that we're trying to to learn. And we'll
talk about the structure in a minute.
All right.
So
let's kind of motivate this sort of
structure and and ODEs. All of you I
assume are familiar with ODEs. You've
seen the review so on and so forth. So
I'm not going to spend too much time.
But yeah, the idea is that ODEs are a
continuous problem, right? We have a
derivative and then we'll probably
either discretetize later. And so the
the question is can we sort of get this
continuous structure embedded into our
neural network, right? The second thing
is that we've spent the last 100 years
and multiple DOE grants building these
supercomputers all around the world. So,
how many of you guys have heard of NURK?
Anyone?
Nobody. Okay. So, NURK is is the famous
cluster kind of run by the DOE. Um, the
main supercomputer from the DOE is at
Livermore, which is just outside of San
Francisco. And basically, these these
computers actually are are mainly
CPUbased. Believe it or not, they're
becoming more GPU based given the change
of times. But the reason they were CPUs
based is because all the old physics
solvers, for example, your SW your OD
integrators and these types of things
for for quantum dynamics were all
actually built on on OD or on CPU
architectures, right? And so when the
DOE asked the government for funding,
they basically had to justify, okay, why
do we want to build this large
supercomput? And it turns out that if
you can say that you're doing nuclear
science research, basically simulating
some small quantum dynamics, you can get
quite a bit of funding, right? Because
you can argue that you're preventing
nuclear war. And so basically all of our
last since the 1960s have been developed
these sort of solvers and the modern
machine learning architectures that we
looked at so far haven't really talked
about them too too much. Okay. And
lastly, we will do some some modern
stuff. So for example, the idea of of
normalizing flows are all built on
neural ODEs. And anybody heard of
normalizing flows anywhere? Got two.
Okay, great. Yeah. So these these are
essentially the backbone of of
neurologies and they're the backbone of
things like diffusion which generate in
this case this is a giraffe with
sunglasses from Sora.
All right. So let's kind of give you a
little bit of a review of ODEs. Bear
with me. I think most of you are
familiar but um just for those who
aren't an OD is going to have two
components. So we're going to use this Z
of T to denote the state. Okay. And we
say that this is a continuous OD that is
its derivative is described by some
dynamics function. And we'll assume that
this dynamics function is locally lip
shits which just means it's it's
continuous locally. And typically the
way we work with OD's is we have some
initial condition and this ODEs describe
a flow of a trajectory right so for
example you could think of a time series
and you're forecasting product demand
you might have a current demand estimate
and you want to know how that demand is
going to flow in the future right and so
what would be interesting is okay that
flow is described by f maybe we can
learn f in some way all right and the
main reason kind of these objects are
studied is they describe pretty much the
language of any of these flows. So,
anyone familiar with robot kinematics?
They're a second order system. Climate
modeling, weathers typically are partial
differential equations, which we'll look
at in two lectures. Anyone seen the SIR
model?
No. Okay. It's basically a description
of spread of diseases. So when COVID was
really really big, people developed
quite a bit of SRI models that describe
exactly how often we anticipate the
vaccine to actually work. So if you see
like okay this vaccine should take, you
know, 6 months for the world to be fully
recovered, it's probably projected from
from an OD. And of course the stock
market, I think that's kind of
self-explanatory. any sort of
forecasting problem that we want. And
lastly, surprisingly actually acoustics
and music show up as ODEs. So there's a
famous paper called WaveNet that kind of
introduced a backbone for generating
music through um matrix multiplication
which I find kind of cool, right?
All right. So we discussed these ODEs
and the dynamics mathematically, but
like what is an example? Simplest
example I can give you is is the
pendulum. So you have some string, you
attach a ball to it and you start it
from some angle and it swings, right?
And typically what I can do with this
pendulum is I can map this angle theta
across time, right? And I'll get some
sort of sinosorta wave where the
pendulum eventually swings to the
bottom, right? Simple example. Okay? And
so what is something kind of important
in this structure that maybe you weren't
taught in your OD class is that OD's
solutions are actually unique. So that
is if I start at some position, I know
that in the future I will take a
trajectory that's completely unique
described by those dynamics. And
actually we'll see that this structure
is actually really important later. So
here's an example of why for example we
know well you'll see in your homework
why OD's aren't unique and you'll
actually prove a way to to handle this
this question but here let's kind of
explain why this is you know the case so
imagine I have two ODEs and they start
at initial position zero and one and
they follow the same dynamics f okay the
rule is or this uniqueness basically
says that these odes actually can never
Ross. Okay. And you can prove this
mathematically kind of by the flows. But
one of the things that kind of this
gives us is some interpretability about
our machine learning model. So if we
make a machine learning model and it
follows the flow of an OD, we'll know
that for example trajectories will never
cross at the exact same time. All right.
And so kind of to bring this all
together and give you a little bit more
review, we're going to go through
basically the simplest case of how OD
solvers work that I discussed from the
1900s. So I assume you guys have maybe
heard of Oilers's method and maybe runa
show of hands. Rungakuta.
Okay, maybe 10 of you. So this should be
actually useful. So numerically how do
we sort of represent these objects?
Well, it turns out that we're going to
basically use some ideas from calculus
to derive a scheme to simulate them, for
example. Okay. And so here's kind of the
the simplest possible way to do this.
And there's been a thousand different
research directions on it since. So we
have this OD and it's in continuous
time. Remember, we have some initial
condition at time zero. And we're going
to approximate this OD with a discrete
representation. And what do I mean by
discrete representation? Well, you know,
we know that computers don't work in
continuous time. We need to sort of grid
or vectorize each each problem. And so,
how do we represent something that's
sort of continuous in a discrete time?
The simplest method for that is Oilers's
method. Okay. And so, how does Oilers's
method work? It all starts from a tailor
approximation. So imagine that we want
to estimate the state Z at some future
time step given by delta T and we're
going to assume that delta T is pretty
small. Okay? And we'll see why in a
minute. Then a tailor expansion at delta
t will look something like this, right?
Z of t plus delta t is equal to the
current state times the little time
change times the derivative. But the
thing about an od is actually we know
this derivative, right? By definition,
it's f. Okay.
And so if some we do some algebra, we
can get sort of an estimate of this
derivative, right? Essentially what
we're doing here is if we subtract Z of
T over and we divide by delta T, okay,
we get an estimate of this derivative dz
and essentially an estimate of F. Okay,
and so the question is, okay, in what
case are these two actually equal? Well,
the case that delta t kind of goes to
zero, right? The smaller we get on that
limit, you could think of this as like a
a limit by the definition of a
derivative. And so the smaller delta t
goes to zero, typically it's like h in
high school, you might have seen it or
grade school, then we will approximate
dz, right? So this all comes from
Taylor's theorem or from the definition
of a derivative depending on which way
you want to do it. And then we have some
error which will bound by delta t ^ squ.
And if delta t is really really small,
then this error is really really small,
right? Okay. Okay. And so how are we
going to derive this integration? Well,
we said that okay, we have this
definition up here and we're going to
plug in our continuous representation f.
Okay. And so then we can kind of get a
dynamics model for the next step. Yes,
sir.
Sorry, one more time.
Yeah.
You're saying here?
Yeah. Yes. Yes. Technically, yes. If you
divide it by delta t, yes, it should be
o of delta t. then instead of O of delta
T squared, I'm kind of giving like a
very shorthand derivation. But yes,
actually it would be O of delta T
because it's a first order.
Good point. Good point. And so then
okay, from here, right, so this would be
what he's saying is that this should be
O of delta T because we divided by delta
T here for everyone else. Good. And so
from here, okay, we plug into our
continuous representation and we get an
approximation for the future time step t
plus delta t given the current time
step, the step size and our dynamics
function f. Okay? And so then this is
perfectly simil simulatable in a
computer, right? If I know everything at
current time step, I can estimate the
future time step. And I can do this over
and over and over again. And as long as
delta t is small, we'll get a good
approximation of our OD. Right? Any
questions here? Everyone have an idea of
Oilers's method?
Great. Okay.
Great. And so then why is this important
or what is it related to
in the past? So I I think some of you
may have seen this idea of ResNet
before, but let me give you kind of a a
recap and a high level idea of the
architecture. So the idea of ResNet is
actually really simple. It's instead of
you know an MLP, what we have is that we
basically say from some input, we're
going to learn the change essentially an
additive change in input. Okay, so we're
going to learn this sort of f0. You can
think of this as any neural network
architecture that you want. transformer,
an MLP. Typically, it's just a weight
matrix. Okay. And this is sort of
learning the residual between Z0 and Z1.
And then we pass through a a
and then we pass through a nonlinear
activation function. Okay? And we're
going to do this over and over and over
again. So this is sort of a ResNet
layer. So you see the difference
basically is that we have this residual
term, right? So in our previous examples
for example in MLP this would have been
Z1 equals F of Z0 without the plus Z0
right and so this is pretty common uh
for example the transformer architecture
uses some ideas like this we would have
seen uh before and so the cool thing
here is that we notice that there's some
structure actually similar to an OD that
is okay at an OD point right we said Z
at T plus delta T is equal to Z at T
plus the dynamics X at Z of T, right?
And so it turns out actually that one
could show that in the case where you
take this delta T fixed, you actually
get a ResNet architecture with these
dynamics F. Okay.
And why was this important at the time?
Well, about you know uh five or six
years ago when neural OD came out, all
the rage was actually using ResNet.
One of the most famous approximations is
is ResNet 50. It was commonly used uh
pretty much everywhere.
And we'll think of this this ResNet
connection a little bit later. We'll
come back to this. Okay. But the idea is
that again the residual can be learned.
Okay. And so the problem with ResNet of
course is is you have many layers. So in
this case let's say you have 50 layers
and we know basically when we have these
these large layers especially we saw in
RNN's we get this vanishing gradient
problem it can be very dangerous
actually in in ResNet
and so the idea is that instead of for a
neural OD instead of learning these
individual networks f1 f_sub_2 f_sub_3
fn for all 50 layers we're going to
learn a single neural network
that describes our OD dynamics.
Okay.
And so the idea is okay, we're going to
learn this f hat essentially. And this
fhat is just a vector field mapping us
to our next step. Okay. And then the
output becomes t,
you know, for enough steps. Let's say we
do capital t steps. We're going to take
t movements of this vector field. And so
we're going to get some output Z of T
for our neural network dynamics. So my
first question for you guys is is in
this case what is Z of T equivalent to
in sort of the ResNet architecture?
Any ideas?
Any guesses?
Yes sir.
Yeah. So, so like each time step would
be a different layer essentially of the
hidden state. And so the final time step
would then be equivalent to what?
Output. Exactly. Right. And so the idea
here is that okay, we've done a
continuous representation of resonant.
And it turns out okay we talked about
the fact that we cannot actually
implement this OD, right? And so what
could we do instead? Well, if we do
let's say an Oilers's method on this OD,
we'll directly cover ResNet, recover
ResNet, which is kind of a cool little
like tidbit, right?
Okay.
And so what are kind of tricky about
this neural OD that we haven't sort of
discussed, right? So the idea is okay,
we have some OD, we're going to
represent the vector field by a machine
learning model. Let's say it's an MLP.
What what are the problems? Well, the
first problem is that we promised some
continuous representation and we still
need to compute this output by
propagating through a neural network.
Okay. And we'll see that actually this
capitalizes on what we know in our OD
solver. Okay. So for example, we can use
runaata to solve this problem. The
second thing is and this is a little bit
complicated. How do we do back
propagation? So we get this Z of T at
the end of our neural operator or neuro
architecture and we get some loss. Let's
say it's an L2 mean squared error loss.
How do we do back propagation? And it
turns out this isn't very
straightforward actually.
And lastly, is this actually better than
a ResNet? Okay.
All right. So the like I promised you
this ResNet was going to come up because
it's akin to Oilers's method. Okay. And
the problem with Oilers's method is that
it's like our friend mentioned here,
it's a first order method. So it has
error delta t. But we've done you know
50 years of work in OD solvers. For
example, a common one you might see in
your mat lab or python package is is
called doper 5. And basically what this
does is it allows us to solve this OD a
faster and b with an adaptive time step.
So that is delta t is changing at every
second and we want to capitalize on this
OD architecture right and so how are we
going to do that well the idea is is is
the following and I I'll explain in a
second but just to give you a sense of
what I mean by accuracy
here's for an example Oilers's method in
blue right so that's what we derived and
here for example in orange is the exact
OD flow and let's say I know this OD
flow exactly for example I actually took
a pendulum and measured it right
and RK2 is a second order method it
stands for runa cuta 2 we haven't talked
about it but it's available actually in
your OD review if you want to take a
look and you see that RK2 approximates
this much better than Oilers's method
and RK4 does it almost perfectly where I
can't really notice a difference at this
scale okay so here's the point that I'm
trying to make is that we don't want to
use Oilers's method actually for our
solver, but maybe something better. And
actually, we want our neural OD to be
solver independent. Um, and so we'll
talk about what this means in a minute,
but that's the idea. And you can see why
we would want to use one solver over
another.
All right. And so how do we do back
propagation?
So let's consider a standard loss
function. Okay. And in this problem,
let's assume that we're just trying to
handle the output of our target. So for
example, imagine we want to we have a
pendulum and we drop it. We want to know
where that pendulum is at some final
time capital T. And let's say we
measured that. So those are our labels,
right? So we picked an initial condition
to drop our pendulum and we marked in
our experiment where that final output
time is. Okay? And so we want to learn
these dynamics of our pendulum. So we
gather a bunch of these input output
pairs and we could consider an L2 loss
of these pairs.
And so how are we going to back
propagate through a neural OD design?
Right? This is actually not so simple
and we'll see why in a second. So
naturally what you would do is you would
say okay I'm going to take the
derivative of the loss function with
respect to the weights. Remember our
weights are our dynamics function. And
it turns out that we're going to have to
expand this with the chain rule, right?
And so when we expand this with the
chain rule, we're going to expand it
with respect to the final time Z of T Z
of T with respect to the weights.
And so the problem with this is that
let's assume for example and I will be
solver independent later, but let's
assume that we used Oilers's method.
Well, if we get Z of T using Oilers's
method, we know that relied on the
previous step plus that step size plus
our dynamics function evaluated at that
previous step, right? And we actually
have to go all the way back to Z0, which
was our input. Okay? And so, let me ask
you, if you have to take the gradient
with respect to Z of T with theta, and
remember F is parameterized by theta.
That's what we want to learn. Uh how
easy is it to take this gradient? It's
not so easy, right? Because I have to
take the gradient here. I'm going to get
a multivariable chain rule. Then I also
have to take the gradient with the
previous step. Again, I get another
chain rule and so on and so forth. And
so you can see how this could be
numerically a nightmare to uh to take.
Any questions here? Give it a little bit
of a second.
Okay, great. So we have to take this
chain rule and and you can see it's it's
tricky and so how can we think about
this? Well the problem is that we need
to compute this this expensive dz of t d
theta. Okay and when we plug it into our
discretization right we get something
that looks like this where we're taking
it both with the previous time step and
our function. And of course, like I
mentioned, we have this chain rule.
That's that's pretty gross actually,
right? Because here we're going to have
to take it with respect to the weights
and here we have to take it with respect
to sorry here with respect to the
weights and here with respect to the
previous step again. Yes.
Yeah.
The graph. Oh yeah.
So this is okay. So you could think of
this very simply as a pendulum. S oft is
the angle of the pendulum.
Okay, it's it's just an example, but
that's how you could think of it. So
basically this is saying how the angle
changes over time.
Make sense?
Go ahead.
Sorry.
Yeah. Okay. So, it's not actually a
pendulum simulated here. I was just
giving you an example of you could think
of it as the trajectory. So, this would
be the state s of t is equivalent to the
state z of t in my previous notation if
that makes
the difference. Yeah. So, like you would
plot the absolute error for example is
is what you would look at. Yeah. Yeah.
Good question. Yeah. Um yeah so here for
example this trajectory is is just some
stable point it's it's not an actual
physical system
but the key is that okay like we could
see that when we use oiler we're going
to get a large error compared to a
better numerical solver it's kind of the
idea so I'm trying to tell you that
oiler although it's nice and we can
expand it in pretty clean way it's not
so useful
unless you choose delta t very small
Okay.
Okay. Does everyone follow the maths
though so far?
Great. Okay. So, well, so we get this
this multivariable derivative. It
depends on two functions. And then we
would have to take the derivative with
respect to Z of T as well, right? And so
that can be super expensive. And so how
can we sort of think about handling
this? Um it turns out that
for this simple case it is not so easy.
Okay. And remember we have this goal of
being solver independent. And you can
believe me that the runa cuta methods
are going to be a little bit more
complicated than oilers's method for
example right and so what we're going to
introduce is kind of an interesting
paper developed in 2018 by by Ricky Chen
and his co-authors and this paper is
going to tell you how to compute these
gradients in a good way. Okay.
All right. So the idea of this is not
new. Yes. Go ahead.
Okay.
So, let me ask you this. Okay. If t is
large,
okay, we're going to have a lot more
computation, right? And
Let's see. Do you agree that the oilers
method is a simple method?
Yeah,
it scales with the depth of the neural
network for but but not the neural
network actually. It scales with the
depth of t because our neural network is
actually just one matrix multiplication
we could think for example, right? And
so it kind of scales with the depth of t
which you can think of as like the
length of the reset, the number of
layers in a resnet, right? And so as t
blows up actually you're going to have
to compute all the recursive gradients
below t. Right? Second thing is that we
need to use a small step size. So you
can assume delta t is really really
small right. So if t is five delta t is
0.01 which are reasonable numbers right
that's 500 different recursive calls for
one forward pass and one backwards
gradient. Then we batch this up and you
can imagine it it gets expensive. Do you
agree? Yeah. And then remember this was
for Oilers's method the simplest case.
So for example runa are you familiar
with it or runa for example
we'll do an expansion not just on the
first tailaylor series let's say but say
a second order tailaylor series
expansion. So then we'll have a second
term here that might be a function of
delta t ^ squ right it's a little bit
more than that actually I'm even
underelling it but you can see how it
will blow up with time and we want to
eventually what we want to do is is be
solver independent which we'll see is
actually kind of a unique property that
comes up from this ad method. So
in 30 minutes, let's revisit.
Other questions?
Great. Okay.
Okay. So I'm going to introduce
this new state theta of t. Okay. And
it's going to represent my weights of my
neural network function f. And it of
course theta of t is constant, right?
Because our weights are are are not
going to change throughout our our time.
And so what I do is then I make this
what's called an augmented od. And we'll
see a little bit more about this later.
But we have some time derivative. And
for example, theta sorry should be zero
here on the right. Okay. And so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to define a
function that represents the gradients
of this OD with respect to my loss
function throughout time.
Okay. So I define this function A. It's
going to be called the adjint which
we'll see. And I define it as the
gradient with respect to Z of T and the
gradient with respect to theta of T. And
remember theta of T is just a dummy
variable that equals theta. Okay, let me
clarify. This should be zero.
Okay.
Okay. And so the key is that okay if I
know this adjint state at every time
then I know actually how to compute my
gradients in a pretty easy way. Do you
guys agree with that?
Because we saw that the gradients
required this sort of expansion over all
of time and we had to do it recursively.
So if I know this adjoint state for all
of time then I know my gradient
calculation.
And so what is the idea here? Well, the
idea is that this gradient
as a time can be rewritten by
differentiating as an OD itself. Okay.
And two things are easy to compute in
this gradient. The first thing is that
we'll see how to actually get this D of
t in a second. I'll derive it for you.
But before that, the initial conditions
are not easy to know at time zero. Do we
agree with this? Because at time zero
then I would need to know the derivative
of dz of0 and that requires my whole
recursive chain.
But instead what I do know is actually
the value of the state at time t.
Why do I know the value of the t state
at time t? Well because I know what z
oft is. Right? So it's just the
derivative with respect to my L2 loss
function of my output.
So it's very easy to know what a of t is
and that's what we're going to treat as
our initial condition. And actually to
get our gradients, we're going to
integrate this OD backwards in time.
Okay? And we'll see a little bit of a
diagram in a second.
Okay? And so how did we get this sort of
OD? Well, we differentiated up here.
Okay? And so how do we do this?
We'll just do it for a of t in the
simplest possible case. Okay. And so
here what we have is the gradient with
respect to the loss function. Okay. With
respect to z of t.
And the first thing we're going to do is
we're going to make this identity via
tailaylor's theorem. Okay. And we saw
again from Taylor's theorem that if we
add some small epsilon, we get the
difference between z of t plus epsilon z
of t * epsilon times our derivative
which we plug in for our dynamics plus
some order epsilon squ.
Okay, follow so far. So this is just a
tailor order expansion of z. Okay, we
saw this for example in our oilers's
method as well. Okay. And so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to first give
you an identity by differentiating this.
And we're going to see where this comes
into play in a second. Okay. So I take
the derivative of this with respect to Z
of T.
Plugging in over here, I'm going to get
the identity function or matrix, sorry,
plus the derivative with F with respect
to Z of T partial derivative.
So we build this identity. Okay, I
haven't told you why we're doing this
yet, but let's just say we did this.
Then why is this going to matter? Well,
if I expand this derivative of the
state, the adjint state, which remember
is our gradient of our loss function
with respect to Z of T, what do I get?
Well, I can use the chain rule. The
chain rule says that DL / DZ plus
epsilon times the epsilon augmented
state divided by DZT. And then what am I
going to do? I'm going to plug in,
right?
And so if I plug in I get two things.
The first thing is that okay I plug in
this to the second term get I plus
epsilon time the derivative of f plus
some o of epsilon squar o of epsilon squ
and the second thing I get is actually
this function here by definition is just
a at t plus epsilon.
Okay any questions make sense?
Okay. And so then we get okay something
for a of t plus epsilon times the
identity plus the second term on the
dynamics. All right. And it turns out
what we can do
is if we expand this multiplication
right we're going to get t plus epsilon
plus a of t plus epsilon times this
quantity.
And if we subtract for example a of t
plus epsilon on both sides. switch the
order. You can trust me that you'll get
something that looks like this.
And from here the question is okay
for example is what does this thing on
the look left look like as epsilon goes
to zero?
Any ideas?
It's the small difference between a of t
plus epsilon and a of t. Right? So if I
divide by epsilon for example, I'll get
this differential over epsilon. This
epsilon will disappear. Okay? And I'll
get something that looks like da dt.
And so then this is actually the
quantity the exact quantity. Sorry, I'm
missing an a of t here because when we
expanded it, we had a of t on both
sides.
We'll get something that looks like
this. And this is actually our exact
quantity that we used to describe our od
state.
So if I go back,
I promised you it looks something like a
of t times the derivative of the
dynamics with respect to z of t.
Does everyone follow how we got the the
different or derivation of the OD state?
Yeah.
No, no. Okay. So,
if you divide both by epsilon on the
left here, you'll get the d uh a of t
plus epsilon minus a of t over epsilon.
Okay. Then we take the limit as epsilon
goes to zero. That's the definition of
the derivative. So then you get the da
of t over dt. We agree this epsilon is
going to cancel when I divide by
epsilon. Okay. There should be an a of t
here that multiplies and a of t plus
epsilon.
Yeah. It's yeah. So so
right. But then when I take the limit as
epsilon goes to zero, it becomes a of t.
Let me draw it out. So
can you guys see if I write on this or
no? If I write big. So we get a of t
plus epsilon minus a of t equals minus
epsilon
a of t plus epsilon time df dz.
So this is what's missing.
Do you see? Okay. I divide by epsilon.
divide by epsilon
then I take the limit. So limit epsilon
to zero a of t plus epsilon minus a of t
over epsilon equals a of t plus epsilon
limit epsilon is zero dfdz.
Okay, ignoring let's let's assume things
are scalers ignoring the the mric. From
here this is the definition of the
derivative. From here epsilon's going to
go to zero. we get a of t.
We agree? Yeah. And so then you get the
final expression there. So it's Yeah.
Okay. Okay. The same exact idea can be
done for a of theta dt.
Okay. Same exact derivation. I don't
show it for for that reason. Okay.
Okay. And so then here's the whole idea
of the of the process. So I have this OD
state for the forward pass, right? We go
from an initial condition, we pass it
through our OD solver with our neural
network and we get some output dynamics
Z of capital T
and the adjoint state which represents
our gradients with our cost function
gets solved backwards in time. Okay, so
I promised you that I knew what the
adjoint state was at capital T, right?
because that's the gradient of the loss
function with respect to Z of capital T
which is just our output. Okay. And I
derive the dynamics for the state which
we saw over here. Okay. So what I can
actually do is to get the gradients for
my state for my entire neural
architecture is I can actually solve
this OD backwards in time using my OD
solver to get a set of gradients and
then I can use those gradients to update
my dynamics fs
idea and the key for the backwards idea
is that both of these can are sort of
solver independent, right? I choose my
OD solver. I solve my dynamics forward
in time. I use that same OD solver to
get my dynamics backwards in time. Okay?
And so then the key here is that okay,
if I'm solving instead of having to do
that recursive calculation by hand, I
can essentially just plug two different
dynamical systems into my OD solver.
Okay, so here's kind of some selling
points for this adjoint method. Back to
your question. So the one thing that's
really nice is that we don't need this
entire trajectory in memory at each time
step. Okay, we can calculate our new
step out of our OD solve based on our
backwards trajectory. Okay, so we don't
need all the recursive time steps.
Basically, we only need it at each time.
Does that make sense?
The second thing is that like I promised
you this is completely solver
independent. Okay, I'm just have to
solve two ODS to get my architecture.
And so the great thing is that we can
capitalize on any solver that you want.
So instead of you know pigeon holing
ourselves to this oilers's method which
is you know first order method it has o
of delta t o of delta t error in this
case we actually don't need to do that
right we can use for an example an
adaptive solver
anyone have any disadvantages to this
design
it's a perfect design.
What could be the problem with using OD
solvers both forward and backward
instead of perfectly recursively
calculating?
Any ideas?
Error. Yep.
Yep.
Yes. So, you're saying basically, let me
let me clarify what you're saying. So
you're saying we had a mathematical
formula for the derivative. We knew it
was 100% correct. And in this case, what
we do is we pick an initial condition at
Z of capital T and we integrate
backwards this OD. But we have no
guarantee that this OD integration
backwards is actually what our
mathematical formula says. That that's
essentially what you're saying. And
that's also I think what you're saying
is that our OD solution could have some
error introduced, right? And so the
shift of the the computation is actually
on whether or not this OD solver is
good. Whether or not that those times
actually coincide with the recursive
definition that we derived, right? And
what did I promise you at the beginning
of the lecture? Well, I promised you
that we spent quite a bit of time
working on OD solvers. And so we're
taking advantage of that sort of 50
years of OD solvers such that I can
promise you it's actually pretty good.
Okay, so that is that error is is
actually small. And for example, you
could actually investigate this yourself
if you wanted to. I'm sure GPT could
generate this for you in a minute. You
could say, okay, let's actually
calculate the recursive gradients for a
simple problem. Take, you know, t= 1
dynamical system x dot= x^2. Okay. And
compare it actually with this adjoint
method and see what the error looks
like. Okay. And I promise you, as long
as you use a good OD solver, it'll be
small.
Okay. But yeah, that's certainly a
disadvantage. Go ahead.
So the okay if I expanded that recursive
calculation right for Oilers you agree
that that's different than actually
doing the OD solver
do you agree with that
okay so in that case if you imagine that
our RK4 solver okay is optimized
you know it takes advantage of let's say
some tricks okay and I instead have to
do that recursive calculation by hand
let's say for RK4 so you can imagine
they're equal on both sides right would
you agree that the optimized solver is
probably faster than my h hand
derivation of the recursive calculation
so that's that's the point yeah we're
taking advantage of the fact that these
things are not just well understood but
they're also you You could have have a
package you know for example scypi has a
package right od45 is beautiful mat lab
these types of things I think Julia even
has a very nice solver nowadays so yeah
okay
other questions
great
okay okay
yeah so as you were saying if this OD is
hard to integrate or it's stiff we we
run into some big errors
Okay. And so let me give you like a a
highle summary of the whole architecture
kind of recapping what we did today. So
or so far. So what we said is that okay
we're we have these ODEs and they
basically are the language of which we
describe dynamical systems spanning
everything from epidemiology to
manipulators. Okay. And we want to try
to think about how can we design a
neural network architecture to sort of
approximate this flows right because for
example I would challenge all of you to
find me a perfect weather dynamics model
that is it wouldn't be so easy to write
it down and so we have to maybe learn
this OD from data okay and this sort of
respects the structure that we know and
so what was the idea of a neural well
the neural OD idea is we have this
differential equation with some input
okay so this could be for example a
starting position pendulum. You could
even think of this input actually as for
example some MNST data. So MNIS is set
of handwritten digits and your goal is
to classify the digits for example.
And what we said is we're going to learn
this function f which represents the
flow of our dynamics. Okay.
And how do we learn this function f?
Well, it's not so simple. So let's let f
be classic MLP.
Then what we're going to do is we're
going to integrate this dynamics f using
our OD solver until some time capital T.
And we saw that this was like the ResNet
structure, but remember the ResNet
structure had a bunch of discrete layers
where we learned a new set of dynamics
for each layer. In this case, we only
have one set of dynamics f, but we can
integrate to say a very large T.
We then said okay that's great but how
do we compute these gradients and the
gradients with respect to the loss
function are I would say not so simple
to compute we saw this recursive design
and so we said okay we can sort of
approximate these gradients in a good
way by defining this adjint state and
doing a sort of reverse backwards solve
the OD solver okay
and what was the key kind of point of
this is that this is the first time
we've actually thought about embedding
some structure physically into our
neural network architecture. Right? So
up until this point we looked at for
example attention which kind of is an
idea basically from
any of you guys know like what seek to
seek is or no?
Okay, let's ignore that. uh but it it's
sort of built off of these years of of
of natural language processing and how
do we handle kind of entire sequences
all at once. Okay. And in this case we
said okay well for dynamical systems we
have a different type of structure the
sort of OD structure and we show that
okay by embedding a neural network in a
structure we can get some some new
architecture but I haven't shown you
whether or not this architecture is good
which of course I'll let you guys kind
of find out in your homework but also
show you some examples in a second
and so here's an simple example I
promised you we would do the handwritten
digits so for example MN
uh is is a very famous data set. For the
longest time, it was considered like the
benchmark data set in sort of computer
vision where okay, I get a pixelized
representation of this number and I have
to classify it as two.
And so how could I turn this into a sort
of neurode architecture? Well, what I
could do is the following. I treat this
pixelized input as an initial condition
for my OD.
Okay, I then will run to some capital T
seconds my neural network architecture
learning this vector field f. Okay, and
then I will do our back propagation like
we talked about.
And so this was kind of the first
experiment ever done with these neural
ODEs. And what do we show? Well, they
showed that you could get approximately
the same performance as ResNets
approximately
with 01 memory. Okay. And you know about
a third of the number of parameters.
So this was a bit pretty big result at
the time. It was 2018. So you can
imagine seven years ago. But the idea is
that this resonant actually works. Okay.
Or this this ENET. Okay, the RKNet is
actually a very simple similar
algorithm. Okay, but they did not
introduce the adjint method. So you were
asking earlier about like why wouldn't I
just expand A4 that actually was done.
It was sort of this RK net. It works
pretty well in practice. The only thing
is that you have to store the whole
time. Okay, because we saw that when we
expand the gradient with respect to f,
it depends on all of the previous times.
Okay.
All right. And so then since this now
these kind of methods are all over
generative modeling. So does anyone know
the problem generative modeling off the
top of your head? Like if I ask what's
the difference between like a
discriminative and a generative model?
Any of you guys gotten that question
before?
Okay. A generative model aims to
approximate a probability distribution.
Okay.
And a descriptive model aims to learn a
mapping from input to output labels.
Okay. And these are actually
fundamentally different ways of thinking
about problems. Um and so in generative
modeling what I could do for example the
way kind of diffusion models work is
imagine I take a data set and I want to
learn the mapping from pure noise let's
say Gaussian noise okay to a target
image. Okay, well this target image can
be represented by a probability
distribution. And it turns out that this
mapping from a noise to this target
image can actually be represented by an
OD.
And so basically all of the generative
modeling work nowadays is built off of
this idea that we actually just need to
learn this OD mapping from say pure
noise to a a beautiful image.
And so where what is the architecture
that's natural to do that? Well, of
course, it's a neural OD. Okay. And so
this is kind of the backbone be behind
Sora. It's now kind of being used all
over the place for actually text
generation as well. So one advantage of
this is that for example, imagine that
you are Google and you're trying to make
Gemini, but you want Gemini to work on
your phone. Okay, one thing you could do
is you could say, okay, have the phone
send a signal to the cloud, run on my
GPUs, and then kind of send it back, but
you can imagine that could take some
time and it depends on network latency.
In this case, actually, what they've
tried to do is develop a on phone
diffusion model for the new Pixel
phones. Um, does it work?
to be seen. But the idea is that you can
at least run a large language model on
your phone, for example, with this
architecture. It's it's a little bit
more than that, but
give it a second.
Okay.
And so here's the exact idea that I was
talking about. We have some noise, okay?
And we want to learn the mapping from
noise to an image. Okay. And this is
actually what's called an inverse
diffusion process. So the forward
diffusion process is okay I slowly add
image to the noise. This is easy to do.
We know how to add uh noise to images.
But learning this reverse direction is
actually a little bit tricky. And we can
represent it with an OD of which we
learn the dynamics function.
And so this is actually like the
backbone idea behind generative models.
You can imagine okay now if I want to
say okay draw me a picture of a giraffe
well I'll learn a conditional backwards
pass right conditional on the word
giraffe
okay where else is this sort of popular
so I promised you that this was big for
for co it's really big in learning based
control okay you can imagine that
control theorists love to work on these
OD dynamics and so learning the dynamics
is always a challenge Especially
for complicated systems where we just
have input output data and so commonly
people have tried to learn neural
architectures and then drive controllers
based on that architecture.
And then lastly of course I promised you
forecasting. So here for example is a
set of weather patterns. Okay. And what
I have here basically is I can learn a
neural OD where each time step I might
check my data. Okay. Okay. And then I
can restart the OD over and over and
over again. And so what I see here is is
for example two things, wind and
pressure. And actually what I know for
example is this green line that's solid.
Okay. So this is actually what I know
and actually can truly measure. The
green dots are then samples that I
actually fed the model. Okay. And from
those samples, you can see that I can
actually forecast later beyond my
estimate. And you see it has this sort
of syosoidal um type shape. And then
these green dots are again what the true
values ended up being. So you see it's
not perfect of course when it's quite
hard to predict, but it looks reasonable
actually as a as a prediction model. Um
and this actually I I saw a paper
recently that it is doing the same thing
in financial markets but you know
financial markets you need to be a
little bit more uh thoughtful because
you want to output a distribution over
risk. So not just a single point
forecast but a full distribution but the
same idea can sort of hold and here's
another example. Okay.
And so let me kind of conclude. In your
homework, you're going to train a neural
OD to solve a simple problem. And
actually, you're going to look at
whether these architecturals are
universal. That means they can sort of
approximate any function. And so what
are some things to consider in an early?
Well, that dynamics function f you
typically actually want it to be simple
because we're going to need to evaluate
it quite a bit. Okay? And so usually we
use something like an MLP. Second thing
is that we have to be careful when
initializing our neural OD. It's just
like a typical MLP where we have to be
careful with our gradients for example
in the first couple iterations of our
back prop. The same thing happens here
and it's exactly what you guys
mentioned. The reverse process can be a
nightmare to backwards integrate if we
don't choose some very simple initial
conditions to start from. Okay.
Second thing is that
we need our functions, our neural OD
architecture to actually be a C1
function to guarantee that the adjoint
is actually well defined mathematically.
This is kind of hidden in practice but
what people use nowadays in the neuro
architecture is some modification of
RLU. So maybe you guys have seen like
JLU or sireu functions. Um they're kind
of all over the language models. Now the
problem with RLU of course is you guys
know and maybe talked about is that
there's that kink at zero, right? So
this is my RLU function. This is the
point Z and there's a kink here and so
it's not C1 there. Right? And so we kind
of use well-defined approximations for
example where this is differentiable.
That'll help you in practice, but
everything on your homework can be done
with a relu function. Okay.
Lastly, it's very common to augment this
neural OD architecture with a softmax at
the end because you can imagine if I
want to do discrete binning, right? And
my input is this, you know, 256 x 256
set of pixels, I might want to add a
soft max at the end to actually do
classification. So in our handwritten
data set, that's the kind of final
puzzle piece that they did.
Okay,
I promised you also that these neural
ODs would be more inter interpretable
give or take. And so what do I mean by
that?
Well, the nice thing about these sort of
ODS is we can actually visualize the
vector field dynamics. So anyone who's
familiar with with regular ODS you might
look at what the flow of f looks like to
check for example stability limit cycles
these types of things we can actually do
the same thing with our learn dynamics f
and this kind of gives us an idea of how
the behavior is going to look so for
example here what I've kind of plotted
is is a vector field dynamics of x and y
and the arrows represent the direction
of f okay and every arrow is normalized
to be unit size okay or even smaller
than unit size in this case just for the
image and what I can see is that these
trajectories are actually going to kind
of flow along f and this visualization
gives us a little bit of
interpretability of what we actually
learned and so can you imagine then if I
learn this dynamics function f and let's
say that this is correct but over here I
start doing some seriously odd stuff
with my neural od well I can imagine
that it probably the neural network did
not see some trajectory that belongs
over here. And this gives me an idea of
how I can do for example how well I'll
do for example out of distribution right
because if I plot this this field and I
say okay we're doing some weird things
over here I don't see why we're doing
that well then I can assume that maybe
those trajectories are out of
distribution gives me a little sense of
where my neural network's actually going
to work. Okay
another thing is that we can ask all the
questions that we asked about dynamical
systems. So what does stability look
like? Do we have fixed points? What is a
region of attraction? Um, we can also
augment our function f to maybe enforce
these types of of things. So, for
example, imagine that we know the
pendulum is going to be stable at the
bottom. Well, we can kind of maybe think
about that and add to our loss function
a condition that guarantees that our
neural network at the point 0 is also
zero. These types of things we'll think
about later. They're called physics
informs losses. We'll do we'll do a
discussion on that. But this kind of
lens lets us help think about this.
Okay. Lastly, we can kind of in
investigate what happens if we perturb
this matrix to our vector field. So for
example, we learn some dynamics and we
know that our learn dynamics are not
perfect. Okay. So we go to use let's say
a controller based on these dynamics.
How bad can we expect our system to
behave with this sort of approximation?
You can kind of do an analysis of this
by actually perturbing the weight
matrices. So for example, you add some
epsilon to f to all the weights in f.
How far off do my trajectories go? Do
they go really far away or are they
close together? This is sort of a
sensitivity analysis and it's kind of
very common in in ODEs. For example, you
guys have probably done like a
bifurcification analysis. Same type of
idea, but now we're thinking in terms of
learning. Okay. All right. And lastly I
want to kind of give you some
disadvantages. We talked about some but
the the overwhelming sort of
disadvantages are are really there. So
the first thing is that we see that
actually the structure of an OD cannot
approximate any function. Okay. So maybe
you guys have seen this universal
approximation theorem. It's a theorem
that mathematicians care about but
people in practice don't care about too
too much but all your favorite
architectures are universally
approximal. So transformers for example
are. And actually the structure of the
OD as we presented today is not which is
kind of something that might upset you.
And we'll see that you can make what's
called an augmented neuro sort of fix
this. So for example, why this would be
a problem is that imagine we're using
this on on some computer vision task. It
might be that the architecture is a
fundamental limitation that we can't
approximate that function which is kind
of gross. Okay.
Another thing is that we do still have
those gradient problems that we talked
about. if t is humongous. Okay. And this
is all because if you imagine that
backwards od solve, the farther we get
away from where we started for the
gradients, the more error we're going to
have. This sort of compounds.
And lastly, a real problem for these
these objects is that when we have
highdimensional or stiff dynamics, that
backwards OD solver does not work well.
Okay. And so that actually might be a
case where you mentioned that the
recursive calculation may be better
because we have like for example an
analytical form but you're going to pay
a cost right and the cost is going to be
the cost of training and here we have a
little graph this was only up to 23 but
you can see actually it's quite quite
the trend upwards on the left we have a
log scale cost okay and so back in the
day I mean compute almost costed very
little to try to train a neural network
now you can imagine it's much even
higher than this right so we have to
always keep this cost in mind because
you know the US actually like has a
limitation on power lines and these
types of things so we can't just build
data centers left and right
um and so with that I'll leave you with
some future reading if you're interested
you'll look at this augmented neurode
IDN homework another thing that you can
look at is integrating that sort of
stabilizing point that I was talking
about. So I give you a little example.
And lastly, one of the things that we
showed was that sort of example of
forecasting where we're sort of getting
new sensor measurements. I didn't really
explain how that works and that's kind
of developed in these articles as well.
Okay. Lastly, this is what happens when
you have pertabbations to that weight
matrix. Okay. And so with that, yeah,
we'll see you next