Well, today we're going to talk about
neural operators. They're one of my
favorite topics, kind of my whole PhD
resolves around them. And we'll sort of
be looking quite a bit at PTE. So, how
many of you guys have played with PTEEs
before?
Just one person. Okay, great. We'll have
a little bit of a review kind of to help
everyone and then we'll go from there.
So, yeah.
All right.
All right. So remember last time we
talked about neural odes and neural odes
introduced this idea of embedding
machine learning models into
differential equations right and so the
key idea was okay we're going to learn
this new dynamics f right and the idea
is okay maybe we have some set of
initial conditions and we can do
supervised learning on f and the problem
with learning this f was a little bit
tricky about how to compute the
gradients and so what we did is We
defined these things called the adjoint
dynamics which are essentially the
gradients and we derived a separate OD
state for those adjint dynamics and then
we argued that we could just simulate
that second OD state backwards in time
to get our back propagation.
And so this was sort of the first
introduction that we've seen to what it
looks like to represent things in a sort
of continuous way. And we talked about
Oiler's method for discretization and
we'll see an analogous method for PDEs.
So today there's kind of quite a bit
more to be explored in this direction of
of connecting machine learning models to
dynamical systems. And so what we're
going to talk about today is is
something called neural operators. And
the idea is okay for neural OD we had to
build a set of points t from zero to
some terminal time, right? And one thing
is that we had to pick a sort of
discretization via our OD solver for
these set of points. We're going to see
we have to do the same thing for PTE but
also over space. Okay. And one of the
key problems is that if you have say a
three-dimensional space and you have
time and you try to build a grid of
these things, it's a 40 grid and this
grid's going to grow exponentially.
And so what we're interested in is
designing machine learning methods that
we can query at any desired time or
space location. Okay? And so we'll see
what that means in a second compared to
discretization.
Okay. So since only one of you is really
familiar with PDEs, I kind of started
with a little bit of history about how
we simulate PTE just like we did for
ODEs. So remember PTE are a function
multivariable function with partial
derivatives in both time and space. So
this dell operator here, have you guys
all seen this before? Gradients, we're
all familiar, I assume. This this
quantity is this evolution both in space
and time. And so the idea for PTE, what
we need to do is we basically grid not
just over spa over time like we did for
ODEs, but we're also going to say build
a set of points X0 to Xn, right? And we
build this grid representation
of, you know, these could be uniformly
spaced. for example 0 0.1.2 so on and so
forth. Okay. And what we're going to do
is then we're going to approximate these
derivatives which are given to us
continuously
over these sort of discrete intervals.
And I'll show you an example of how to
approximate these using finite
differences later but there's quite a
bit of approaches to do this. Okay. And
then we're going to step the PTE in the
same sort of time stepping scheme we
used last time. Remember for an OD we
used oiler scheme and we said okay you
know the state at t plus a little bit of
delta t depends on the past state and
our derived quantity of the time step
and we're going to do the same thing for
PTEs but we're going to see it gets a
little bit more complicated.
So this is the highle idea or paradigm
of how you would simulate a PTE
classically. Okay. So you would describe
some grid. How you define this grid is
of course up to the engineer. you would
describe a way to approximate some
derivatives and then you're going to use
a chosen step solver and of course all
of these are intermingled but that's the
sort of paradigm classically
and so what is the problem that people
have been fighting with for the last 30
40 years with these sort of classical
approaches. Well, the problem is is that
you kind of have to choose this grid
typically either at a fixed resolution
and solve your PTE either at a fixed
resolution a priority or if you do as an
adaptive solver. Then if you want to say
know your PTE at a new grid point,
you'll have to rerun the computation. So
for example, here's an example of a
triangle mesh. It's pretty pretty
complicated. So what I or pretty simple.
So what I did is basically I grided up
my domain which is from minus1 to one in
x and let's say minus1 in y and I built
a bunch of these voxalized points
essenti essentially which represent a
triangle. Okay. And so this would be an
example of all the points at which I
approximate the derivatives of my PTE.
And then from those derivatives, I'm
actually going to solve my PTE over this
grid moving forward in time.
But you guys can see okay the problem
here is that once I solve my PD on this
grid if I say want a point here where
there's no you know dot I would have to
redefine a new grid and resolve
technically or do some sort of linear
interpolation or or any type of
interpolation right a second thing that
we kind of see and I've alluded to is
that when I solve a PTE typically I'm
going to have parameters right just like
in an OD
And when I change those parameters,
those can drastically change the values
of my PTE naturally. And so again, if I
change these parameters, I will have to
resolve this PTE from scratch over this
grid, right? And unlike ODEs, this PTE
is going to be expensive to resolve. You
could think you could think maybe a
couple days on a cluster, right? And so
if I have to do this for a bunch of uh
new parameters, it's kind of
computationally infeasible.
And so I want to give you an example to
kind of hone this in and really explain
where the the problem is. So have any of
you guys seen this dynamics before? It's
a transport PD.
One person. Great. Do you know what a
transport PD might do? for example,
what is transport? Yeah, what does that
mean?
Yeah, essentially what this is going to
do is it's going to take some initial
condition. So, which I've represented
here with this function f ofx. Okay. And
it's going to basically transport it
you'll see from one side of the domain
to the other essentially there's a a
method called the characteristics and
you're basically going to flow along
these lines. Okay? And so let me just
explain a little bit more of the
notation here. So this is the state
we're going to use u depends on two
functions x and t. We have a partial d
with respect to t is equal to x. And
then these two things down here are sort
of like our initial conditions for our
od analogously. So the first one here is
actually an initial condition. So this
says at time zero over all of x I'm
going to identify with this function f
ofx. And for those of you from the math
community, let's assume f ofx is a c1
function.
The second condition is a boundary
condition which is actually needed to be
specified for a PD to ensure the PD is
well defined. And I kind of talk a
little bit more about this in in my
review notes. So take a look at that if
you have some time. But in this case, I
pick a very simple boundary condition.
It's called a derslay boundary
condition. Just setting the value at the
end point to zero.
And so like our friend said, this PTE is
sort of just transports your initial
condition over time or or flows it. And
here's kind of what it looks like. So
what I have here is a Gaussian. Okay. On
the uh yaxis here, I have time. On the
x-axis here, I have space. And this is
the value of the PTE. And so what I have
is a Gaussian here to kind of start. And
what you see is that the PTE just shifts
the Gaussian over time essentially.
simple super simple example probably the
simplest PTE you can come up with you
have actually an analytical solution to
this PD for example but numerically
we're going to have to simulate it okay
and so how do we do this well we're
going to apply Oilers's method in the
same way we did before but now to both
space and time okay and so what I can
say is that the approximation of this
derivative
is equal to the difference between two
points and this delta t / delta t. And
remember we looked at this last time,
right? So this just comes from a
tailaylor series expansion of u at x
comma t plus delta t. All right, any
questions? Does it make sense? We
remember it from last time.
I can do the same thing, same exact idea
to space. Okay. And so I define these
small time steps delta t and delta x and
I get approximations for the derivative.
Okay. And then what I can do is I can
substitute these in to my transport
dynamics because we remembered that in
my PTE in this case I have the partial
derivative with respect to t is equal to
the one with respect to x.
And so when I plug this in, you can
trust me on the math here. I get
something that looks like this. Okay,
where I can get the time step, the next
time step for all of space depends on
the current time step for all of space
plus this ratio delta t over delta x
as well as the difference between two
spatial values at time t.
So all I did was I took this PTE
and I plugged in these two approximate
derivatives and solved for this top
value.
And so this is called a finite
differencing scheme. Why is it called
finite differencing? Well, essentially
I'm approximating the derivatives with
the two closest points as a difference.
And it turns out that we can solve this
PTE over time. And recursively we sort
of have this time stepping algorithm
right and that's how we would
classically solve this PD essentially
with some boundary conditions of course
and we need the boundary conditions
because if we're on you know the
rightmost boundary the leftmost boundary
we depend on this point x plus delta x
right and so we're going to need
essentially for the point zero okay
we're going to need zero to be our value
and for the point one well we don't
necessarily have this x plus delta X and
so we need to approximate it and it
comes from the boundary condition sort
of as a flow in the same way that the
initial condition gives us the initial
time for t
all right and so okay we could simulate
this recursively until we reach our
desired value right and so this is a
classic approach to simulating PDS
make sense any questions here
Okay. And so I promised you that unlike
ODEs, PTEES can get very very expensive
very quickly. And so let's give me, you
know, some reasons why. I think you guys
know why. We talked about the fact that
this spatial and temporal component is
going to grow significantly with
dimension. So, for example, if I want to
simulate a PTE that describes the
dynamics of this room, I would have to
simulate a course in 3D and then I'd
also have to simulate in time, right?
And we could see how that that's going
to blow up. And actually, I'm going to
give you a calculation later that really
puts the numbers into perspective.
Additionally, one thing I didn't really
talk about in that last derivation
is that this finite difference scheme
really requires a small number here. And
there's some condition. It's the Cedric
Frank Louie condition CFL. You can look
it up. That basically says what that
number needs to be. And typically it
needs to be for example for a transpoint
less than 1/2.
So I need to choose these step sizes
delta x and delta t extremely small
actually and you'll see this in your
homework as well. And so to choose these
actually super small you can imagine
then the smaller I choose this the more
grid points I'm going to have right and
for a PTE I really actually need delta t
to be much smaller than our spatial
variables.
So for example,
for this case of solving to time equals
5, let's say it's 5 seconds. For these
choices of delta t and delta x, which
are reasonable, but they'll take a while
on your laptop, we'll need about a
million points per recursive step,
right?
Similarly, let's consider like the holy
grail of PTE, Navier Stokes equations.
Anyone heard of Navia Stokes equations?
Famous equations. You get a million
bucks if you solve them. We'll talk
about it a little bit later. For a 1D
Navier Stokes problem, we'll see that
it's actually pretty reasonable. Okay,
we get a million points. Just like I
said,
for a 2D solve, notice we get a 100
million points. Okay, and you can see
how things are blowing up already. For a
3D solve,
we're going to require 10 billion
points. Okay, which I know there's quite
a bit of explosion in computation from
modern data centers, but that's still
going to take quite a bit even on a a
supercomputer. And so that's actually
why the DOE started building all these
supercomputers because like I was
telling you that last week, basically
the DOE is interested in the nuclear
stockpile. Essentially, there's a a
little wing in the DOE called the NNSA.
stands for nuclear national security
administration
and if you're a scientist any quantum
physics simulation requires solution of
the Schroinger equation which is itself
a PTE with a complex domain right so
complex meaning you have I involved as
well and so basically what all those
scientists said is in order to simulate
these quantum dynamics we need
supercomputers and so the government
built a bunch of supercomputers
And the interesting thing is that
they're all basically CPU based up until
the last. Okay, actually Sierra is the
first one that is GPU based. It uses
AMD's GPUs.
And so kind of this machine learning
route is really really new historically.
I mean we really put a lot of resources
we saying in the country of of the US
into solving these PTEEs without machine
learning up until the last 10 years or
so. So, kind of a cool little tidbit,
but you guys can see. Okay, I would
challenge any of you even on your nice
laptops. If anyone has like a new I see
a nice Alienware over there or a new M5
chip, you're not solving a 3D Navier
Stokes equation.
Okay. And so that's kind of where we are
today in our design of okay, how can we
solve this problem by just throwing a
bunch of parameters and doing gradient
descent. And of course we're going to
think about this a little bit smarter
than just throwing our machine learning
models. And so what we're interested in
is this sort of discretization
invariance property which has come and
gone and and we'll see sort of some
examples of it that we want to train
this PTE surrogate model to not only
give us an amateurized solution of our
our our classical solver but also give
us a little bit of flexibility
essentially doing the interpolation for
us.
And so one of the key ideas here that
we're going to use is that we're going
to think of things sort of in a
continuous representation first in our
design and then we're going to think
about how to discretetize and implement.
Okay. Okay. And so to do this in sort of
a continuous representation of course
today we're working on neural operators
and I assume some of you may have never
formalized an operator although you're
all very familiar with them. Okay. So
for example um it's sort of an
abstraction of functions that's how I
would think about it. So consider for
example okay we have some function
vector value that takes r okay we agree
on this is well known you know it could
be for example x squar to a vector right
and so what is an operator well an
operator is essentially what we're going
to treat it as in this class is an
operation on a set of functions. Okay.
And what does it mean to be a set of
functions? Well, you guys know many
sets. So, for example, here you guys
know all polomials of degree less than
or equal to two, right? All quadratics.
Or another example is all sign functions
of this form a sin bx plus c. Okay?
Where we let a, b, and c vary. So these
are examples of classes of functions.
What an operator is going to do is it's
going to modify classes of functions.
It's essentially going to operate
instead of on vectors, we're going to
operate over functions. Okay. So for
example, in this case, we map a
functions class. Let's take this class f
ofx to let's say its derivative, right?
And so we'll get something like ab
cosine bx, right? Similarly,
you guys have seen many many types of
these functions. So for example, if I
take this class f again, one of the
operators I could do is the integral
operator. Okay. And this integral
operator is actually going to tell us a
little bit. It's going to mathematically
tell us quite a bit actually about the
structure and ingredients we need to
approximate such operators. We talked
about the derivative operator. Another
one is the shift operator. Okay. So just
given a parameter C, shift the function.
I want to ask you guys, is there any
other operator that comes to mind off
the top of your head? Maybe it's from
something we looked at earlier in the
classes,
not necessarily my class, but
yes.
So, an activation function. Okay. What's
the input to an activation function?
Right. But what are they? Are they
scalers, vectors, functions?
Yeah, they'll be data points, right? So
an activation function is actually a
function, right? Because it maps let's
say scalers to scalers. Whereas an
operator in our case, we're actually for
example, our input here is actually this
function f, right? So if I tell you,
okay, you know, you know the polomial
rule for derivative. So x^2, it's going
to become 2x, x cub's going to become
3x^2. So this is a mapping. My input
function would be x^2. My output
function of the derivative is 2x. So
those still both depend on vectors,
right? Does that make sense? So
activation is still function actually.
But you're on the right track. Maybe
thinking about architectures very
popular maybe in computer vision. I saw
some of you guys doing computer vision
projects. So um
ideas there. What was like the first
computer vision designs? What was a very
famous neural network architecture
there? CNN. And what is a CNN? What's
the first word in CNN? Convolution. What
is a convolution,
right? But we call it a convolution
operator, right? Because you know you're
passing through that infinite integral.
Exactly. And we'll see an exa exact
example of this a little bit later. So
convolution is a great example.
With that said, does that make sense to
everyone what an operator is first? Stop
here.
Amazing. So with that said, we're going
to start talking about some of the
mathematical properties of these sort of
operators. Okay.
And one of the important properties that
we're going to see that makes things a
little bit complicated is that we don't
have this sense of dimension that we
have for example in finite spaces. So
for example, I remember or you guys all
remember maybe you took linear algebra
with pia pal if she's still teaching it
but you learn this notion of a basis and
even from your undergrad I'm sure you
know what a basis is where you can say
okay you know if I'm in R3 I can define
a set of linearly independent vectors 1
0 0 1 0 and 0 0 1 that will span the
space and remember we mentioned that
this thing of span means I can construct
any other vector vector as a
decomposition of these things, right?
And you guys have seen this for example
for many dimensions. So I gave you it to
you in three but and actually three
there's some connections to a cube in
four you sort of extend it to a hyper
cube and so on and so forth. Okay,
but for functions it's not so simple.
So let's consider for example the set of
all continuous functions on 0ero to one
continuous functions clear to everyone
what that means right there's no jump or
gap okay
and what we could say is that is it
possible to build a basis of the set of
continuous functions and you know zero
to one it could be a to b whatever let's
just assume it's a compact topology
ology. Do you guys think it's possible
to do this
in let's say a finite number of ways?
Good.
So, so one more time. So you said it's
the same problem as the sigmoid function
can build
essentially yeah essentially yeah but
the okay but you need an infinite number
of functions right to perfectly
approximate it so what we do in in the
homework for example is you'll truncate
right right so the the point is that
okay the because you need an infinite
number of functions the basis is
necessarily infinite dimensional Okay.
And this is a little bit tricky because
we said that the
neural operator or we'll see that the
neural operator is going to take in a
function as an input and a function as
an output. Okay. And the reason we kind
of want to do this is to query that
function at any points. But how do we
represent a function in a computer
is not so simple, right? So one of the
things that we could do is is use a
symbolic form. So for example if we have
the function let's say you know if we
consider all polomials of degree 2
right we could actually represent this
in a form ABC
okay you guys agree that sort of
describes the function but if we open
our space up to example continuous
functions all continuous functions well
this is going to include ss cosiness ABC
exponentials so on and so forth And so
it's really not so easy to do things in
symbolic ways. And we'll see why this
creates a problem and talk about a
little bit how to encode a function into
a computer. At least one simple idea.
All right.
Okay. So our goal then is to approximate
these operator mappings.
And we'll connect this to PDEs in a
minute.
The idea here is what does it mean to
approximate an operator? Well, for
example, if I want to
take in the function x^2 and I want to
approximate the derivative operator, the
output of my neural network should be
something like 2x. And maybe even to put
that into a real value, I could output
the number two. And then let's say the
user can also specify what the value is
for x. So for example the derivative of
x^2 at the point one might be just the
value two right
and the problem here is again what I was
talking about is that we need to kind of
figure out how to encode this function
and we also need to figure out how do we
represent its output in a good way sort
of a decoded way. Okay,
the last thing I kind of want to answer
or ask you guys is, okay, I proposed
this idea. We're going to learn this
mapping between functions seems pretty
abstract. Yeah, why why would we be
interested in this?
That's a pretty great example. Yeah, I
think that makes sense. Yeah. So, okay.
So, learning actually learning these
transfer functions as operator mappings
from AB into let's say the transfer
function is a common like I think that
paper exists probably as an example with
the neural operator. So, great example
any other kind of thing. So what was the
problem when we were thinking about okay
you know we want to learn the solution
of PTEES perhaps we have some initial
state of our PTE initial condition and
we want to learn let's say the value of
that how that PTE evolves over time you
know the initial condition for a PD is
not a vector for example it's a function
right so we saw that it was that
function f ofx and the output of course
is also a function and we described the
solution to the PD as an operator. So
that's one reason we want to do it for
our interest in PTEES. Another reason
that I kind of hinted to is what was the
problem with solving PDS classically?
Think about in that area we saw this
huge blow up of points in space. If we
do things sort of in a continuous
representation, what advantage could we
potentially encode into our neural
network?
Any ideas?
So the main advantage that we want to
encode is this sort of discretization
and variance property. Okay. And when we
start to think about things in
functions, it makes us ask the question,
how are we going to encode this
function? How are we going to decode
this function? If we decode, can we
choose the points that we decode at
without having to retrain? Okay. And so
that's kind of why this this type of
thinking and framework is going to be
useful for our dynamical systems
problems that we talked about.
Okay. And so here's a good example of of
what a simple solution for an OD would
look like. And actually this here is
itself an operator, right? Because we
have to apply the integral. And for
example, we might want to be interested
in actually mapping let's say from this
init initial condition Z and some
dynamics F of which you know might
change over time. We want to make a
surrogate model for this approximation,
right? And so the solution to this of
course is given by an operator. It's the
simplest one.
In the same reason we're going to say
okay well if we do this in a continuous
representation maybe we don't need to
get you know a specific sped of points t
but we can actually choose t at the end
okay without retraining our surrogate
and then we have solutions to odes in
you know millisecond time let's say for
quering the same idea is going to apply
to pdes
okay and so let me give you an example
of a pretty nasty PD PTE and let me
explicitly specify what we might want to
learn. So this is of course the Navier
Stokes PTE describes fluid flows. If you
want to describe how air flow moves in
this room for example, you would use
some combination of the Navia Stokes PTE
and you would want to say okay like why
would I care about fluid flows or air
flows in rooms? Well, basically one
problem I'm actually working on in
research is on data centers and we're
interested in how the flow of fans can
keep the air and the thermals cool in
data centers. And that powers your um
lovely chat GPT that you guys are not
going to use on the homework, right? And
so this is the idea and why we're
interested in these types of equations.
Okay? And I give you what the
coefficients here are going to be, but
let's say that most of them are fixed.
And so we're interested in learning this
solution operator from let's say an
initial field. Okay. So this initial
field I'm going to use with this
function g of x. Okay. And I know the
notation is going to be a little bit
weird here, but what I'm going to do is
I'm going to denote functions
in bold and nonfunctions or scalers,
vectors, etc. in this sort of non-bold.
Right? I give you the exact spaces that
are everything in. For now, we can just
assume that everything except G is
fixed. Okay? And we want to learn a
mapping, let's say G to the solution
operator U. And I promised you that
okay, if I want to do this, let's say X
is a threedimensional object, this would
take 10 billion parameters per
simulation.
So we want to do this in a fast way with
a sort of amateurized machine learning
model. And how are we going to do it?
Well, we have to consider two things.
First, we have functions as our input.
Okay? And so that's why we need to learn
an operator. And second thing is that we
need to consider this grid invariance
that we talked about. All right.
Another example is that we don't
actually need to consider the mapping
from G for example into U. But we could
do other functional inputs. So for
example, okay, this was the G one. Very
common setup. Another one actually we
could consider is that okay, let's
assume G is fixed. Okay. And let's say
that I'm interested actually in changing
these fields because for example, let's
say, you know, I'm in a data center. The
ambient temperature of that data center
outside is going to affect the cooling
in. So each day I need to resolve and
even throughout the day I need to
resolve this PTE. And I promised you
that we couldn't do this in real time.
Well, what if I train a neural operator
surrogate over these parameter spaces?
So, that's another common example of
what we might learn.
In control theory, we have these sort of
source terms or nonlinearity terms.
They're very common also in in inverse
problems as well, okay? Where you might
have like for example, you cannot
measure the full PTE but only some part
of it. And so learning a mapping from
these force terms actually to you is
also a common example. I'm not going to
go too into detail. See me after if
you're if you're more interested in
problems. Okay. And of course the key is
that we're interested in learning this
over a bunch of domain shapes. So for
example, this room has a fixed layout.
Everybody's chairs are in the same
location. But if I move this chair over
here, the whole geometry of my PTE
changed for example, right? and how air
is going to flow in this room is going
to change. You open, you know, you move
your table to block your window, well,
you're not going to get the air flow.
So, this geometry generalization is
actually also a problem.
So, here's some examples of why we might
be interested in learning these
directions. There's quite a quite a bit
of variability in setting up the problem
and quite a set of things that can
change our problem um of which we would
want to know new solutions, right?
And so the idea is that okay our neural
network is some fast surrogate.
Okay. So I want to give you an idea of
what the structure of this neural
network design is going to look like
look like in a very high level in
practice. Okay. The idea is kind of as
you might imagine. What the first thing
you're going to do is we're going to
have to encode a function. And typically
to do that, we're going to have to do
some finite dimensional projection. So
like our friend said, we might have to
truncate the basis. For example,
we then need to do some finite
dimensional approximation between two
finite dimensional objects. And we're
going to see that actually this needs a
specific structure. So you guys know how
to actually approximate finite
dimensional mappings. Well, that's just
approximating a function.
It turns out when we need to approximate
an operator, we're going to need some
special structure. And we'll talk about
why.
And then lastly, we need to project back
some infinite dimensional space. So this
is a very high level idea of what our
overall structure is going to look like.
And it turns out when you follow this
sort of paradigm, a bunch of popular
designs come out.
Okay? And so let's go back to our
example that we talked about. We're
going to consider our 1D transport PTE
with zero boundary condition and initial
f ofx. And we want to learn the mapping
f ofx into the solution operator. Okay.
So that is for example given f ofx we
want to know the solution of the pd from
times 3 to 5. Okay. And this is how we
could you know say this mapping.
All right. And so the first question I
said is okay how are we going to think
about encoding this function f ofx and
the simplest way we can do it is just by
discretetizing and evaluating.
So consider that we define some points
x1 to xn over the domain 0 to one. These
could be uniformly spaced. So you could
think about it as like 0 0.1.2
all the way up to xn equals 1.
And we talked about how these points
might need to be close together that is
have a small time step to minimize our
error. We'll see that in a second. The
second thing is that okay let's evaluate
our function f at these points. Simple
enough. And then what we can do is we
can concatenate the evaluations and that
can be some vectorzed representation of
our function f.
Does anyone see any advantages to this
representation over maybe like the
symbolic one I gave here?
Any ideas?
No. Everybody thinks the symbolic one is
better. So,
what do you think?
Which one do you think is better?
Uh I would say they have disadvantage
and advantages for both. Okay. So the
nice thing about the symbolic one is
that I don't need to define these grid
points. You agree?
The bad thing about the symbolic one is
that I assumed some structure of my
functions. And here I have no assumption
on what f looks like.
So two different approaches, you know,
different cases for each. But actually
you could see that this one's pretty,
you know, it's a wider approach. But the
disadvantage is I have to choose these
points. And if I don't, for example, my
function is oscillating very, very fast.
It's going to be actually hard to
capture that function if I don't choose
the right point. So let me give you an
example. So for example, if I go here,
okay, this is x
and here's f ofx. Okay, and my function
looks like this. Okay, something like
this. And let's say it's it's periodic.
And I choose the points along this
periods. Okay, for whatever reason, you
know, uniformly space. Well, then is
that any different than encoding the the
straight line?
Because it's going to look exactly the
same, right? I'm going to choose those
same points. I'm going to get the same
values of f f ofx along that line. And
so it's a little bit tricky in that
okay, this is technically the same
representation to our neural operator,
but it's not unique here.
And so the point is that I need to
choose a sufficiently small distance
between the x points. So for example, if
instead of choosing, you know, every
period, I choose every, you know, fourth
period, I'll get points that look like
this, right? And then I'll get a much
better representation of my function.
Exactly. Yeah. It's it's it's
essentially how should you sample? Yeah.
Yeah. And so the point is, okay, if we
take a sampling based approach, we can
have problems with non-uniqueness if we
don't choose our points tight enough.
Well, you'll always have this
theoretically exist, but we have no
structure that we assumed. If we take a
symbolicist approach, we have some
structure. All right, make sense?
And so, okay, well, this is just one
idea of how to sample. There's a bunch
of other examples, but one thing I could
do is okay, I could take these F points
and then I could project them up to some
highdimensional space and let's let my,
you know, first layers, you know, neural
network actually do some interpolation
in that high dimensional space. That's
one way we could sort of think about
this sampling. Okay.
And like I said, this is going to have
some error because we have to choose
these points x1 to xn. But we can pass
it into a computer just like we saw in
the symbolic case over here.
All right. The next kind of key part I
told you in that sort of diagram is that
we're going to need to do finite
dimensional approximation.
And we're going to need to do this for
an operator. And so I think you guys all
recognize this form. Okay, we have a
sigmoid function, weight matrices W and
B.
For endural operator, we're going to
need to choose an architecture
that's a little bit more expressive than
that of the standard multi-layer
perceptron. And the inspiration behind
this is actually the same inspiration
behind how we chose the multi-layer
perceptron. So it turns out invented at
actually UCSD was one of the the main
mathematicians you can approximate any
function with this type of
representation. So maybe for example you
can do the same thing in polomials. So
you can represent any function by a set
of polomials. It's called the stone wire
straws theorem. Similar theorem it's
called the universal approximation
theorem for neural networks says that
you can approximate any function f by
this representation.
Well, you run into a problem when you're
interested in approximating
any neural operator by something like
this. And so what it turns out is you
need to add this new function or
operator which is essentially an
integral over every single point in your
space. Okay, so this would be every
single point in 0ero to one for example
for my PD
times some kernel representation and
we'll talk about this kernel in a minute
times okay the previous layer f
and this is called a non-local term and
the reason it's non-local is that we
have points here y that actually don't
depend on the point at which I'm trying
to evaluate my operator x
and so why do we need this non-local
term. Well, it turns out that we can
come back to that integral example that
I promised you. The integral example.
Okay, let's assume we have no analytical
form of this integral. Okay, so you know
it's not x^2 or something like that.
Well, then we could say, okay, if we
want to evaluate this integral at the
point y from 0 to y, it's going to
depend on all the points
between 0 and y,
right? That is, it depends on an
evaluation of f at points not valued at
y.
Does this make sense to everyone?
Okay. And so from this, okay, if we're
evaluating a points not needed to y, we
need to encode, if we're going to
approximate this integral, which is an
operator we talked about, we're going to
need to encode some of this non-local
structure. And it turns out one of the
simplest ways to do that is an integral
with this sort of extra term. Okay?
And so this is our structure. The
beginning part is again pointwise. It's
a machine learning perception. And the
non-local part here is, you know, an
integral. In practice, you'll turn this
into an approximation with a sum. This
kernel function will turn into a matrix
because it depends on x and y. Okay? And
f, of course, will be represented as a
vector. But you're going to have to do
this over every point y. And so you can
imagine that this is a really hard
problem to do.
And so actually, you've seen this
before. So our friend here told us about
the convolutional neural network and we
actually see this kernel come up. If I
choose xus y I get a convolution.
We're because we're not trying to
approximate any function anymore. We're
trying to approximate any operator,
right? And so when we're trying to
approximate any operator, it's sort of
an abstract level up. Does that make
sense? We're asking actually more. And
so like for example the integral
operator right depends on a bunch of
points
another term essentially. Yeah. Yeah.
Because essentially that's what this
non-local term is for. Yep. So it's it's
inspired from this universal
approximation theorem but it actually
recovers a lot of beauty from what you
can see you've already seen. So for
example you can get a convolution and it
turns out you can implement this
convolution with a forier transform as I
think many of you guys know and this
actually recovers a forier neural
operator.
Another example is actually in self
attention. So I spare you the details
here but there's a way to show that the
self attention mechanism in a
transformer can be transformed into a
kernel that looks something like this.
So you have an exponential and an inner
product between two weight matrices the
query and key matrices times f ofx and f
of y.
It's I know a little bit of a stretch
but I promise you that there's a nice
paper on it and see me after class if
you want to know more.
Okay. And lastly we needed to think
about that third component in our
architecture and that's the decoder
component. Okay. and the decoder
component. Remember we wanted to have
one key property. We wanted to think
about if we could have this
discretization invariance property that
is you know we can evaluate it at any
target point. All right. And it turns
out that there's a lot of ways to do
this and we really need to talk about it
from an architecture to architecture
perspective. And so at the end of the
day you're doing some sort of projection
but I can't really give you a general
form. Okay. And so we'll see for example
one architecture today a deep net which
I think you may have read about that
where the decoder is actually sort of
this trunk network.
All right. And so let me give you a high
level idea of what we talked about as a
as a main structure. So we have this
encoder that obtains some pointwise
representation or some symbolic
representation.
We need to perform a neural network
approximation with this second kernel
term.
And lastly we do some sort of projection
back and I know this is very very
abstract as I've given it to you but
that's the general structure. Okay. And
so we'll give you an example in a second
of what this structure actually looks
like. All right. But first, we have a
participation quiz.
Web clicker. Yeah, if you just Google
web clicker, it should come up.
Okay. Oh, I can see the results. Okay.
Sweet.
How many usually respond? 100.
150. Okay.
You have like 70.
Give it a couple seconds.
Also, this is like a very general
question. So, think generally like what
is going to be faster to solve. I know
like some cases you may have one faster
than the other.
about 115.
Maybe we could keep it open for a couple
minutes, but I'll continue. Okay, so it
looks like from this web clicker, 80% of
you said A ODEs are faster and 20% of
you said B PTE are faster. Let's say for
those 20% that said B,
let me ask you if my grid consists of
say 10 billion points and my OD grid,
let's say I need to solve it over XYZ
and T and my OD grid only represents T,
which one do you think is going to be
more expensive?
Yeah. And so it turns out the answer is
A. ODEs are much faster to simulate
because I don't have that spatial
dimension on average. Okay.
Okay. And so let's go through an example
and we'll actually look at a specific
architecture the deep to give you guys a
little bit of instantiation because at
this point we've done a little bit of
abstract math. Okay. And so in practice
what is this training paradigm going to
look like compared to our classical
solver? Well, the first thing is we're
going to need some input output pairs to
train from. It's a supervised learning
task. And how are we going to generate
these trails? Well, we're going to run
those supercomputers for a while. Okay.
And the key is that okay, maybe I'm
building a new data center. And part of
the infrastructure that I'm thinking
about when I'm building my data center
is not just actually building it, but I
paid for some compute power, you know,
or I'm I'm Google. I use my own TPUs and
I actually spent two three weeks solving
PDEs all day, okay, for various
conditions, various initial conditions,
various parameters. And this sort of
allowed me to build my data set,
supervised learning data split, okay,
and then what you're going to consider
is some sort of loss function that looks
something like an L2 loss of the
following form. So the key is that okay
my neural network or my approximation I
represent with this calligraphy g of
theta okay it's going to take some input
representation of f and some query
points xjt and we're going to compare it
to the solution at those query points in
an L2 fashion. Okay. Another thing that
people actually commonly do in PTEES is
called an H1 loss, which means that they
actually don't just compare these in an
L2 fashion, but they also compare their
spatial derivatives as well, which we
can actually get by calculating for
example uh the gradient and actually
PyTorch can do this for you for free or
you can approximate the spatial
derivatives with some finite
differencing if you don't know it for
example. Okay, so typically modern PTE
structures will actually use the H1
loss, but we're going to consider an L2.
Keep things simple. Okay, and I is my
set of PTEs that I solved. So I think
one highle question for you guys is, is
this sum over J or the sum over I going
to be a larger number of points that we
sum over?
Yeah, exactly. J because J is over the
whole spatial grid. I is over the number
of PDs we solved.
Yeah, go ahead.
So, actually, okay. So when we it turns
out PTE's solutions may not be
continuous and so we get this notion of
called a weak solution and weak solution
means that essentially the solution of
the PD only holds when you inner product
it with some test function.
uh keep the so with that in mind what
people usually say is that weak
solutions live in this space H1
and H1 is defined as not just the L2
norm but the L2 norm plus the L2 norm on
the gradients.
So it comes from a mathematical
inspiration at a high level. I can give
you more about it after class.
Practically, you might also be asking
about practically it depends on the PTE.
So a PTE that actually doesn't
necessarily change that much, you might
be happy with the L2 norm, but a PTE
where you have high variation, so for
example, shocks, you could think about
you might want to include that gradient
because it'll help your training
stability.
Okay? because you you know it's going to
be hard to learn how quickly you're
moving in your solution and the
gradients can sort of help you predict
that. Does it make sense? You can take
can take you more after less.
So you don't the solution to the PD
isn't continuous.
Yeah. So that's what's called a weak
solution. So basically yeah let's we
let's talk after class actually.
Yeah or you can ask chat GP to explain
and it'll be actually helpful like this
is a good thing to use chatgbt for. Um
but yeah it's it's basically you don't
have a good sense of what continuity is.
So you you do can inner product with a
test function. The rule for that test
function is it needs to be infinitely
different differentiable and that sort
of gives you the continuity um that you
need.
Yeah. Yeah. But there's a lot of theory
there. Book to read is Evans if you
want.
Okay. And then you're going to do back
propagation as per usual. And actually
all the terms that I've shown you so
far, the kernel, the encoder and the de
well we haven't talked about the decoder
but are all easy to back propagate. So
we don't have this problem with the
neural OD where we have to define these
adjint dynamics and back propagate
through this this way. Maybe you could
do something like that. I haven't
thought about that. Okay. And so the
problem you may ask is okay well I have
to generate this training data. It's
going to take me three weeks to do so.
why didn't I just solve my PTE in my
training data like what is the point of
doing this and the point is that you get
an amateurization right so if for
example you train your PTE and then you
slightly modify your parameters for
example your construction company for
whatever reason screwed up your building
dimensions maybe you have bigger
problems than this but you
can still adapt to that situation for
example and so that's the the kind of
point is that you pay the solver cost
once
Let's say you pay that three weeks once
and then you can use this sort of neural
network surrogate as often as you want
and your data center engineer can use it
every day.
All right. And so any questions here
kind of this is a highle idea of of
where our neural network is going to
look like and where we're going from a
training pipeline perspective.
Great. Okay. Okay. And so let me give
you an example of one architecture. This
one is called the deep onet. It stands
for deep operator network. It was
actually a rediscovery by George
Carneadakis at Brown. And it's a
rediscovery of a 1995 paper by these two
authors. They're both last name Chen. So
it's called the Chen and Chen paper. And
it essentially gives the first neural
network structure that's provably
approximable for an operator. And so
what is the idea of this structure?
Well, the encoding is going to stay the
same that we talked about. We're going
to have these X1 to XN representations.
Okay? And we're going to pass these
through something called a branch
network. Okay? And the each branch
network, let's say there's P of them,
we'll talk about what P is a second, can
be, for example, an MLP. Okay? And that
MLP is going to receive the entire set
of F values.
And so then each MLP is say let's say it
outputs some vector BP or B1 B2 BN all
the way up to P. Okay. So that's the
first sort of encoding.
The second sort of encoding that we're
going to have is comes in our decoder
and we're going to define this thing
called a trunk network.
And what this trunk network takes in is
the point at which we want to evaluate
our operator function. So for our
integral case, this is that y point that
controls the upper limit of our
integral. Okay. And this is going to
actually project this output into a
vector
of p length as well.
And then what we're going to do is we're
going to take the dotproduct between
these two outputs.
All right. So just to recap again, we
have P different neural networks in our
branches. Okay, each one takes the full
vector representation of f and it
outputs let's say a scalar.
Meanwhile, the trunk network is a single
neural network. It takes a single point
location y finite dimensional and it
outputs or upwards projects into p
different scalar values output and then
we can take dotproducts between two
vectors right to get our for example
scaler in our output right and so this
is the whole deep net architecture and I
promise you that this is a neural
operator architecture and it might not
be clear at first but we'll see in a
second okay and so where does the
inspiration comes from well it comes
from this idea A that we can represent
any function by a basis and eventually
that basis we can truncate it and we'll
have some error but we can truncate it
right so what we're going to say is that
we're going to say okay any function can
be written as this decomposition from i=
1 to p ci is some coefficients and fi of
y is our basis functions
and so like one example you guys know of
this for example is if I choose a 4a
series that is I let fi of y be this
sign. So cosine series, right?
And so the idea of a deep net is that
instead of fixing either one of these,
we're going to learn both of them. Okay?
So we're going to treat this trunk
network as our actual basis at that
point Y. And we're going to treat the
branch network is outputting
coefficients over our basis. Okay? And
so this is the whole idea of our deep
net. And then of course if P is large
enough we approximate any operator
structure.
All right.
And so like I was saying that we have
two jobs. So the branch that's going to
read the input function and it's going
to give coefficients for our basis. And
the idea is okay given an input f what
is the right mixture for our output
operator function?
And the trunk net is going to do the
same thing except it's going to generate
our point dependent basis.
And you may ask like why does this basis
need to be point dependent? It's not
obvious here, but in fact, if you for
example wanted to build a basis for your
function, for example, the 4A series,
you know that the signs and cosiness are
still going to depend on that point Y,
right? So, taking in inspiration from
that, we still need for example Y as an
input to this basis. But the important
thing about the basis is that they don't
actually depend on our input function to
our operator.
So, it's sort of this separable
deconstruction.
And the idea is that this architecture
emits a super resolution or
discretization invariant property
because okay I can train this
architecture over a set of points Y and
basis functions B. But then what I can
do is I can say okay if I want to know
it at some slightly different point well
my trunk net can estimate a basis for
that new point you know let's say call
it yhat without retraining
as long as you know it's within
distribution we have enough training
data so on and so on
and so that's where we actually get this
discretization of variance and okay why
does it matter well if we need a super
high resolution grid we can sort of let
the neural network do the interpolation
for us. All right.
And so then, okay, this architecture
looks a little different than what we
talked about for the first hour today,
right? So, let's see what it actually
looks like in that representation. And
here's my claim. The deep net is a
neural operator layer with a specific
simple choice of kernel.
And what does it look like? Well, it
looks like the following. Okay, the
first thing is that I promised you that
this neural operator had three parts. It
had the original multi-layer perceptron,
a non-local term and the sigmo
activation function.
And so what I can do is I can first say
okay let's get rid of this first part
and let's just treat w is z b as zero
and sigma as the identity.
Some simplifying assumptions then I get
something that just looks like the
kernel.
And so my claim is that the deep on net
is actually this kernel with a certain
representation. So remember the kernel
looks like this over the whole domain x.
Okay. And it turns out that if I choose
my kernel to be the sum of two things,
my output from my trunk network and a
set of coefficients.
Okay. Then what I will get when I plug
in this sort of low rank representation
is something that looks like this,
right?
Using the fact that ti of y does not
depend on this integral x I can pull it
out
and then I can say okay I'm going to
treat this sort of non-local kernel all
inside those BF branch functions.
All right. And so then I actually
recover the full structure of a neural
operator in a in a simplified way.
All right. Any questions here? Does it
make sense how the two parts connect and
how the deep net is one example of an
instantiation of this design?
Great.
Okay. And so let's talk about deep net
and some of the the features of perhaps
one of the first I meanet and forier
neural operator which we'll talk about
on Thursday are kind of you know brother
and sister in their inventions.
So like I promised you it can query the
neural network at any desired trunk
location y and we can use this for a
sort of super resolution property
although it does not work that well in
practice. I'm going to be honest with
you, but that's that's one at least
inherent idea in the architecture.
One thing is that we didn't actually
tell you that the branch and the trunk
networks needed to be MLPS. They could
be a CNN, you could use a transformer.
Um, such extensions are available and
kind of well studied.
I promised you that we would get these
sort of universal approximation
guarantees that we wanted from our
neural networks and we still do have
that. So the theory people are happy
and we have some pretty interesting
results for these basis vectors
actually. And so what I want to show you
is something kind of neat. So this is
from the original depotet paper. And on
the left we're learning an invection
diffusion PTE. So we're learning the
solution of a PTE mapping. Okay,
excuse me. From the initial condition to
some po point in the future. And on the
left I have is the mean squared error.
Okay. And on the bottom right I have is
the number of basis functions that I
choose P.
And what I'm showing here on the left is
essentially the mean squared over as I
choose more basis functions. And it's
you see notice it's log scale. So what I
see is the following. Eventually okay I
have a serious overfitting in the
beginning with too many basis functions
and a large train test gap.
Okay. And then as I go further along, my
training error sort of stabilizes. Okay.
So if I'm just looking at training
error, I'm not going to see pretty much
any improvement, but the test error kind
of converges to the training error as I
increase more basis functions. And you
can see you can imagine a thousand's a
lot of basis functions, right? That's I
mean you could think of that as a
thousand different uh MLP layers. Of
course, you can stack them in a good way
to make it efficient, but that's the
idea.
And so this kind of shows you okay
here's how we scale with the number of
basis functions kind of how good are we
approximating our operator and how much
are we sort of truncating.
My second diagram here
is the number of points
okay in our training data. This is
essentially okay the number of views I
solved three weeks ago for my data
center. Okay. And what I see is that
okay with I don't have many points I get
an overfitting exact same property and
as I have about a thousand different PTE
solutions I start to converge between
train and test error okay and you can
imagine okay if I have a thousand
different PTE solutions that's a pretty
expensive set of solves for a 3D
geometry
but it gives you kind of scaling laws
for how to think about this deep on net
if you train one yourself right any
questions make sense
All right.
Okay.
Disadvantages of deep net. Any ideas?
Any questions? Yes sir. Go ahead.
Um
yeah maybe maybe you could. The uh the
thing is though the the point about the
deep net right is we didn't actually
specify that the neural networks have to
be an MLP right so we could actually
maybe have skip connections between
those basis branch functions but you are
on the right track in that okay yeah the
branch and trunk functions are separable
it's a pretty big assumption actually
that our operator can be represented by
these two basis decompositions and
actually it turns out like yes you can
represent every operator theoretically
But in practice is that separable
assumption so good and it turns out no.
And yeah, there's a paper kind of built
off this idea. It's called Nomad where
they sort of instead of doing that dot
product at the end between the branch
and trunk, they pass both of those
outputs into another neural network. So
they concatenate and pass. That's one
one idea. other ideas there's there's
more than one of course
lot of data points and a lot of solver
time and that is a that's a fair
complaint of any neural operator
architecture I think but let me ask you
like what can you do that's better
no no no I'm saying like is there any
paradigm out there that is nasisly
better than this sort amateurized idea
if you need to evaluate something really
quickly.
Can you think of one? Because there is
one any ideas.
So in I I give you in our dynamics I
told you this room the proper dynamics
for it are PTE right but do you think
that okay from you know air up okay I'm
not very tall but you can imagine 10 ft
higher all the dynamics is pretty much
the same there's not a huge geometry so
do I really need a PTE to solve those
dynamics well maybe I could use a
reduced order model which is just a
simpler model I might be giving up
something in terms of my accuracy, but I
might speed it up in terms of solver
time. And so people have designed these
classical reduced order model designs.
They're very popular in control theory.
Um that that can work, but usually
they're problem dependent and they
really like require a PhD or or not or
some not a PhD but someone who is really
familiar with the design of that area to
to sort of build out. So, but that is an
option and so that is kind of a paradigm
that maybe is better than neural
operators at the top off the top of your
head if you have that huge domain
expertise.
So, yeah, good answer.
I'll give you some more examples. So, as
you said the linear combination is a
little bit non-expressive in that dot
product. Another thing is that what you
talked about the sample efficiency it
requires a lot of data.
One thing that we didn't really talk
about is this resolution m mismatch. And
so if all of my data comes on the same
uniform grid every single time, that is
I choose the same x values, the same y-v
values, this super resolution property
can really fall apart. I need to choose
sufficiently interesting grid
representations. And there's an entire
kind of paper on how to choose these
grid representations is something we've
looked into. I also the pin community
has looked quite a bit into it which
we'll see in two lectures.
And so with that I want to leave you
guys and and you can see this sort of on
the slides of a bunch of extensions that
may be interesting for those who who are
valid. So the exact one I was talking
about that you mentioned was nomad that
was a paper I think 2022.
um all these paper links in in in
parenthesis you can click on them on the
uploaded slides in canvas. Okay, so just
to keep that in mind. Another thing is
that yeah it's actually interesting of
whether or not you enforce some
structure into the encoder and decoder.
Another thing is multiscale deep which
kind of considers this non-uniform grid
challenge. They actually consider it
over time though. So you want to
actually evaluate things on let's say
like a nancond scale, a microscond
scale, millisecond scale, so on and so
forth. You can get sort of different
approximations at each time
and then we can see some interesting
ideas about how you know a deep onet
right now does not consider the temporal
correlations between its points and
there's been some ideas about embedding
RNNs inside of that. Okay. And lastly,
with any machine learning model, we can
do uncertainty quantification, which
we'll talk about kind of in four or five
lectures about what that means in more
detail. All right. And so with that,
I'll leave you with a little bit of hint
for next time. Hopefully, you guys can
take a look at the Forier neural
operator paper. It's another
architecture. It uses that sort of
convolution kernel design and it's going
to approximate it with with a 4A series.
And so yeah, with that I'll see you guys
on Thursday.