So just to just to recap last time,
just to recap last time, we introduced
this idea of an operator, right? And can
someone give me some examples of
operators that we did not talk about
last time? Anyone
got an idea,
guys? Some of you are going to just
become victims, I think.
Sir, over here, any example of an
operator we didn't talk about last time.
Yeah, in the tan. In the tan. Yes.
Anything. Any sort of oper. What about
one we did talk about last time?
A derivative. Great. How about you, sir?
And the laptop
operator we talked about or didn't talk
about last time. Any ideas?
Integral. Integral. Right. I think you
guys know a lot more. So, for example,
an identity operator, the most trivial
one. Projection operators. So, you've
definitely seen this one. I think of
course we're going to talk about Forier
neuro operators today. Kind of a gimme
is a forier operator. How many of you
have taken a dynamical systems class?
Anyone? Anyone anybody have nightmares
of applause transforms? They're also an
operator. Um, and so yeah, as we talked
about last time, many of the problems
you guys already know can be formulated
as operator learning problems, right?
And so what did we discuss were the
three components of a quote neural
operator? Well, the first kind of
component that we had was we had this
encoder, right? And this encoder was
important. It was a way to represent
this continuous thing, a function in a
vectorzed form for a computer. Okay. And
the second kind of key point that we
introduced was this new layer
architecture, right? Where we have our
traditional MLP over here. And then we
introduced this non-local kernel term.
Okay? And remember this point of this
non-local term was that many operators
are going to depend on points that we
don't want to evaluate them at. So
remember for example our integral
depends on all the points between zero
and y, right? And we saw one example of
this kernel and we're going to see
another one today about how to sort of
decompose this really expensive
intractable integral, right? because you
know if we imagine this is over every
point in our space we have to evaluate
some sort of weight matrix over all
points in our space um it can blow up
quite quickly and then the last thing
that we were interested in is the
decoder and the key point or property we
wanted to to introduce in our decoder
was this idea of discretization and
variance right that is we can query our
neural network sort of at any target
point all right
and so here's kind of a little highle
diagram we talked about last time about
how neural operators sort of function
and and the main components, right? And
so what did we introduce? Well, we
introduced one idea, a deep net. And the
idea of a deep net is we're sort of
approximating a truncated basis for
operator learning, right? And so what we
had is we said, okay, any function is
going to admit some sort of basis
decomposition. And remember we talked
about that functions live in infinite
dimensional spaces, right? And so this
this approximation with a sum of course
in reality would have to be to infinity.
So for example a 4A series. And so we
said okay let's let our neural network
learn these two objects of a truncated
basis. And of course we're going to
introduce some error but it's okay.
And so we said okay the first set of
objects that we're going to learn are
these set of CIS. Essentially, we're
going to represent them by a neural
network. And this is going to become our
our branch network. And the second set
of objects we're going to learn is sort
of the basis components at the position
that we want to evaluate our neural
network. This is why, right? And so we
built this architecture. It looks like
this. On the right, we had a branch
network which takes in our function
samples. It outputs P different basis
coefficients. And the idea is how do we
mix the bases which is also learned from
our trunk network. This trunk network
reads our target location, outputs the
true values of the basis and estimates
kind of what these basis functions will
look like and then of course as in you
know linear algebra we did a dotproduct
to sort of combine these things right
okay and so this formulation we're going
to see is actually extremely general
it's going to be a little bit powerful
especially today when we talk about
forier neural operators and so the key
kind of idea a of the deep on net was
that we assumed our kernel matrix here
was sort of a separable low rank
structure right we're injecting some
structure into this kernel matrix in
order to make this integral tractable
and so we did this derivation in class
and I kind of give you a link to a a
little bit more detailed derivation but
the idea is okay we can write our kernel
function as a sum of our basis where our
trunk is dotted with that learned branch
outputs right Okay. And so I'm going to
introduce the idea of F and O from the
same starting point. That is we're
interested in approximating this
integral, but we're going to introduce a
different structure on this kernel
matrix. And so the idea is we're going
to introduce this structure of
translation and variance. Basically,
we're going to let K be a function of Y
minus S, okay? For any of its two
inputs. And so what we get is we get
something that looks like this. the
integral over all of X times K and the
previous layers output, right? And we
talked about this last time. This is a
convolution.
And the key kind of point of this, why
we're interested in this is we have this
famous theorem. I think since you guys
are ECE students, you probably know it
quite well, that says that convolution
in physical space can become pointwise
multiplication in for space. And so for
those of you not familiar with this
theorem, I actually uploaded a note
right before this lecture kind of
proving this for you. So it's in it's in
a review note if you want to take a
look. But the key is that okay, we have
a way sort of to implement this
practical integral by using Forier
transforms.
And it turns out that basically every
property that we're going to we're going
to look at today depends on
understanding when and where this 4A
transform applies. Well,
All right. And one kind of advantage of
doing this sort of forier transform
compared to like let's say injecting a
separable kernel is we'll see that we
get a set of frequencies that we'll
truncate to modes and when we tr care
about the inverse for a transform we can
sort of pick the resolution that we're
going to um convert back to and we'll
see that a little bit more spelled out
in a minute. All right. Okay. So any
questions here about the idea of this
this new kernel and separability the
convolution theorem how many of you are
familiar with convolution theorem seen
it before
okay actually not too many so take a
look at that review sheet but yeah okay
and so here's kind of a review sorry for
those who raised your hand but it seems
like most of you haven't seen it the
idea is okay we have a convolution of
two functions over some integral and
usually this integral from like in
signal processing you might have seen it
from minus infinity to infinity right
and the idea is that the fora transform
just becomes a pointwise product of
sorry the convolution of a or the 4a
transform of a convolution becomes the
pointwise product of the forier
transforms okay basically we get this
nice decomposition
it all comes from using oilers's
identity which basically is the idea
that ss and cosiness can be written as
exponentials
And essentially we also get that the
inverse applies. So if we apply the
inverse warrior transform to this
product we recover the original
convolution. It's pretty important that
we can actually go both ways because if
we want to sort of analyze this this
structure, right? We need sort of this
this bjection kind of idea. And this
actually comes up a lot in control. So
for your differential equations, not
only did you care about the forward
directional applause transform, but the
reason your solution actually works is
because the inverse direction will form
a bjection.
And so the whole idea of this forier
neural operator is is actually pretty
simple. It's this integral operator here
is intractable. So we introduce some
structure on the kernel and then we just
have to pay the cost of two FFTs to do
our multiplication.
All right. And so let's go back to our
example that we saw last time on this
famous transport PTE. Okay. And so the
operator we're going to want to learn is
the same thing as we learned last time.
We have some initial condition F. Okay.
And we want to learn the mapping to the
solution of this transport t at say t =
0.5 seconds. All right. And the same
sort of idea holds that we did last
time. So what we're going to do
essentially is we're going to
numerically solve this PTE with our
expensive PTE solver and we're going to
build a data set. And this data set we
had to use a very small discretization
size to actually ensure numerical
stability in our classical solver. And
we're interested in training an FNO
that's going to sort of save us this
amateurized cost.
So this is the problem we're going to
work with throughout today's lecture.
And I think most of you are comfortable
with it now.
And so what does our data set look like?
Well, it's essentially this matrix
uh where what I'm using for the
subscript on the numbers is the number
of datas. So, this is the number of
different solves of our system. So, for
example, we have capital n different
data points. So, we ran our numerical
solver n times. And let's assume that we
have a resolution of 101 grid points x.
We can assume it's uniformly
distributed. And we'll we'll look at it
as an example. And the goal is to learn
this outside or this supervised result.
Again, basically the data set and the
key difference is that we're trying to
learn it at this capital time t, which
in this case will take 0.5 seconds.
Okay.
All right. And the key property that
we're going to try to ask for today is a
little bit different than the one we
asked for last time. Okay. So we'll see
that due to the forier transform we have
to ask for a uniform grid. So that is
the samples x1 to x101 are uniformly
spaced. Okay. And so the the notion of
discretization and variance is going to
have to keep that sort of uniformity to
hold. That is unlike our deep net where
we could query it at any target point Y.
We're going to see that we can query it
at a new set of target points Y1 to YN.
But these need some structure. Okay. And
you'll see the reason for this basically
comes down to the fact that we have some
assumptions on whether or not our forier
transform will actually work. Okay. And
so this property here is a little bit
stronger than discretization and
variance. And we'll see what that looks
like in a in a few minutes.
All right. And so what's the idea of a
forier layer or neural operator? It's
actually super simple and I think you
guys will pick it up quickly given our
deep net. So basically the idea is we
take our previous layers output. In this
case I'm assuming I'm doing the first
layer and I have samples X1 to XN and I
evaluate F by applying a 4A transform on
this vector. Okay. from that forier
transform what I'm going to do is I'm
going to get a vector in frequency space
and that frequency space vector all I'm
going to do is multiply it by some
learnable matrix okay just like we would
have done in our MLP so the only
difference is that we did this forier
transform first
so we have a forier transform times a
learnable matrix and then we're going to
do an inverse forier transform
and you may ask me like okay How is it
is it a real pain to compute for example
gradients across a 4A transform? It
turns out uh we'll see in a minute the
discrete 4A transform turns into a
series of sum of exponentials and we
know how to compute gradients of sum of
exponentials quite well. The first thing
I kind of want to give you is that like
why why are we doing this? Why do we
care about this idea at a forier space?
um how could you have written this paper
yourself uh with you know 10,000
citations um and so okay the first thing
is that you know 4A 4A series as you
guys know from signal processing give us
a sense of of compression now there's no
avoiding like a lossless information uh
type object but essentially we kind of
think about this dominant frequency case
where if we only are interested in the
highle shape of something we don't care
so much about the jagged details. We can
approximate that function with a very
few number of modes and we'll actually
see this is a negative as well in that
it's hard for example our friend in the
back actually asked a question it's hard
to learn high frequency modes of
functions and this is a well-known idea
developed by Benio famous Turing award
winner who who basically said that
neural networks kind of only learn these
low frequencies u in the beginning.
The second thing is okay we talked about
this integral and the problem of
computing this integral right was that
we had to learn it over all of space and
so in this case here what we've done is
we basically said okay the integral
becomes two ffts and a multiplication
if we can parallelize the FFT we're even
better and actually when this paper came
out FFTs were not a naive or native
object of torch so you can imagine the
original authors authors actually had to
write the DFT out themselves and do the
back prop. Now CUDA has its own FFT team
actually I think and FFT is a member of
torch so you guys get to sort of save
that a little bit in your homework.
Okay. And then the lastly we're going to
see this this sort of resolution
flexibility that is like okay we do this
discrete 4A transform and we're going to
get a representation in terms of
frequencies
then when we want to go back for example
we can kind of pick the resolution that
we're going to transfer back of course
we have to be careful about information
loss and we'll talk about that at the
end but you see okay this is kind of an
interesting place to learn right we have
some ideas from from differential
equations about compression we see that
it helps us approximate our integral and
we're going to talk about this idea of
super resolution.
Okay, so let's talk about 4A transforms
kind of given your poll results.
I think it's pretty well known that a
signal okay can be represented as a set
of frequencies
okay with various weights on their
omegas right and so for example this is
a continuous forier transform of any
function f ofx right and in practice
okay imagine you have you know some I
use minus infinity to infinity here to
represent the whole space but for
example if your domain of f ofx only
lives on 0 to one you could treat
everything outside of that as zero,
right? Okay.
And then in the same way we have this
inverse 4A transform, exact same thing
except the exponential is no longer
negative. And this takes what our
representation is in frequency space and
turns it back into actual space. Right?
And so the key kind of point here is
that like I was saying and this is the
kind of the way you prove the
convolution theorem same exact idea is
that Oilers's theorem is basically
saying that these two transforms are
just a weighted sum of ss and cosiness
okay
essentially if I plug this in right I
get a co cosine omega x plus i sin omega
x in this case you'll have the minus and
essentially what we're saying is that
functions can kind of be represented as
borier series, right?
And I assume for most of you given your
chart, this is at least familiar. You've
seen this idea before. Not going to
spend too much time on it, right? And so
here's an example of what we're talking
about when we say frequency. Very, very
simple. High frequency is essentially
fast oscillation or or a very small
period. And likewise, low frequency is
this sort of low oscillation. And so the
point is that we'll see that lower
frequency modes that is the
overgeneraliz or the slower kind of
oscillation are going to be easier to
learn. Why would you actually like care
about this in your problems? So for
example, if you're interested in shocks,
right? You're going to have very
discontinuous movements, especially if
your PTE only has a weak solution. And
it turns out that's actually really hard
to learn. So you might be trying this,
trying this, trying this, and you'll run
into some issues.
Okay. And so now we kind of did a quick
quick review of 4A transforms. What we
actually care about is this object
called the discrete 4A transform. Okay.
And basically it's just a discretization
of the actual one. So what we're going
to do is we're going to first turn that
integral into an approximation via a
sum. And the second thing that we're
going to do is that we have to choose a
set of discrete values for omega. Right?
Just like we had to choose a set of x
points to evaluate our function. Okay?
And we're going to call these omega
discrete values modes. Essentially,
we're going to use the integer k. K is
just going to represent a modes one to
n. And these are essentially the
frequencies that we have to kind of
pre-implement.
All right? And so what do we get? Well,
we get something that looks like the
following. Here we have our original
function over xj. So for example in our
transport PTE this was the 101 points we
discretetized over and then what we get
on the right is essentially that same
exact integral we added a 2 pi to kind
of represent the frequency and we'll see
why we did this in a minute
as well as a
uh k overn where k is essentially our
frequency points. Okay.
And so the key kind of thing that we're
going to use today is okay we promised
that this architecture was going to take
the forier transform of its previous
layer multiply it by a weightric weight
matrix and take the inverse transform
and of course in practice we're going to
have to use a discrete forier transform
and so if we're going to use this object
we need to think about the assumptions
that that it originally had and the
reason why we care about the assumptions
they're going to affect our engineering
design.
And so the first big assumption that
this object has is that the samples from
x0 to xm minus one are essentially one
period of our signal. Okay. And why is
this important? Well, you know, many PTE
initial conditions will not be periodic,
right? Uh you can imagine
that we start this room at some initial
condition. it's likely to not be
periodic given that you know back there
the geometry of the room is definitely
going to influence the air flow more
than out here due to the seating
architecture right
and so this is going to be we're going
to apply a little bit of an engineering
trick here where we pad zeros on the end
of our input and we'll talk about this a
little bit later but it's kind of just a
trick
thing that a DFT assumes is that our
spacing is uniform that is the
difference between all the points is
some dx. Okay. And this is going to
actually limit that ability to query at
any point that we had in our deep net.
And then I promised you we'd talk about
why does a 2 pi show up in the exponent
of our dft. And it's not that
complicated. I mean I think you could
imagine it's just a normalization
coefficient. And essentially what it
says is okay we know that s and cosine
complete one revolution over 2 pi. And
we know that we're going to assume that
our samples are periodic that is that is
equivalent to one revolution. Okay. And
so what we do is we basically say okay
let's treat this factor 2 pi divided by
the modes to be approximately one
revolution depending on the first mode
two revolutions for the second and then
you know k resolutions for the kth mode.
Okay. And basically this is going to
tell us okay how much what frequencies
are we going to choose to decompose our
signal at. Okay so k equals 1 is
obviously the weakest frequency kals 2
we have two so on and so forth.
Any questions here? Kind of a review of
forier transforms dft assumptions.
Okay great.
Okay. And so what is the the cost of
this DFT? Right? Because the whole point
of this is we needed to approximate that
intractable integral in our problem.
And it turns out the cost of the DST is
as follows.
For each of the modes, if we implemented
a DFT exactly as you know we saw the
equation, what we would get is an O of N
squared implementation. Okay? Because
for each mode if we go back
you can see here okay for each mode we
need to consider okay a sum over n minus
one points where each n minus one points
is is over a whole set of space. Okay so
if we had 101 points here we would need
101 squared to evaluate all of these for
k from 0 to n minus one. Very clear. So
it's an n squared operation
and actually this is not so nice.
It turns out that in practice you can do
a little bit better. So does anyone know
what the the best algorithm known today
can achieve
or discrete 4A transform? Yeah,
you got it exactly. So there's a famous
algorithm in 1965 before chat GPT where
these two guys Kulie and Tur Tuki sorry
Kulie and Tuki invented this algorithm.
Actually one of them is still alive
today which is kind of insane but uh
that invented this algorithm that
basically lets you do this FFT and
login. Okay, how many of you have seen
that before?
Okay, decent number of you. Okay, so for
those who have seen it before, great. If
you haven't seen it before, maybe ask
chat GBPt for its implementation. But
for now, we're not going to ask you to
implement it. It's it's basically uses a
trick where you basically can compute in
both directions at the same time by
reusing sums. It's kind of high level
idea and you you could maybe figure it
out. And so why does this care? Well,
each layer of our 4A neural operator of
which we're going to stack, you know,
anywhere from five to 10 layers has to
do this computation.
Okay. And so let's kind of recomputee
what this this whole architecture looks
like. Then I'll give you an example and
then we'll kind of go into some of the
nits and pieces. Okay. So again we take
inputs x0 to x n minus one and these are
just sampled and we have to assume that
these are uniformly sampled. Okay. And
what are we going to do? Well we're
going to apply this fft to our inputs
and we're going to get n different
coefficients for our k values. Right?
And it turns out this is a n login
operation.
Then we're going to multiply by a weight
matrix
and we're going to apply inverse FFT
which is also done in n login. Okay. And
so basically the cost of the extra fora
transform is essentially n log or 2 * n
log n plus the multiplication of a
weight matrix which I think we know how
to do really really well. Okay. And so
the question that you might all go ask
is is there a limit to the number of
modes K? How much does this matter?
Well, essentially there's something
called the Nyquis frequency which
basically says that if I have n
different uniform points, how much
information can I extract out of those n
without aliasing?
Um, and we'll see an example of what
this looks like in a minute, but the
point is that the max amount of
information you can actually encode is n
/2.
Okay? And so basically, if I have, for
example, let's say 101 points, the max
number of frequencies I would use to uh
to guarantee something lossless is
something like 56 frequencies, right? Or
no, sorry, 51 frequencies, right? You
would take the ceiling of n /2. Okay?
And so why does this matter? Well, it
turns out we're going to have to choose
the number of modes in our 4A neural
operator. And if we want to do things
like super resolution, which we'll talk
about in a minute, the number of modes
is actually really going to matter for
exactly how good can we get. And there's
actually a paper uh by a friend of mine
written just this last year and I clear
about where this sort of breaks down.
And so here's the full design of our
FNO. Essentially what we have here is
the forier layer that we talked about.
So we take our previous input, we do a
forier transform, we multiply by a
weight matrix R, take the inverse input.
And the second kind of component that
they have in this layer is just
multiplication of the original previous
layer by a weight matrix. Okay, so sort
of that MLP structure that we talked
about before. In the original FNO paper,
they didn't have any bias term. So we
could set the bias term to zero. And
this is sort of our forier layer. Okay.
Now, what I haven't told you about yet
is the sort of encoding and decoding
structure of a fora neural operator and
what that looks like. Okay. And
essentially what it looks like is just
projection.
And what do I mean by projection? Well,
I mean the following. So for every grid
point that we have, essentially we're
going to apply a basis MLP neural
network to it. Okay. So imagine that we
have x subi. It's just a grid point.
Let's say a scalar.
What we're going to do is we're going to
take an MLP that takes each s of and
projects it up to a d-dimensional value.
And this is what's meant by our original
encoding essentially.
What basically you're happening here is
is you're taking this shape of size n
let's say for example where each one of
these is a scalar and we're projecting
up to a shape of size n by d. Okay, so
for each f ofx of i, we basically expand
to a feature vector of size d. And this
is going to be actually really valuable
here because you see that nothing here
actually depends on how many numbers xi
I have. Okay, nothing depends on n
because I apply it to each individual
one.
And so this is going to allow us to do
super resolution later.
Then what we do is we're going to also
okay so sorry what also we can consider
is that when we project back we're going
to have something of shape again m byd
and what we can do is we can actually
collapse it back to a shape of r. Okay,
so projection, encoding and decoding
work in the same way.
Any questions here?
Okay. And so one thing to note from an
implementation standpoint is actually
the FNO introduces an idea not just
where you have these values f evaluated
at a bunch of points, but it also tells
you what points you're evaluated with.
Okay, so for example, if I wanted to
include more points, okay, I would use a
higher uniform discretization and I'm
going to concatenate this vector with,
you know, the value zero, 0.1, 0.2, so
on and so forth. Okay, just an
implementation note, but you know, it
makes more sense actually to include the
points.
Okay. And so how does super resolution
sort of work? Well, super resolution is
this idea that we're going to train on
say very coarse data. So imagine we have
our data set okay and our data set
essentially is let's say n data
x is equal to 101 okay and so basically
the point of this is that our solver was
only able to solve reasonably fast on a
very coarse grid. Okay, so we have you
know spacings x0 x1
xn and here we would have okay zero 0.01
to one and n is going to be 101. And so
we solved our PTE on this grid. But
we're interested actually in other
points for example that we didn't solve
our PTE on just like we were with our
depotet. And so without retraining we
want to ask can we for example evaluate
our PTE on a grid of say a thousand and
one okay just a 10% or a one magnitude
reduction in the resolution and it turns
out that this type of architecture
allows us to do that with this exact
projection and encoding. And so I'm
going to kind of walk you through an
example of why that works. Okay. So
imagine we trained at this 101 and we're
going to run inference at let's say 401.
So the key is that we're going to apply
this MLP to every single point. Okay, so
we'll have a 401 by D sized output after
our encoding. And this D is chosen by
the user. Okay, it's usually called our,
you know, hidden dimension. You could
think of it as the same thing as
choosing the weight sizes of your neural
network. Okay, then our fora layer is
not going to modify the size of this
this n. So essentially we can take an
fft and we're going to get a spectrum of
401 by d. Okay, from that output we can
consider some truncated number of modes.
Okay, so for example in this case we're
going to choose 16 different
frequencies. Okay, and we're going to
ignore the rest of the modes. We're then
going to get a matrix that looks like
401 x 16 x6. That's going to be our R
matrix. And we can multiply that by the
output of our FFT.
And then we can take the inverse FFT on
the 401x6 object that we get from our
multiplication and we will get another
object that's again 401x 16.
And so the point of this is that we can
then apply our MLP on each one of those
points individually to get an output
shape of 401. Okay. And so the key is
that what is the size of our matrix?
Well, it turns out our matrix R does not
depend on this 401 at all. We just said
it was it was a size of 16. And so it
turns out then okay if that matrix is
only a size of 16 and it's always a size
of 16 for example.
What we can do is we can also evaluate
this same architecture on a thousand
and1 output points you know 10,000 and1
the same exact idea. So the point is
that this architecture is actually what
we call sort of discretization invariant
in a way. Now it's not perfect though
and the reason it's not perfect is what
we talked about last time. So or a
couple slides ago. So the DFT has two
limitations we talked about. First the
periodicity and the second thing we
talked about is uniform spacing in X.
Okay. So we still have to assume that
this for one is a uniform discretization
of our true neural network. So if I want
a specific point, I would have to sort
of know my input function at an
evaluation set that's same as the one I
want to know for my output. Okay, so for
example, we could not let's say have an
input function f discretetized on 201
and ask for an fno output at a
discretization of 401. Okay, because you
see that the the entire architecture
preserves that discretization size of
the input.
This is different actually than donet
where the branch function handles the
discretization of the input but the
trunk function actually allow you to
choose any y-value that you'd like.
Okay.
Okay. So let's go to our favorite
problem that we've been talking about
for two lectures now. So we have here a
transport PTE. I've used this partial t
notation. Okay. We have some initial
condition and we're going to define this
initial condition as the difference
between two negative Gaussians. Right?
And I chose this arbitrary size for my
domain to be minus 2 pi to 2 pi. Okay.
And again we talked about this that this
transport PTE just learns the shift
operator. It's actually extremely
simple, right?
And we want to be interested in okay we
have some initial condition we want to
learn this operator from the initial
condition to some time in the future
here I took it as half a second okay so
this is our problem setup and what I'm
going to present to you is some initial
results when we train with an FNL okay
the first thing is I want to tell you is
that I used a thousand different
training examples so I had my solver
solve this a thousand times with these
randomly uniformly sampled
Okay. And it's important to note that
these basically produce just different
different centers for the uh for the
Gaussian. The second thing is that okay,
I split it into a train test set. 900
were train 100 were test. Used all your
regular tricks. Atom is your
regularizer. So on and so forth. And
what did I get? Well, I got something
that looks like this. So in gray here, I
have the initial condition. Two
Gaussians. And in blue, I actually just
analytically solved the perfect
transport PD.
And in orange, this is what I get for my
neural operator. And so what parameters
did I choose? You might be interested. I
chose 16 modes, four layers. The total
number of parameters something like
24,000. So actually like pretty small
neural network by today's standards. And
I get something that looks pretty
reasonable overall time. Now I want to
make it clear that this the training and
the testing data set discretization was
exactly the same. Okay. And then what I
did is I said okay without retraining
let me try it on say 6x better testing
set
and I pretty much got the same thing. So
I think it would be hard to find a
difference here. If you actually
subtract the errors you'll notice that
the errors are around the magnitude of
minus3. Okay. So 10 the minus 3. And
here though the key value is that I only
trained at a small discretization. And
here I'm basically testing at a 5x
increase. Okay 5 to 6x. And you see okay
this is kind of extremely valuable if
you wanted to use this in an amateurized
PTE solver and you don't want to do like
linear interpolation between your points
because we talked about that last time.
Okay. So here's an example of what super
resolution looks like. And the next
thing I kind of want to show you is when
this thing fails and it fails when I
don't provide for example enough
sampling points with respect to the
number of modes. Okay. So we remember
that the number of modes it has to be
equal to approximately n /2 sampling
points. And remember I told you I use 16
modes and in this case I'm using 16
sampling points for my initial function.
Okay. And so you can imagine we're going
to perform pretty poorly, especially
since most of these sampling points did
not capture the actual change of our
initial condition, right? So this is my
f. And what we get is this sort of
aliasing procedure that is pretty well
known in in PDEs. And the idea here is
on the output, what I've shown you in
green is the true value. And in orange,
we have this sort of oscillation, right?
So we're slowly oscillating. we do try
to capture this peak a little bit well
but then we sort of have this
oscillations between peaks and similarly
again on the edge we have this
oscillation so this is called aliasing
where you're sort of oscillating where
you don't want to be and it's due to the
fact that I just didn't have enough
sampling conditions for my initial
condition okay the same exact problem
will occur if you don't choose enough
modes
and so just to give you a high level
kind of going back we see that We do
have a little bit of this aliasing on
the super resolution as well. Okay, for
the same exact reason, but this time we
didn't have enough number of modes. Now,
it's it's less less involved because
actually we're evaluating it at almost
600 points or a discretization of 0.02.
So, here's just one example. How about
something that's a little bit more
challenging, you know, a little bit more
ump? And so what I have here is a
two-day Nabier Stokes problem that was
actually originally introduced in the
Feno paper in in 2020. Okay. And we've
seen this problem before. I've
simplified it a little bit, but
essentially my domain here x is going to
live on the unit interval from 0 to 1.
I have again the same problem a partial
derivative with respect to t times what
we're going to call this v term. I'll
explain it in a minute. The viscosity
here is is represented by new and we
have this source function G. Okay. And
it turns out that you know I have here
for you exactly what you would want to
want to know but essentially let's
imagine that we're interested in the
same type of problem. Okay. So we're
interested in learning the vorticity. We
know ex for example the velocity field
actually has to satisfy these two
conditions. So the gradient of the
velocity field has to be the braticity
and we have a this or sorry the cross
productduct of the gradient and we have
this sort of dotproduct condition
and we have some fixed external forcing
let's say we know it for whatever
reason. Okay, this is going to describe
our fluid flow or for example our
thermals in the uh in the building.
Okay, and the operator to learn is
actually a little bit more complicated
than the previous learn. We want to say
given the first t not amount of data in
this case it'll be 10 seconds of data we
want to predict the rest of the
trajectory from t kn to capital t okay
and here's what the original fn paper
told us were their results essentially
here what I have is four or five
different neural network architectures
and the relative data where I considered
capital t was just equal to 30 okay and
I picked reasonable parameters
And what we see here is okay, the ResNet
that we talked about earlier really
doesn't do well. Okay. Meanwhile, things
like UNET or TFNET do a little bit
better. Have you guys raise your hand if
you've heard of UNET?
We got one, two people. The idea of UNET
is you basically take your input and
you'll transform the dimension to
something small over and over and over
again through layers and then kind of
transform it back to something big. So
it's kind of almost like an autoenccoder
you could think of it. Okay. And it was
it was a popular approach at the time
for PDS. And then you see okay in red
and blue we have two implementations of
FNL. Okay. For now let's just focus on
the 2D implementation. It works exactly
as you can imagine but except we're
going to use a 2D fastfor transform.
And what we see is we're getting about a
magnitude of difference, maybe half a
magnitude compared to the unit and the
TF. And what does this look like
quantitatively? Well, here's an example
of how many parameters each approach is
taking, the time to train, and then the
relative L2 error on a variety of
different parameter settings. So let's
just consider for example the last one.
Okay, so the point here is the viscosity
is extremely small. So it's actually a
hard tolearn problem. The the larger the
viscosity, the smoother you can think of
your solution. Okay, and we're
interested in learning 20 seconds into
the future. So from 10 to 20 over a grid
of size a thousand. And what we see is
that okay, the FNL gets about half a
percent of magnitude better than the UN
net. you know 0.05 maybe 30% better but
it's using almost two magnitudes better
in terms of the number of parameters
actually. Okay, so here we have, you
know, only 400,000 compared to uh to 25
million. But what you might notice is a
problem in this paper and it was
explicitly pointed out is for some
reason the time per epoch on this small
number of parameters, okay, is much more
than that for the UNET architecture.
Okay, ignore the FNO3D. It's a different
architecture kind of. And can anyone
give me an idea about why the time might
be so much, you know, more per epoch
despite a lot less matrix
multiplication?
Any ideas?
Yeah. So the the question is okay here
we see that the FNO2D has many less
parameters than that of the unit but the
time per epoch for training the FNO is
about two and a half times any ideas why
so I'll give you a hint unit does matrix
multiplication only
is there anything we talked about today
that the FNO
Exactly. So the problem exactly as our
our friend said is that the FFT here
even though it's an N login operation is
still pretty expensive and this was
actually before Torch had their own
implementation and sort of spent some
time you know improving it especially if
you think about it like CUDA is
basically using a gem underneath which
has been
maximized insanely to this point to take
advantage of your cache and these types
of things where the FFT was just kind of
naively implemented. And so that's the
big difference here is that you know you
want to introduce a new architecture it
might work better but if we built
everything around an old architecture
kind of we get this sort of problem. So
for example today if you guys try and
implement a new paper and you want to
present this new scientific machine
learning algorithm and you know your
reviewer number two asks you to compare
with a transformer
it's going to be hard to beat the speed
of flash attention for example okay and
so this is what you can kind of say is
why and there's a precedent for this
okay all right
we talked about an advantage I showed
you two examples where it's at least
working relative to state of the art.
What can we think about are some
downsides?
Actually, okay, let's try this. Since
you guys don't like to talk to me too
much, maybe you could find a friend or a
neighbor, introduce yourself, and talk
for two minutes about what are some
downsides, and then be ready. I'm going
to randomly call on some of you. Okay?
So, feel free to chat with your
neighbor.
this class. You guys don't like to talk.
Okay. So,
you
All right, guys. Sounds good. So, do we
have any volunteers
before we maybe randomly Go ahead. Yes,
sir.
Exactly. Exactly. So, one thing that's
very kind of limiting in our problem is
that we do need a uniform spatial grid.
Okay. Anything else? Anyone else chat?
Maybe over here. Anyone over here have a
have a chat with their neighbors?
Any of you guys talk to do you meet? You
at least meet your neighbor. You know,
it's going to be good. What if they have
a job at Google someday and you want
their their information to ask for a
referral? Yeah, go ahead.
Training data. Yeah, definitely.
Definitely. I mean the same problem with
the deep onet is that we need to use a
solver to sort of build out our our
classical solutions. So yeah great point
maybe one more one more someone in the
back maybe
anyone.
All right
you almost got you got you got saved. I
didn't decide on you. How about How
about behind you? Two two doors back
here.
Anyone over here?
Any This is just a perfect architecture.
Go ahead. Go ahead.
Yeah, great example. What if it's not a
periodic function? That's actually what
we talked about quite a bit over here.
So, just to give you a sense,
Right. So we said okay uniform meshes
it's exactly what we mentioned over
here. One thing we didn't talk about is
that we do need a truncation of these
modes and frequency space. And when we
do this we're not going to maybe learn
all those high frequency modes. So like
we may miss some details of our
function. FFTs are expensive
computationally which we kind of just
saw in the previous slide. And we had a
discussion about that that uniform
target point where with the bonet we
could actually just pick any y out of
the box. Here we need to actually know
our sample f right. Okay. Another thing
that our our friend just told us is that
we need a periodic system. So what
happens when we have boundary conditions
and functions that are not necessarily
periodic? And this is actually a big
problem when it comes to when we're
trying to do sort of super resolution
over time actually. So what do I mean by
that? Well, we saw that for example, we
want to do a mapping from 0 to 10 to 10
to 20, right? Well, what if I want that
mapping from 10 to 20 to be extremely
high resolution? We need to really
consider the effect of those boundary
conditions. And that doesn't really help
us if we're adding padded zeros to the
sides of our function.
Okay, so I'm gonna kind of finish with
some applications and maybe some of
these problems are relevant to things
that you guys are actually working on
today. So, anyone working on weather
modeling? Show of hands. I think there
was we had a couple people in the
beginning of the class working on
weather modeling, but they I guess may
have dropped.
One of the famous kind of things that
was built on FNO is this thing called
forecast net. And the problem with
weather is it's described by these PTEEs
that can be chaotic. Okay? And chaotic
PDEs are very hard to forecast in the
long run because what it means to
actually be chaotic is if I change
something about the PTE a little bit,
the output can change dramatically
later. Okay. And so forecast net
actually was the the first sort of deep
learning model to attempt forecasting
winds on global on our our entire globe
and they have now developed a spherical
fno to kind of handle the geometry but
it's it's actually a pretty interesting
result. So I want to show you for
example wind speed and why why would we
care about wind speed? I think most of
you have flown on a plane before. um you
know turbulence may bother some people
right and that's one thing another thing
is if we want to learn about where
hurricanes are developing over oceans we
really got to care about wind speed so
we can evacuate people and so on and so
forth so here for an example is the
ground truth of wind speeds over the US
okay at a unprecedented three-day lead
time okay so on the right we have three
days and here's what forecastn net
approximately gives view. Okay, it's in
meters/s.
And what we see is, okay, at 18 hours,
we're actually somewhat reasonable. I
mean, the hot spots are identified. You
know, San Diego, the middle of the
country towards Alaska, and say maybe
down south by Texas. At about 36 hours,
we sort of miss how bad the winds are
getting up in the northeast, especially
in the top right corner, but we have
some reasonable representation.
And even at 54 hours, we're still kind
of missing things, especially the
details, but we're getting a highle view
of the currents. And by 72 hours, we're
missing a lot of the detail, right? So
you could see how hard it is, how much
this has changed over 3 days. But you
know, an FNO at least can give you a
highle idea reasonably well. And this
was kind of the first machine learning
model to do this. So before this, people
actually used purely dynamical classical
methods to solve these PTEEs. Okay? And
there's even some still arguments
between the weather community and the
deep learning community about this
problem. But um I thought it was a
pretty cool example.
Another example is in earthquake
detection. Okay, anyone work on seismic
waves, earthquakes, any level?
Guys, I thought you guys were like
physics informed people. So like I
thought physics problems would connect.
Okay. I mean, but anyways. Okay. So
imagine you have a deep net and you're
trying to figure out the epicenter of an
earthquake, which is essentially the
travel time of the earthquake from a
target location, right? And so what I
have here are sort of two different
approaches. Okay? And what we see is
okay this is the you could take this as
the sort of ground truth okay it's a
it's using something called a fast
marching method essentially for seismic
wave problems and it's important to note
that this PTE solution is not
necessarily continuous so for example
you see a jump right here in the
velocity pretty significantly again you
see jumps okay so this is not that easy
of a problem it's not that smooth okay
and so how good does the FNO do well it
depends on where your earthquake
epicenter is. So we can see the
percentage error or this is sort of the
relative percentage error on the right
and what we see is okay the top example
we don't do so well. Okay, but the
bottom two were at least a reasonable
percentage errors are less than a half
almost everywhere and the important
thing about this result was that we
didn't have huge jumps actually where
the the actual model jumps. Okay. And so
that's a kind of an important thing
because you know this continuity that we
talked about in our design doesn't
necessarily
hold in these neural operator
architectures, right? All right. And one
more example is about planning and
robots. Anyone work on robots,
guys? What do you guys work on?
No, like actually like give me something
you guys work on just for next time.
All right. Well, anyway, so this is this
is a result and it's basically about
okay, if we're given this sort of
occupancy map, so everything in yellow
is we'll consider space we can go to.
This is like a map of Paris or New York
I think and everything in blue or purple
is somewhere we can't go to. Okay. And
we're interested in learning let's say a
value function to a goal. Okay. So that
is okay. Imagine my goal is in red. I
want to know the optimal distance to the
goal from say this point this point so
on and so forth around the obstacles.
Okay. And what's kind of cool is that we
developed a neural operator architecture
taking advantage of some ideas from FNO
where we actually can learn this value
function which as a solution to a PTE
and we can learn it at various super
resolutions. So in this case the entire
data set was trained on a a 64x 64
resolution and in the top we have a P
solver almost perfect and in the bottom
we have our R our approach. Okay and the
nice thing here is that this approach
actually works quite well. Now where
you'll actually see the most error if
you subtract them is around the
obstacles which you'd sort of expect
because the boundary there is very
discontinuous. Okay but here's an
example of okay I need to plan in
robotics how can I do that? So you can
see this super resolution idea is super
versatile. There's even a new paper in
computer vision. Anyone computer vision?
Okay, one person. Great. Yeah. So
computer vision where they actually
learn essentially a nerf but with a
using a neural net neural operator
architecture kind of modified. Okay.
Okay.
One thing I've kind of glossed over up
until this point is that my geometry was
square in all those examples. Okay. And
so what happens if it's not square?
Well, if it's not square, there are a
couple approaches we can do. The first
is that we can kind of map it to a
square. That's the simplest possible
thing we can do is map it to a square.
Uh let's define an autoenccoder. And the
question is though if you do this sort
of autoenccoder you kind of maybe will
lose super resolution unless you design
your autoenccoder in a good way. Okay.
The second thing that we kind of have
seen in the community is this domain
agnostic FNL. So this paper was
published I think in 22 at Nurups and
the idea is actually pretty cool. So we
take whatever geometry we have and we
essentially make it a square around it.
Okay. And everywhere that you see is red
here is say an obstacle or something we
don't want to click. And so what we do
is we then modify this kernel function
which we saw in the design of our layer
to just be zero at those points. Okay.
And so if you do this the neural
operator will actually output zero if
you make some adjustments at all of
those points that are not valid for the
geometry. And it's sort of a geometry
wear kernel design.
Another thing that I mentioned up until
this point is we've looked at like two
cases of how to do kernels, but you
could imagine there's a billion
different ways to approximate that
integral. And so here's a bunch more.
Instead of the forier transform, we can
do other transforms as you imagine. So
we could transform to like a wavelet
basis or we could even use like let's
say the lelass transform. Another thing
is that we made this sort of assumption
about a separable neural operator in
deep on net. We could actually design in
a little bit more detail where we have
two sort of functions and this was kind
of done actually before FNO's. Okay, the
next thing we could kind of do is a
graph neural operator. So remember how I
told you we had to approximate this
whole kernel over some set of points.
Why? So why don't we let this
essentially be an adjacency matrix?
Okay, then we could kind of treat this
entire thing as a graph where we're
learning an adjacency matrix. Okay, and
this one doesn't work so well actually.
Can anyone guess why?
I give you an answer. Okay, so the
reason this one doesn't work so well is
we still have to sum over every single
point in our domain. So if we have a 3D
domain, we have 10 billion points to sum
over. Okay? And so you can see this
adjacy matrix can blow up pretty
quickly.
Lastly, I kind of want to leave you with
this tidbit that we looked at a little
bit and that transformers we saw last
time in the deep onet when we introduced
this kernel. Transformers actually are
one instantiation of neural operators
and we can write the attention mechanism
in this way and I give you guys the full
derivation today in section 52 of of a
paper. So all of the things in orange
are paper links. So if you go on Canvas,
you can uh check them out for your own.
Okay. Lastly, I want to give you guys
like a preview to what you're going to
see a little bit later uh in the in the
in the course and we're going to talk a
little bit about where uncertainty
quantification has been done in neural
operators is just a high level. So just
to give you an idea, everything we
looked at today was point predictions.
Okay. So essentially we said okay from f
ofx we want to predict the output of the
value u but instead let's say we want to
give some sort of range or how good our
neural operator is right because in
statistics when we give an output let's
say we do linear regression right you
know especially if you're into
uh something that involves safety you
need a range of of values and usually
you'll give like a 95% confidence
interval so the same thing could be done
for our neural operators Okay. And so
you've seen some of this. For example,
we could do softmax waiting. Kind of
gives you a confidence for each token if
you think about it. Another thing is
that we could do these ensemble methods.
So for example, we train five neural
operators. Take the average or take the
range. And last thing is is something
called a Gaussian process where at every
point instead of outputting just the
value at that point, we estimate the
mean and coariance of a Gaussian at that
point. Okay. And lastly, there's a new
paradigm called conformal prediction.
Not going to talk too much about this. I
think later you'll see it. And so in
neural operators, what have been done?
Well, conformal prediction's been done.
And the idea is it gives you an
uncertainty ball around that point post
hawk. Okay. And so how do people do
this? Well, they train two things. They
train the actual FNO model and then
they'll train a surrogate model that
takes the FNO model and gives you a ball
around each point of an estimate.
Another thing that I talked about is
sort of these ensembled neural operator
designs. So we train five neural
operators and we take the range of their
outputs. And actually this works kind of
quite well. The key is in a smart way,
right? So how can we take, you know, if
we're going to train five neural
operators, how do we actually give a
good confidence bound for those neural
operators? For example, like I said, we
might fit a Gaussian to them or
something like that. Okay? And instead
of just doing five neuro operators, we
could just predict the Gaussian
ourselves. That's been done as well. And
there's kind of a lot more ideas. And
actually, sorry, there's a typo here.
It's not UH, but Yan is actually
teaching the uncertainty quantification.
Okay,
with that, I think most of you are not
so interested in theory, but for those
who are, I want to give you some final
results about what neural operator
theory looks like. It's kind of a rich
and growing field quite a bit. People
are interested in many many questions.
So you can imagine that universal
approximation theorem we talked about.
You can also imagine we're interested in
how much our discretization error is
going to affect our ability to
approximate. Okay. Next thing is how
much data do I need? Right? So these
things are called sample complexity
estimates. So for example, if I have a
hundred different PTEs compared to a
thousand, is there a diminishing law of
returns?
Okay, the next thing is okay, how big
should my neural networks be? How big
does that weight parameter matrix R need
to be? How big does the branch need to
be? It turns out you kind of get this
exponential size, which is ideally not
what you mean. That means is if you want
a lower error, so let's say an accuracy,
a theoretical accuracy of epsilon, you
need at least exponential parameters in
epsilon kind of blowing up, right?
Not great, but the same sort of
complexity estimates you'll actually get
for neural networks.
And here's kind of an example of what
this epsilon error blows up to. So for
example, if I need, you know, one
epsilon error, I don't actually need
that many parameters, but you can see
going to 0.1 and so on, I blow up to
machine precision essentially. Although
now we have trillion parameter models
almost. So maybe this 10 to the 7th is
doable.
Okay. And lastly, I kind of want to
leave you with some open problems and
maybe some of you guys could find some
things that you actually want to work on
because you don't work on anything. But
yeah, so at this point kind of the PTE
world is looking like the following. So
people have these PTE solvers on the
left where they don't have much data but
they use a lot of their knowledge and on
the right where basically pure data and
we're kind of in this battle here
between the two. And so people have
tried combining these sort of ideas in a
neat way. And then people are also
interested in learning the solution to
PTE dynamics, right? So we don't
actually have any data for example at
the top and we're trying to discover
PDS. And these are known as inverse
problems. So this sort of triangle is
where the the world begins and I would
say like even this right side is
starting to become popularized compared
to the left. Another thing that we kind
of talked about and hinted to is
geometries, different boundary
conditions, different architecture
styles.
And one thing I showed you an example of
with the deep net for earthquake
detection was about discontinuities.
But FNO really doesn't work for this
problem actually because you can imagine
your 4A modes are smoothing everything.
And so how do we learn PDEs with
discontinuities is really an open
problem. And lastly, we talked about
different ways we could encode f. So
symbolically
or in the sense of different points. I'm
sure there's better ways. And so it's
sort of a a final open problem.
Actually, we looked into sampling a
little bit in December. So yeah. Okay.
And we'll see you on next lecture about
these objects called pins. I'm sure some
of you have heard of pins. Whether they
work or not, we'll talk about it and and
where where things are going in that
direction. But the key promise I would
give you as pins is you don't need as
much data as say an operator learning
paradigm. Okay? And so yeah, with that,
I'll see you guys next Tuesday.