So today we're going to be talking about
pins, physics informed neural networks.
It's kind of a new class of ways to
solve PTEs and ODEs. And the promise
when pins came out was that they didn't
require data. Okay? So you could learn a
solution to a PTE strictly from
equations. And we'll see it's not so
easy to do that. I think probably many
of you have heard of pins and heard they
don't work. And so we'll talk about a
bunch of engineering tricks today
basically. And these engineering tricks
aren't just useful for pins. Like
they're pretty useful in general
whenever you guys are trying to train
neural networks. Okay. So,
okay. So,
like we were saying, for example, for
Navia Stokes in 3D, we need 10 billion
points. It's going to take quite a few
days on our solver to generate 10
billion points. And so what happens if I
don't have access to a DOE or you know
one of the crazy open AAI compute
clusters right
but typically what you will know for
your phys for your problem is you will
know some governing equations derived
you know in an old textbook of which
it's not fun to read but you can get
through it right and so the question is
can you learn a model a surrogate let's
say with that fast inference time for
your problem just from equations And
that's kind of the the question that was
asked around 2018 now almost almost
can you do this and it turns out you can
talk about how to do that today and so
just to give you guys an idea of where
we're going. So where we've been
recently is in this neural operators,
neural odes, dynamical systems realm
where we had high amounts of data. And
today we're going to go and look at the
opposite end where we have no data but
we have some physical equations. And of
course you could combine these two ideas
to build you know these sort of hybrid
models. But this is kind of where we're
going today and and and we'll talk a
little bit more about what this looks
like.
All right. So let's consider our
transport example. We've been working
with this for a couple weeks now. We
have a derivative in time equals
derivative in space, an initial
condition given by this function g of x
and a boundary condition ders at one,
right? And so what we used to do or what
the paradigm that we kind of claimed up
until this point is that we would use
our expensive PTE solver to generate a
bunch of outputs, right? So we would
have x1 to xn for different times and
we'd have to do this discretization over
a grid. And we showed a couple different
ways to do this. For example, we showed
Oilers's method. We talked about what
RK4 looks like. And we remember the
problem though is that we might not have
access to this compute, right? We don't
have this Oracle PTE solver always for
all our problems. And even if we did
have it, maybe the PTE solver is not
working out of the box. You know, you
could imagine this is a problem. So what
can we do? Well, we're going to
introduce a paradigm, the pin paradigm
today. And with a bunch of engineering
tricks, we can make it work. But there
is one caveat and we'll sort of talk
about this. It's only going to work for
one PTE. So if we change our initial
condition, for example, or change our
boundary condition, or we don't have the
coefficient one here, but we have some
number, we're going to have to retrain
our neural network, which is kind of not
so great. We'll see that in a second.
So, okay. So, the idea of a pin is
really, really simple. What we're going
to do is we're going to let the solution
PTE be given by a neural network
parameterized by theta with positions x
and t. And the goal is to just enforce
that u of theta x oft is equal to u of x
of t. And so, we're going to do this for
example with an MSE loss term, right?
And so in a supervised paradigm right
what we would have done is we would have
said okay we have some solution over
some grid and we can sort of map these
two together. We could take the mean
squared error right and the thing is is
that we kind of hoped for example that
our neural network might be able to give
us some some generalization over an
entire topology. So that is like for
example if we let our neural network be
represented with two inputs x and t it
can give us interpolation over those
points x and t instead of say you know a
linear interpolation or something like
that right and so we saw this paradigm a
little bit with neural operators
although we talked about things like
super resolution and asking a little bit
more of our neural network we're not
going to focus on that here what we're
going to focus on is the fact that we
may not have this you. Okay.
Okay. And so just to give you guys an
idea of of why this paradigm may or may
not make sense. Okay. First of all, we
argued that we could query at any point.
The next thing we could say is that we
could do some sort of outof sample
prediction. This is kind of a a stretch.
I'm not going to tell you this works all
the time. For example, if you're ever
like getting a paper back and you're in
a new field, let's say you're in
weather, okay, and you had some reviewer
and the reviewer is always going to ask
you this question if you're using a
neural network and they're not familiar.
Does it work outside of your training
distribution, right? And the safe answer
to that is no, it does not. Okay? And
typically the reviewer will be okay with
this especially if they're non neural
network but people have still tried to
kind of show that these types of
paradigms will work on X and T outside
of the training distribution.
I will don't want to sell that to you
today but just I have to put it up here
just so you can say it is possible.
Okay. One thing you may do to kind of
handle this is you might have very few
let's say you have long horizons problem
right so t is very large you may have a
very few number of instances where you
solve for that full long horizon and you
can train with those instances as well
as a lot of instances where you solve to
a short horizon right and then you can
ask okay hopefully the neural network
can kind of interpolate that longer sort
of amateurized training data essentially
that's an idea that you can do and and
it kind of works actually if if you do
this sort of parameterization
and then yeah one thing I haven't really
talked about or showed you is that these
things actually work better than some
interpolation solver and this is of
course problem dependent so I can find
some problem with you know shocks or
high oscillation where the linear
interpolation is going to break or even
if you use splines or something like
that it's going to break and maybe a
neural network does a little bit better
it's sort of though not always honest
Right? Because if the problem is very
smooth, the neuronet network could
actually you know for some reason
interject some aliasing which we talked
about last time if there's not enough
sample points and in that case it's
probably better to use some linear
interpolation. Okay. So you can see it
depends a lot on your problem. And then
the last thing is that this sort of
paradigm where we use this neural
network the neural OD and the neural
operators they did have some physics
incorporation compared to like an MLP
right but you know we've spent I don't
know 300 years since Newton working on
calculus and sort of trying to derive
how how these sort of ideas work and we
kind of just ignored that and said let's
replace this with some datadriven
approach. Okay. So, um, you can see
there's a quite a bit of trade-offs for
this idea of, okay, let's let our
solution be a neural network. Um, and
we're going to kind of see, okay, what
that looks like, and then we're going to
see about 50 training tricks to make it
actually work. Okay. All right. So, let
me give you the high level of pins and
then we'll kind of go into some training
tricks. So remember that we talked about
our original transport PTE with some
initial condition and let's say we want
to know it for some future time you know
t equals 0.5 for example. So the way pin
works is we explicitly are going to
model the PTE as parts of our loss
function. Okay. So this first loss
function with some let's say waiting
term lambda 1 is going to be the data
that we have. So imagine we have maybe
one or two examples. Not very many
examples, but we have one or two. Okay,
so that's going to be our our classic
root mean squared error that we saw two
slides ago. Then we're going to add some
new terms, these three on the right. And
these are going to be called the physics
informed terms. Kind of why you took
this class maybe for that hot keyword,
but physics informed. And what does that
mean? Well, it means that we're going to
consider these equations up top here and
we're actually going to encode them as
loss functions, right? So, if u of theta
is our PTE, you might imagine, okay, our
data is our MSE squared term and we
might assume that okay, since we know
that U of theta for any initial
condition should be G, we can encode
this. Okay, and we could code this for
as many X points as we want. For
example, some uniform discretization.
Okay. And so this is just a very simple
idea, but it says, okay, let's penalize
our learn neural network whenever it
doesn't match our initial condition.
Pretty simple. We're going to do the
same thing for the boundary condition.
And actually, we can do this for in this
case, I have a derslay boundary
condition, which just means I'm actually
setting the boundary at the point.
Another option maybe you guys know is a
noman boundary condition and that's
where you're
you're going to set the boundary
condition at the derivative at say one
for example and we'll see that a little
bit later but the same exact idea we're
going to say okay this should be equal
to zero so we're going to put a penalty
on it for its boundary condition and the
last part kind of the most interesting
part is that we can actually enforce
sorry this should be a minus we can
enforce this equation
up top here to actually hold, right? So
we know that u minus ux should equal
zero. Okay. And so down here for
example, if this was a correctly a minus
term, this would be enforcing that
equation. And now you may ask, okay, how
do you do these derivatives? It turns
out, well, we can just run them through
torch because we know how to take
derivatives with respect to our inputs
uh after years of auto differentiation.
And we'll talk a little bit more about
auto differentiation later, but it turns
out these aren't too bad to evaluate.
And so you can see now here we've sort
of encoded the dynamics of our PTE into
our loss function as a sort of soft
constraint, right? And actually it turns
out we don't even need any data. So if
this term for example was zero, we don't
have any data. We could still try to
learn the solution to the PTE based on
the parameters that we have completely
from designing this loss function.
So this is the whole idea of pins. Any
questions? Maybe to stop here. Slow
down. Yes sir.
Okay. We'll we'll get there. We'll get
to an example
actually. So what we're going to do kind
of where the rest of this talk is going
is this is not a hard idea to introduce,
right? like it's pretty straightforward
but it's actually a hard idea to
implement and make work and we'll see
okay our choices of lambda are really
going to matter our neural network
architecture is going to matter how we
train is going to matter so I'm going to
give you a couple ideas there to think
about yeah sir in the back
just a normalization
nothing nothing very particular but if
you think about it like we don't want
our loss function blowing up, right? For
example, then you would get training
instability and then your gradients are
going to blow up and then nothing's
going to work. We'll see how to sort of
choose these lambdas a little bit later.
Um, but for now, you can just treat them
as a as a normalization.
Um, well, what well, in what sense do
you mean diminish it?
um it won't necessarily okay this is it
won't necessarily
it'll keep the gradients reasonably
numbered but the gradients can still
blow up right because these loss terms
can still blow up Okay, so it's kind of
just a normalized way to trade off
different terms essentially. So for
example, if lambda four is 0.9 and the
other three are 0.03 for example,
something like that, then we're really
going to weight this equation term more
than the other ones. That's the whole
idea. Whether or not lambda blows up is
kind of
more a function of the actual loss
terms. and we'll see they'll get large
as you would imagine.
Yeah. But if your training for example
is super unstable, it might be worth
choosing a lower normalization actually
and see if things work. It's sort of
Yeah.
Yeah. Minus minus right here should be a
minus. Yes. Yeah.
The reason is I actually did a different
PTE earlier and so yeah, but this was
the one we've been doing kind of the
whole class. Um so wanted to keep that
in mind. Other questions? Yes sir.
Sorry.
Where's K?
These are the number of points that I'm
going to choose for uh I okay so for
example like I may have picked a un a
grid right. So for example uniform grid
in X might be 10 points 0 0.1.2 0.3 0.
So these K are kind of chosen by the
user essentially however many points you
have and you want to choose. Now these
are called collocation points and we'll
actually talk a lot about how to choose
these points later. Um sort of as well.
Yeah. All great questions though like a
lot of the questions you're asking we're
hopefully answer later. So yeah any
others
everybody gets the idea though hopefully
of introducing sort of these terms to
represent your equations. Okay. Okay.
And so just a brief review. How many of
you have heard of auto differentiation?
I would assume everyone. You probably
used it on your homeworks. Great. Just a
brief review of what it is and where
else kind of things exist. So how do you
compute these derivatives? Just one.
Essentially the way the derivatives work
is you break everything down by a chain
rule into a set of simple operations. So
what do I mean by simple operations?
Add, multiply, sign. typically nothing
more than a binary operation which just
means two inputs one output. Okay. And
then you're going to apply this chain
rule automatically
and the key is that you build this sort
of tensor graph of the chain rule and of
course as you know PyTorch will do all
your derivatives for you. Okay. And so
it's kind of like you know you're taking
some highlevel Michelin star dish and
you're putting things slowly adding
layers of flavor. That's kind of the
decomposition of an auto diff. And it
turns out this isn't the only way to do
this. So kind of to give you guys an
idea, for example, we saw a little bit
of how to do manual differentiation. I
think you've seen in your calculus
class. Numerical differentiation. What
does this mean? This is our finite
difference algorithms. So we approximate
a derivative between two points.
Symbolic differentiation essentially you
have a set of symbols and you know their
derivatives. Kind of very close to
automatic. And then there is one other
type of differentiation that is
available. Um, but
can anyone name what we kind of saw as a
cool way to do gradients? Perhaps you
may know because we talked about it.
So, uh, for the neural OD. So, what do
we do?
kind of yeah exactly so I guess it could
fall under this numerical question but
the idea was we created that adjoint
state right then we made a separate
differential equation to do our back
propagation that's kind of a cool way to
do differentiation actually and I guess
it falls in the numerical category
although it's not so slow because we're
taking advantage of our OD sol okay so
just something to know Okay, back to our
our problem. So let's consider a little
bit challenging of an example. We have
the Schroinger equation. Okay, it lives
in complex domain
and it's nonlinear, right? For example,
we have a squared term here. It has a
diffusion term. So that's this second
spatial derivative here. This diffusion
term kind of you can think of spreads
things out. And we're going to choose
some initial condition given by seeant.
And what we're going to have is two
different boundary conditions now
because we have a second spatial
derivative. So the PD needs to be well
defined.
And what are our boundary conditions?
Well, the first one is actually really
simple. It's a periodic derslay boundary
condition. This means that okay, the
left hand side of our domain has to
equal the right. And the second boundary
condition is that noman boundary
condition we talked about. Basically
saying that the derivatives actually
have to be equal with respect to space.
So classic problem very important in
quantum mechanics. How are we going to
kind of do a simple example for physics
and form loss? Well again we had four
terms. The data term, initial condition,
boundary condition and of course the
dynamics. Okay. And so let's assume we
have n data points supervised. N data is
small, right? Because if we had a ton,
well we could just kind of rely on this
term. Okay, so end date is some small
number. And the first kind of loss that
we talked about is defining this initial
condition loss. And so it's pretty
simple how to do it. What we're going to
do is we're going to choose an L2 loss.
Okay, we're going to say that our neural
network at all time zero for all points
Xi, which is just a set of points I
choose. So K, I am going to choose I'm
going to choose these points. And this
is just a normalization.
Okay, you don't need this necessarily.
And what do I say? Okay, I'm going to
penalize this squared error. Pretty
simple. I'm going to do the same thing
for the boundary terms. I'm going to
have two of them, right? I'm going to
have the first one for the derslay
boundary condition and the second one
for the vanoyman boundary condition.
Okay, exactly the same way I did the
penalties for the last two. I'm going to
choose some points from K1 to K2
representing different time instances.
How I choose these is up to me and we'll
talk about why. And I'm going to
penalize the squared errors and the
spatial derivative errors. Now I am
hiding something from you a little bit
here. These actual boundary errors on
the spatial derivative,
they may require ghost points. So any of
you guys studied PD solvers know what a
ghost point is.
Okay, pretty much no one. They may just
require a trick. Let's just leave it at
that. In practice, you won't notice it,
but under the hood, Torch is doing it.
And if you want more information on
that, come see me later and we'll talk
about it.
Okay. And of course, the equationbased
lost is essentially the same exact thing
we saw before. Okay. We're going to
encode that nasty looking Schroinger
equation. So this was the left hand
side. This term, these two terms were on
the right hand side. You see they're
correctly subtracted now. And
essentially what we're going to do is
penalize this term enforcing the
physics. Right? And so I think pretty
easily you guys could adapt this to your
problem in the same way. The nice thing
of course is that we're using backrop to
handle the gradients. Now does torch
compute second order gradients? Does
anyone know if it's easy to compute this
or not?
Any ideas?
Okay. If I can compute a first order
gradient,
you would agree that I can do that,
right? I would say and then it just
turns out I can do the same thing kind
of with that chain rule idea. Uh
essentially taking the gradient again
and it actually is not super expensive
to compute. It is a little expensive,
but like you'll see the simulations I'll
show you later. They were all run within
an hour on my my Mac. Yeah, you have a
question.
Okay, great. Okay. And so we put it all
together, we get this sort of loss term.
We have four different parts, right? The
data loss, the initial condition, the
boundary condition, and the key is
enforcing our equation.
Second example. All right. And so what
does this look like in practice? Well,
it looks like the following. So what I
have here, okay, is the true solution to
this Schroinger equation. Okay? And what
you see is these sort of black points.
These are my chosen collocation points
which means the chosen points at which I
evaluated XI and TI. Okay. And you see
they they are you know symmetric in this
case but they don't have to be. And here
actually we show an example. This was
the example shown quite a long time ago
in that pin paper of how well the pin is
doing at learning this specific PTE.
Right? And you see it's basically
indistinguishable. L2 errors on the
magnitude of 10 the minus4
which is kind of really good actually.
Okay.
And so let's talk about we now we have
this method. Let's talk about some
advantages some disadvantages. So maybe
we'll do what we did last time. Spend
five or so minutes with your friend next
to you or your neighbor. Introduce
yourself and just talk what advantages
do you see and what disadvantages do you
see. Go ahead.
All right, great.
Let's Any volunteers? Any groups want to
share what they talked about?
Advantages, disadvantages?
How about you guys over in this area? I
saw you guys talking. Any advantage,
disadvantage?
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. So, one
disadvantage our friend shared is that
you have to retrain and we'll we'll look
at that in a second. Um, how about over
here? Did you guys have anything
interesting you guys found?
Advantages maybe. Advantages.
How about you? Any ideas? Yeah. No
advantages. Nothing.
Okay. Well, let me ask you a question
then. What in those four loss terms?
Okay. One of those loss terms I said had
a very small number. Do you remember
which one?
So, in these four loss terms, right, we
had this term, the data loss, an initial
condition, a boundary condition, and an
equation loss. Any ideas which one we
talked about maybe didn't didn't have a
huge huge number maybe in this sum?
One of them doesn't look like the other
three.
Um not quite. So these three are all
over points right from K1, K2, K3. But
this one is over the number of data
solves I have. So if I don't have much
data for my problem, that's kind of a
big advantage of our pins. Okay, so for
example, do we need the data loss?
Another thing is scalability. So we
argued that we could query new points
that is not if our PD changed without
retraining though we talked about
interpolation.
And like I mentioned, the whole point is
that we don't need data, right? So this
we'll see a little bit later for inverse
problems and we'll talk about what an
inverse problem is. Another thing is
that we'll see that there was this sort
of soft regularization that is this can
just be added to any neural network
architecture without changing the neural
network. And we'll see if whether or not
this really works later. Okay. And of
course, for example, we could use a pin
loss when training our neural operator.
All right. And disadvantages. So we
talked about those lambda coefficients
with our friend. And why do they equal
one? Well, it's not so obvious actually
why they should equal one. And it's a
good question and we'll talk about how
to choose them.
Another thing is that we showed that
that second derivative right in our
Schrodinger term requires two gradient
passes essentially which can actually
slow down our our problem if we have a
lot of collocation points. Okay, so that
is if K1, K2, and K3 are really large,
it could be expensive to sort of compute
that derivative.
And we'll see that we can struggle with
discontinuity.
And you might imagine why we would
struggle with discontinuity. It's right.
It's because the only thing we sort of
have to base our our problem off of is
that equation.
And lastly, we have this sort of soft
regularization term which means that it
is possible for our system not to hold
at every point, right? There's no hard
constraints and designing hard
constraint neural networks is actually
kind of an open problem right now.
There's still a lot of architectures
coming out. Um, so yeah, and then kind
of to give you an idea of like okay, can
these be used for your problems in your
research or no? And basically the
question is okay if you have a PTE
that's well defined and you have a
solver or someone spent time figuring
out how to build a solver you should
probably use that solver
but many times you're going to have
things like geometries that are not you
know over zero to one as we've chosen in
this or you'll have obstacles in your
geometry like we talked about last time
with that motion planning problem. Okay.
And so for there pins can be really
useful as sort of an augmentation to
your laws term.
Okay. And so here's the the punchline of
today and I think many of you already
had some intuition about this. Like in
practice and research people claim these
things don't work. And for any PTE that
people actually care about pins don't
work. you know, you'll hear it
especially if you go to some ML
conferences. Okay? And so today I'm
going to tell you about all the tricks
we can do to try and make pins work.
Okay? And so we're going to have to talk
about things like
non-dimensionalization. And we'll give
it through an example of what that looks
like. We actually do need to modify our
architecture, it turns out, to handle
this sort of spectral bias problem we've
been talking about for two lectures now.
And lastly, we're going to have to talk
about a very unique training pipeline to
actually get these to work. So, how do
we pick lambda i? How do we pick our
collocation points? And actually, we'll
even see that if we modify our
optimizer, that is we don't use
something like atom every single time,
we will get some some pretty unique
performance improvements.
Okay. Okay. So, first we're going to
start with this idea of
non-dimensionalization.
Okay.
And so essentially here for example
imagine I have the heat equation. It's a
well-known equation. PTE actually
sometimes has an analytical solution.
And let's assume very very simply we
have zero boundary condition and zero
initial condition. So pretty much the
simplest heat equation. We have a 1D
domain from 0 to capital L and we have
time from 0 to t. And we're going to let
this parameter d be called the
diffusivity coefficient. It's going to
have let's say meters squared over
seconds. Okay, so this describes
essentially imagine I have a heat
source, right? So I took a lighter and I
heated up for example a piece of paper
from the middle and that paper is going
to slowly burn outwards, right? That's
essentially kind of how the heat
equation is describing how we diffuse
over some sort of substance.
All right. And so how do we do
non-dimensionalization? It's actually
really simple. Okay, what we're going to
define are new variables that are called
dimensionless in the sense that we're
going to divide them by the size of the
domain. So we define this x prime and t
prime, which is just x over l and t over
t.
And the nice thing about x prime and t
prime is they now both live in 0 to one.
All right? Because we're not going to go
past l. So this number will never be
larger than one. Okay? And we're always,
of course, going to start at zero. And
similarly, we're not going to go past T.
And so what you might do is you might
recalculate the chain rule for this PTE.
Okay, in terms of our new coordinates,
okay, and we'll get something like this.
Okay, so the derivative with respect to
U with respect to T is equal to 1 / T
times the derivative with respect to T
prime. Okay, and it just turns out,
okay, the d of T prime over T just
satisfies 1 / T. And we can do the same
thing for L and we'll get 1 over L^2.
Okay, for the second derivative. And you
know if your PD is not so simple, you
may have to think about these a little
bit and actually compute the derivatives
yourself.
Okay. And so from here, what we can do
then is we can just plug in our
derivatives and we can rescale this D
star to be dimensionless
by multiplying it by T over L^2. And
remember for example your units for d
star were me squar over seconds. So this
exactly cancels out those sort of units.
And then we get everything nicely
normalized in 0 to one with a
coefficient that will be reasonably
small.
Okay. And so why do we do this? Anyone
have any ideas?
Any reason why this PTE might be easier
to solve than the previous one from a
numerical perspective?
Okay, I'll give you a first hint. So
t is now in 0 to one. Okay. And it turns
out that if we imagine things over zero
to one
rather than over zero to say some really
long capital T. Okay. We can sort of
think of that as a little bit of a a
trick, right? So our solver is sort of
now grid invariant, right? So every
every solver or neural network that we
train can always live on 0ero to one.
It's one trick. A second thing that we
might be able to interested in is this
coefficient is now normalized with
respect to its units. So you can imagine
that if this coefficient was very large
in the beginning okay and the domain is
for example t is not too large but l is
for example large it sort of reduces
this coefficient to something easier to
learn.
Just one little trick it's actually also
done when you're using a classical PTE
solver. So that's where the trick comes
from.
Okay. So this is the first thing that
you can do and I'm going to give you an
example at the end after we present all
of these things about how much each of
these really matters. Okay. Okay. The
second thing we could start thinking
about is our architecture design. And if
we think about a pin loss, one thing
that's really going to matter in our
architecture is what our initial
conditions are going to be. that is what
do we pick the weights theta to be
initially for our neural network. Right?
Because for example, if the weights are
like a really large set of numbers, that
loss function is going to blow up and
we're going to get numerical instability
before we even have a chance to start
learning. Okay? And so it turns out you
have to use Laura initialization.
Anyone's seen this before? You probably
used it before.
Okay. Uh yeah, if you're interested in
it, come see me after class. It's kind
of the standard way that torch will
initialize your neural networks actually
by default. The next thing is that we
want to use smooth activations.
Okay, so you have some problems when you
use RLU with these pins in that that
discontinuity at zero that we talked
about, right? So remember RLU is zero
and then it kind of spikes up at the
point zero is actually going to cause
some problems. And so it turns out
smooth activations are very important.
And lastly, I'm finally going to tell
you what this spectral bias for your
feature approach is going to be. Okay,
so let's talk about it. So spectral bias
we've talked about a few times, but I've
never given you an example. Is this idea
that
classical neuronet networks for example
MLPS will learn for example if you're
mapping a signal to a signal low for
modes of that signal first. Right? So we
know that any function we can decompose
as a set of fora features and those
features are going to have different
modes and the higher oscillation modes
sort of describe essentially how how
kind of the features behave you know
very tight together and the lower modes
sort of describe the general straight
for example the envelope and so here's
an example of a neural network trained
50,000 epox and it's just a very simple
neural network it's just an MLP and we
see that okay for this pretty tricky
function it's just trying to learn the
function. So x maps to sine of x plus
sine of 5x. Okay. And so you get this
sort of general sign form kind of shown
with this black dash. And then the sign
of 5x creates the inner oscillations.
And you see okay if it's at 5x you know
it's going to have a higher 4 a mode.
For example five in this case right?
Because the 4a modes are the number of
oscillations in one period.
And so what we see here is okay if I'm
training my neural network it's first
going to learn the general shape and
then after a large number of epochs
it'll eventually learn that sort of
small features. Okay.
And so can anyone guess why this may
matter for our problem specifically?
That is when we're training pins
why do we think this may be an
interesting thing to care about?
Anyone over here? How about you? You
look excited.
Yeah, exactly. So, our friend said
basically that if you're training a pin
and the loss function has some really
high frequency behavior or oscillation,
especially in the equation, for example,
we're never going to learn it. it's
going to be a little bit too hard to
learn it maybe without some data for
example and that's exactly why we care
and so one of the things that was
introduced almost 10 years ago now in
2015 was forier features okay and the
idea is that we're going to encode the
input locations
through this sort of lifting function
okay and so essentially what we do is we
say okay let's let these set of gamas
survise be a set of lifting functions
that encode this into Forier features
which are essentially cosiness and ss
with a period depending on B. Okay. And
B here in this case is just going to be
a Gaussian sampled. Okay. And so
essentially what I'm going to do is the
following. Right? So so for my sign
function here. Okay. Mapping these X's
values. those are my inputs to my neural
network into let's say the solution of
this function f ofx right the same thing
we're going to happen with our PD we're
going to map those x and t values into a
solution of our pd okay and what
basically this this this idea this paper
is is it says okay instead of just
giving those x of values directly okay
you should give this sort of gamma x ofi
transform all right it's essentially a
feature mapping okay of which I think
you guys are all familiar with and so
the idea is okay we just sort of
parameterize this into frequency space
if you want to know why this sort of
works you could sort of think of the
intuition that it sort of rebalances the
modes of the system so that is when the
neural network is learning and it gets
points x of i it's going to see for
example the long oscillation in a
similar way it sees the high
oscillations there's more reason to this
from a theory standpoint but that's an
idea you can think about if you want to
know more of course I link the famous
paper here which is available on canvas
okay all right and so what other things
that we talked about would be useful
well one of them we said was
initialization
the other thing is that we need to use
smooth activations
and the last thing is that we didn't
really talk about this but the weights
of your neural network should actually
be normalized
okay and it's for the same thing that we
cared about that initialization that is
if our weights start blowing up before
we learn anything before we have enough
iterations we're going to reach
numerical instability and then our
solver is going to break in the learning
process okay so just a little trick
basically
all right any questions here about some
tricks that you may want to try actually
I would start with these things
especially if you wanted to train a pen
Okay, great. Let's keep going. So, the
next thing I'm going to answer your
question about is how to choose those
lambdas. Okay. And one proposal that's
pretty natural and shown to work is to
rewe each lambda by a gradient norm.
Okay. And so what is this going to look
like? It looks like the following. So
for example, my lambda for my data term
and my loss. Okay. I'm going to rewrate
by sort of a normalization of the max
theta. So that is the worst neural
network I'm parameter I'm changing with
respect to the original neural network
some bar lambda. Okay. And what bar
lambda in this case or bar gradient
sorry is going to represent the mean.
Okay. So this is basically a reweing of
how far away I'm changing one of my
parameters compared to how I'm changing
most of them. Okay. for each individual
loss term. Okay, so for example here,
okay, we have the full loss term and
here we just have the data portion. Here
again we have the full loss term but now
we just have the initial condition
portion and so on and so forth. Okay,
and the key is
why we we sort of picked lambda eq equal
to one. You may ask that it's actually
just a choice of pure arbitrary choice.
So I could have picked for example
lambda hat bc equal to one. Okay. Okay.
So again the idea is okay I'm going to
choose the equation term right. So that
is the term that matters that enforces
the actual physics of the PD to be one
arbitrarily. And then based on that term
I'm going to set the ratio of all of the
other terms to how effective they are
compared to that term. Okay? It's
essentially a reweing. So let me put you
through an example. Imagine that for
example my initial condition loss is is
pretty bad. Okay.
And my equation loss is pretty good.
Will lambda be large or small
for the initial condition.
So my initial condition loss is bad.
That means probably this average
gradient is a little bit large. You
would agree. Okay. Because we try to
make a big step correction. Okay. My
initial equation loss I said was good.
So this max theta probably isn't too
humongous. Okay. So what's going to
happen is this lambda IC is going to
become small. Okay. And why is it going
to become small? Well because remember
we talked about in pins we have this
training instability
right where if this loss function blows
up that's why we introduced the
normalization then we're going to run
into numerical issues before we even
start learning. And since my I know my
initial condition loss is large and
therefore its gradient's large. I want
to sort of corroborate that by making
the parameter that multiplies it small
so that whole term isn't too big.
Does it make sense? Okay. So then one
more question for you guys. Imagine the
opposite occurs. So for example,
my equation loss is really small. So I'm
doing really really well on my equation
but or sorry imagine my equation loss is
really large. So I just started
training. I don't know too much about my
PTE but you know the boundary condition
is just zero. It's something very
simple. So I learned that very very
easily. Okay. What would you guys
imagine is the value of this lambda BC?
Would it be large or small? Any takers?
Any
ideas?
All right. Someone random
large.
Why?
Mhm.
Exactly. Or so basically he's saying
this term is going to be close to zero.
This term is going to be large. Okay.
Something large divided by something
close to zero is large. I agree. Let me
ask you, do you notice any problem with
what you just said for deriving these
equations? So, for example, imagine
we're doing really, really well in all
of our loss. We're getting close to
convergence. Do you guys see any
problems here
numerically? So, that is lamb. The BC
term is really good. The IC term is
good. The data term is good. They're all
very close to zero. Anyone see any
issues?
Uh, sure. How about just numerically?
It it is going to cost us something to
compute this for sure. Definitely. But
okay, if if these are really close to
zero, are we going to change our
parameters a lot?
Okay. So, what will be the the norm of
these gradients? Will they be large or
small?
They'd be small. Really small. In fact,
we have to be careful about dividing by
zero here. And so what you might do is
clip it. So you could say that okay,
these values can be no smaller than some
number, right? So we need to be careful
about this um and and for this relative
scaling, but hopefully it gives some
intuition about why we chose it this way
or why one may choose it this way.
And so then another thing that we kind
of consider is that loss functions can
be super noisy. Okay, so for example,
here is our loss function and you see
it's jumping all over the place. And so
what we might not want to do is update
our parameters all over the place. And
the simplest way to kind of fix this is
to use a moving average. Okay, so that
we might take okay, let's take the
average gradient norm over the last 50
steps, for example, and we're going to
update based on a linear equation. very
common for example in time series
analysis.
All right.
The next trick I'm going to kind of show
you is is actually to handle the
temporal dependency of your PTE. So
remember we have a PDE. It's evolving
both in space and time. And it turns out
that well let me give you some
intuition. So imagine that I'm trying to
learn this PTE. Okay. And remember that
that loss function that we described
just encodes a bunch of X points, a
bunch of T points. It doesn't care about
how they're related. It just encodes
them. And so imagine if I try to learn
this PTE and I have a very bad first two
seconds. Do you think my next 4 seconds
will be good?
Probably not, right? Because my first
two were bad. And so the idea of this
whole temporal dependency is basically
you introduce a waiting factor that
depends on time and it decays as time
goes farther. So you need to make sure
you get your earlier points right before
your later points.
And so that's the entire idea of this
sort of temporal dependency trick. So
for example, imagine t is very large
capital t almost 100 right? Then what we
will do is we'll say okay
first we will essentially split the PTE
learning the first one second
okay and we'll say okay we want to value
this 1 second very strongly
and then what we're going to try to do
is then learn the PTE let's say we do
really well in this and we valued it
strongly and we're going to try to learn
the PTE later to 2 seconds and we could
do this over and over and over again
recursively for n seconds Right? And
it's sort of a curriculum learning
approach. So that way we don't actually
have to learn to the full 100 seconds
all at once. One little trick I think
you could have thought of that. The
second thing that we might do is we
might add like I was mentioning a
waiting factor, okay, to the front of
the loss function, say the equation
loss. And this waiting factor is
essentially a factor that decays with
time. Okay, you can think of it as an
exponential that decays with time. Okay.
And so basically it says that remember
we said okay we need to learn the first
second really well before we can learn
the second second. Well it basically
says in my loss function value those
early seconds much more. Just a simple
reweing.
Another trick you can do.
And so like I was saying if early time
residuals are large this w subi is not
going to care about later times. It's
just going to focus on the original
times. And once the early time residuals
shrink, then we can start caring about
later times. It's essentially a
scheduling factor. Yes, sir.
No, but this is all we're all we're
focused on here is the training design.
So for example, you will still have one
MLP for the whole 100 seconds, but for
that 100 seconds, you may you may still
have it, but you'll only focus on the
first second, for example, in the
curriculum design, but it's fully you
fully have an architecture for any X and
T. But there is, for example, you could
think of a design that is recurrent,
right? I mean, you could easily think of
that and and derive it. So the thing
with pins is it's sort of architecture
independent, right? Because we're all
talking about the loss function. We're
talking about how to train. We're not
really focused on the architecture
design. Yeah,
good question. Other questions
make sense? Little trick here.
Okay. All right. Uh the next question is
for whoever asked how do we choose K? I
think it was you, right? Yeah. It turns
out this actually matters a lot. How do
we choose not only K but the X of I's
and T's of eyes that we try to evaluate
our loss at really matters a lot. And
the idea of this paper, okay, is to
essentially focus on those points that
I'm really bad at right now and sample a
lot around them. Okay?
And so, for example, imagine this is my
equation loss. I'm going to represent it
with this residual function let's say.
Okay. So this equation loss is basically
telling me okay here's how well I behave
for the physics not including initial
condition not including boundary
conditions. And so the simplest thing
you might do is uniform sampling right
we agree that's you know pretty basic
and it turns out that uniform sampling
is not really going to work. Okay. And
so what you can do instead is take
advantage of what you know your solution
might look like. Right? So here's a
simple example. So here is my sampling.
So blue, every blue dot you see is a
uniform sample. Okay? And here's a
little bit better sampling on the right
knowing that my PTE has some shock
across this line here. All right? And
you might know this going in from the
initial condition, for example. Okay?
And so the point is that okay on the
left here, it's hard to see because the
the font is bad, but I have 8,000 points
and on the right I actually only have
300 points.
Sorry, let me let me clarify it. So I
have two sampling cases both in the PTE
and on the boundary. So on within the PD
I have 8,000 points and on the boundary
I have 300 points. And here within the
PD I have 5200 points and on the
boundary I have 300. It's hard to read
but you can trust me. So basically
within the PTE I'm sampling much less
over here. And it turns out even with
much less sampling I get identical PTE
solutions. That's the whole point. The
whole point is that you shouldn't sample
naively essentially. Okay? You should
really think about your sampling.
And so what can we do that's more
interesting for the sampling? Well, we
can do this kind of idea of called
adaptive sampling. Okay. And adaptive
sampling, it's really really simple.
Pick the points of which I have high
residuals in my loss term and sample
around those more. Okay. And ignore sort
of the points that I have already I'm
doing well. Okay. So for example, I
might train my pin for n steps on a set
of points. Let's call it S. Okay. Then
what I'm going to do is I'm going to say
from let's say a candidate pool, I'm
going to sample a bunch of points and
see how well I'm doing essentially on
those points in that candidate pool.
That is I'm just going to evaluate my
equation loss. And what I'm going to do
is I'm going to say, okay, let's take
the top m highest points that I did
badly on in my equation loss and I'm
going to add them to my sampling pool
and start training.
Very simple idea. Basically, you
penalize the points that don't do well.
It's called residualbased adaptive
refinement. Some fancy name, but it's a
really simple idea.
All right? And so, you can imagine why
this works, right? The network can
identify regions that are hard because
those are going to consistently be added
back to S.
Okay? And now there's about 50
variations of this since how often do
you resample? How often do you choose to
kind of add points? How many points do
you add? How do you choose this
candidate pool? You can imagine there's
quite a bit of hyperparameter tuning
here.
Okay.
And
the last sort of trick I want to tell
you about before we start going into the
details is here's some examples is
actually your optimizer. So I would
guess 99% of you have never touched
anything other than atom in let's say
torch. Okay, maybe some of you have
played with like SOAP and muon second
order operators. It turns out that for
pins using a second order optimizer
really helps. Okay, and we'll see this
in a minute. So just an idea quick recap
of what I mean by optimizer. So this is
how you update our neural network
weights. Okay, atom works very simply on
first order gradient information. So
it's only estimating for example this
delta theta of L and of course it's
derivative. It builds this two momentum
terms and you can prove that this sort
of design achieves a maximum first order
rate of convergence.
Okay, what is the problem with atom?
Well, it's a little bit noisy, but it's
really really cheap to run. Okay, so you
you know you don't really want to spend
too much time with your optimizer and
it's pretty reasonable. You know, kind
of dominates training for almost all
neural networks.
And what is this second order method?
It's called LBFGS. So L stands for
limited. BFGs are a bunch of names, last
names. Okay? And this comes out of the
optimization community and it's
essentially what we call quasi Newton
method. So a Newton's method just
basically says we're going to use second
order information of our derivative,
right? So this would be the second
derivative of L and of course we're
going to get a matrix, right? Which we
call the hessen.
And essentially what we're going to do
is we're going to approximate this
matrix instead of computing it.
and we'll get something that looks like
this. Okay, where we now have this
hesshen inverse times the gradient and
it turns out this this optimizer will
achieve a faster rate of convergence if
I know my hessen. But the problem is for
a neural network my hesshen is
humongous. Okay, so what I'll do is I'll
say for example I'll store a limited
number of hessins sort of a truncation
and I will essentially identify based on
that. Okay, the point is that okay, yes,
this method is better, but it's
expensive. Super expensive, actually.
And we'll see how much more expensive it
is in a minute. All right, so little bit
of review of optimizers, but the idea is
the following for this optimizer for
pins. So for what we're going to do is
we're going to use atom at first, very
cheap iterations, and we're going to do
it for a while. Essentially what we're
going to do is we're going to get we're
going to treat atom as sort of a warm
start for our BFGs.
Okay. And you see atom we use for almost
10 to 50 steps. We're only going to use
maybe 300 in the example I show you in a
minute for BFGs. And we also need to
search for alpha, but I'm not going to
talk about that too much. Okay. And the
idea is okay, Adam was a warm start. It
got our hash and approximation
reasonable. We do BFGS to our bind. It's
going to be expensive, but we're going
to see huge improvements on learning our
pin. Okay. And so why would you do this?
Well, as you can imagine, since I'm
using a limited BFGS, right, I'm only
using an estimate of my hesshin from my
last 10 updates in the beginning, this
estimate's terrible,
right? And so later, what we're going to
do is we're going to say, okay, let's
use Adam sort of as a warm start. And
this is actually a pretty common idea in
optimization.
All right. And so let me give you a
summary of all the things we talked
about when it comes to thinking about
how to training pins. So we talked about
non-dimensionalization.
We talked about using a specific
initialization, specific activation,
factorizing our weights, normalizing
them. We talked about forear encoding
loss balancing using this curriculum
approach for the time dependency and two
different optimizer schemes.
We also talked about how to pick our
collocation points. Okay? And now do you
guys see why people say these things are
hard to train, right? I mean, this is,
you know, I talked about eight different
things here that you need to think about
before you start training. So these
things don't really work out of the box
as you can imagine. Okay? And so at
minimum you're getting four plus you
might have 30 more hyperparameters.
Okay?
All right. So, let me kind of show you
the effect of each one of these things
and you can judge whether or not we
needed each one. All right. So, they're
going to build on each other. So, this
is a classic pin benchmark. It's a it's
a burgers equation which basically
generates a shock used to describe
earthquakes. And the point is that okay,
we have some action term here. The key
is that okay when this new is small
essentially okay we get that super
strong shock it becomes hard when new is
small you can imagine okay it's just
it's just a PT we want to learn going to
be our benchmark example right and
here's what it looks like so here's for
example our initial condition and here's
how we sort of evolve on time as a heat
map and here are various snapshots right
so at t equals 0 we have a sine wave one
period essentially normalized to minus1
to one Right? And then slowly we sort of
come into this discontinuous shock at
zero.
This is a true solution, you know, from
OPD.
And here's what happens when I try to
train a pin to learn this problem over
time. Okay, so if I just try to train a
pin out of the box, imagine I'm just
using an MLP, very simple network, you
know, 100,000 parameters, nothing crazy.
I get an L2 error that's basically
useless. and I get essentially if the
true solution is in black here, I get
what's kind of happening in purple.
Okay, so the shock is not in the right
place at all. It's clearly to the left.
And even over here, it's clearly to the
left. Okay, and you can see though it's
pretty fast. Takes 78 seconds to train
on this laptop. Okay, trained it right
before I came here.
Meanwhile, if I add the lambda balancing
using that gradient approach where I
take the maximum norms, okay, I don't
actually add too much computation time
two seconds, but I reduced my L2 error
significantly, you know, almost over
half almost three three times.
The next thing I tried was each one of
these are additive. So, this includes
the lambda balancing. I tried adding
that causal waiting. Okay, so that
epsilon I term in the loss function and
that actually adds quite a bit of time
fortunately um which is a little bit
surprising to me. I didn't understand
why but it added some time
and it improved very slightly. Okay,
the next thing I did was I said, "Okay,
let me try and add that adaptive
reweing." Okay, where I repick new
collocation points and I add them every,
you know, I think it was every 2,000
epochs. These are about 10,000 epochs
each. We'll see in a second exactly how
many there are. And I ended up with
3,400. So, I added 1,400 more
collocation points based on the highest
residuals. And I got pretty good
improvement, right?
But okay, you can imagine these training
times are equivalent, right? Just due to
warm start or whatever on the laptop.
And lastly, I said, okay, let me take
the output of this and add 300 steps of
the second order optimizer.
And what happens is I actually get
almost three magnitudes improvement. Two
magnitudes improvement. Okay? And I
didn't actually end up using as many
collocation points because we'll see I
train this, okay, for less time than
this one. You may ask why less and
that's why. All right, so it turns out
the second order optimizer really
matters.
Okay, and this will be hard to see, but
let me just walk you through it. So
here's the ground truth. Okay, here's
what the output looks like of the naive.
Here's after lambda rebalancing. Here's
after causal. This is sort of the error.
Here's after that residual. And here's
what happens after I use the second
order optimization. So you see these are
all on the same scale on the bottom. So
you see that on that scale I see no
error compared to the scale earlier,
right? Of course, there is still error
here, but it's hidden by the scale.
And here's actually what our loss
functions look like for each term. Okay,
I sorry I trained a 1500 epoch. And you
see they're very noisy. They're what I
would consider pretty gross to identify.
Um so here's each one. This is the
total. This is that equation loss,
initial condition, and boundary. Okay, I
had no data. no data for this problem.
But I want you to notice this little
green line here where we blow up. This
is at 10,000 epochs. I started using
that second order optimizer. And you can
see that basically it outperforms
everything. I think I only run 200 more
bucks.
When it comes to pins, the key is that
we have an implicit soft constraint.
That is, we're adding things to the
loss. Okay? And it turns out in many
cases we actually care about hard
constraints. So for example, you have a
robot and you really care about safety.
This robot cannot hit a person no matter
what happens. And how do you guarantee
that happens? A soft constraint doesn't
guarantee it. It certainly doesn't.
Right? So what you might introduce is a
safety filter for example. So in our
realm of PTEES, one way to introduce for
example a hard constraint is to modify
the architecture a little bit. And so
imagine I want to bake in an initial
condition and a boundary condition. So
what I might do is I might define my
neural network architecture as the
following. Right? So I have my initial
condition G and then time times some
neural network. Yeah, I can
differentiate through this. And when T
equals Z, okay, my estimate for my PD
will always be G, right?
So it kind of baked in that hard
constraint naturally. And this is kind
of a new sort of growing field. I
actually talked with one of your
classmates, he's in the back about
hardnet, another idea here about baking
in constraints. Okay. And so it turns
out pins are a little bit the advantage
of using a soft constraint is also its
disadvantage. So the advantage is I
don't need to re redo my architecture.
The disadvantage is that I don't get
guarantees all the time.
All right. Okay. So let's talk about
inverse problems. I promised you that we
would get to them by the end of today.
We have five minutes left. So imagine
you have some low amount of data and you
have K sensor measurements and you want
to know the PTE from those measurements.
So you have an earthquake, you measured
a bunch of signals and you want to re uh
reconstruct the earthquake. So what
might you do? You might for example
define something that looks like this.
Okay, where you added those learnable
parameters in. So remember we just
talked about this idea, right? And so we
say okay here's my sort of learnable
parameters.
Okay. And so for example, many places
earthquake MRI acoustic images. Okay.
And so here here's an example of where
this may happen in GPU design. So why do
I care about the Navier Stokes equations
in GPU design? Well, for example, I have
some chip here and I care about how the
air flows over the chip. So it keeps it
cool. And air flow is described by
Navier Stokes. But I won't have for
example sensor measurements anywhere. I
have sensor measurements only at these
green arrows. Okay. But I need to know
the temperature field everywhere because
I need to make sure my plastic doesn't
melt or whatever in my GPU, right? Okay.
And so how does this work? Well, let's
consider this reconstruction from our
pin. Uh on the left is the the true
values, okay? And various constants we
might want to know. And on the right is
our pin estimate of those those values.
Okay? And so, for example, here I'm
interested in the theta parameter. It's
just a parameter. Let's let's just, you
know, we could talk about what each of
these mean, but we have five minutes.
So, let's trust me that these are the
important parameters you would care
about. And you see, okay, it does pretty
well. It's a little bit sharper of a
tail. It doesn't sort of capture this uh
this little handoff.
The pin end for the U parameter actually
does pretty well. Though it misses the
sort of inflection here, but it does
capture this one on the corner. And
likewise here, we sort of miss this
inner inflection.
And down here, we actually do pretty
poorly. Okay, you see the pin kind of
doesn't capture the airflow physics at
all. For example, of the pressure. So P
is pressure, you could imagine. So we're
really missing the pressure here. So you
can see this pin kind of works. Okay,
I want to give you another example and
this is in imaging for MRIs. Okay,
imagine I have an an flowing through an
artery. Okay, and I can measure it at a
bunch of points. For example, I can
measure it here and I want to know how
this blood splits across these two
artery this across this branch. And
let's say I can measure the velocity
here and here. Okay. And I want to know
the velocity and pressure along the
whole artery. You could imagine why you
would want to know this from a
reconstruction standpoint. For example,
imagine you have a small tear here,
right? And then your blood pressure is
going to change and we need to be able
to detect that, right? And so here's the
idea. Okay, essentially everything in
blue I have, okay, are collocation
points. Red is where I can evaluate my
velocity data, okay? and black. Let's
say I can evaluate my pressure data. It
says area but you could think of it as
pressure. So I can evaluate these two
things and I want to know where it is at
this junction. That is I want to know if
I have a tear here. All right.
And you could see okay here they
consider a couple different cases of of
where the data is. All right. But here
is actually the reconstruction at the
green case for both pressure and my
velocity. And you see it's almost
perfect. Okay. except for a little bit
of jumps here that we miss. You can see
on both cases. Okay, we're missing some
jumps,
but it's pretty good. All right, so you
can for example learn a pin for
reconstructing this inverse problem.
And so with that, some future
directions. Training is still not easy.
We talked about those hybrid models and
next time we'll kind of talk about a
different paradigm in foundation models.